const { Builder, By, Key, until } = require("selenium-webdriver");
const ObjectsToCsv = require("objects-to-csv");
(async function example() {
  let driver = await new Builder().forBrowser("firefox").build();
  const endPointList = [
    "https://currentaffairs.anujjindal.in/30th-june-2021-daily-news/",
    "https://currentaffairs.anujjindal.in/29th-june-2021-daily-news/",
    "https://currentaffairs.anujjindal.in/28th-june-2021-daily-news/",
    "https://currentaffairs.anujjindal.in/26th-and-27th-june-2021-daily-news/",
    "https://currentaffairs.anujjindal.in/25th-june-2021-daily-news/",
    "https://currentaffairs.anujjindal.in/24th-june-2021-daily-news/",
    "https://currentaffairs.anujjindal.in/23rd-june-2021-daily-news/",
    "https://currentaffairs.anujjindal.in/22nd-june-2021-daily-news/",
    "https://currentaffairs.anujjindal.in/21st-june-2021-daily-news/",
    "https://currentaffairs.anujjindal.in/19th-and-20th-june-2021-daily-news/",
    "https://currentaffairs.anujjindal.in/18th-june-2021-daily-news/",
    "https://currentaffairs.anujjindal.in/17th-june-2021-daily-news/",
    "https://currentaffairs.anujjindal.in/15th-and-16th-june-2021-daily-news/",
    "https://currentaffairs.anujjindal.in/14th-june-2021-daily-news/",
    "https://currentaffairs.anujjindal.in/12th-and-13th-june-2021-daily-news/",
    "https://currentaffairs.anujjindal.in/11th-june-2021-daily-news/",
    "https://currentaffairs.anujjindal.in/10th-june-2021-daily-news/",
    "https://currentaffairs.anujjindal.in/09th-june-2021-daily-news/",
    "https://currentaffairs.anujjindal.in/08th-june-2021-daily-news/",
    "https://currentaffairs.anujjindal.in/06th-and-07th-june-2021-daily-news/",
    "https://currentaffairs.anujjindal.in/05th-june-2021-daily-news/",
    "https://currentaffairs.anujjindal.in/04th-june-2021-daily-news/",
    "https://currentaffairs.anujjindal.in/03rd-june-2021-daily-news/",
    "https://currentaffairs.anujjindal.in/02nd-june-2021-daily-news/",
    "https://currentaffairs.anujjindal.in/1st-june-2021-daily-news/",
    "https://currentaffairs.anujjindal.in/30th-and-31st-may-2021-daily-news/",
    "https://currentaffairs.anujjindal.in/29th-may-2021-daily-news/",
    "https://currentaffairs.anujjindal.in/27th-and-28th-may-2021-daily-news/",
    "https://currentaffairs.anujjindal.in/26th-may-2021-daily-news/",
    "https://currentaffairs.anujjindal.in/25th-may-2021-daily-news/",
    "https://currentaffairs.anujjindal.in/23rd-and-24th-may-2021-daily-news/",
    "https://currentaffairs.anujjindal.in/22nd-may-2021-daily-news/",
    "https://currentaffairs.anujjindal.in/21st-may-2021-daily-news/",
    "https://currentaffairs.anujjindal.in/20th-may-2021-daily-news/",
    "https://currentaffairs.anujjindal.in/19th-may-2021-daily-news/",
    "https://currentaffairs.anujjindal.in/18th-may-2021-daily-news/",
    "https://currentaffairs.anujjindal.in/16th-and-17th-may-2021-daily-news/",
    "https://currentaffairs.anujjindal.in/15th-may-2021-daily-news/",
    "https://currentaffairs.anujjindal.in/14th-may-2021-daily-news/",
    "https://currentaffairs.anujjindal.in/13th-may-2021-daily-news/",
    "https://currentaffairs.anujjindal.in/12th-may-2021-daily-news/",
    "https://currentaffairs.anujjindal.in/11th-may-2021-daily-news/",
    "https://currentaffairs.anujjindal.in/09th-and-10th-may-2021-daily-news/",
    "https://currentaffairs.anujjindal.in/08th-may-2021-daily-news/",
    "https://currentaffairs.anujjindal.in/07th-may-2021-daily-news/",
    "https://currentaffairs.anujjindal.in/06th-may-2021-daily-news/",
    "https://currentaffairs.anujjindal.in/5th-may-2021-daily-news/",
    "https://currentaffairs.anujjindal.in/04th-may-2021-daily-news/",
    "https://currentaffairs.anujjindal.in/03rd-may-2021-daily-news/",
    "https://currentaffairs.anujjindal.in/01st-and-02nd-may-2021-daily-news/",
    "https://currentaffairs.anujjindal.in/30th-april-2021-daily-news/",
    "https://currentaffairs.anujjindal.in/29th-april-2021-daily-news/",
    "https://currentaffairs.anujjindal.in/28th-april-2021-daily-news/",
    "https://currentaffairs.anujjindal.in/27th-april-2021-daily-news/",
    "https://currentaffairs.anujjindal.in/26th-april-2021-daily-news/",
    "https://currentaffairs.anujjindal.in/25th-april-2021-daily-news/",
    "https://currentaffairs.anujjindal.in/24th-april-2021-daily-news/",
    "https://currentaffairs.anujjindal.in/23rd-april-2021-daily-news/",
    "https://currentaffairs.anujjindal.in/22nd-april2021-daily-news/",
    "https://currentaffairs.anujjindal.in/21st-april-2021-daily-news/",
    "https://currentaffairs.anujjindal.in/30th-june-2021-daily-news/#Quiz",
    "https://currentaffairs.anujjindal.in/29th-june-2021-daily-news/#Quiz",
    "https://currentaffairs.anujjindal.in/28th-june-2021-daily-news/#Quiz",
    "https://currentaffairs.anujjindal.in/26th-and-27th-june-2021-daily-news/#Quiz",
    "https://currentaffairs.anujjindal.in/25th-june-2021-daily-news/#Quiz",
    "https://currentaffairs.anujjindal.in/24th-june-2021-daily-news/#Quiz",
    "https://currentaffairs.anujjindal.in/23rd-june-2021-daily-news/#Quiz",
    "https://currentaffairs.anujjindal.in/22nd-june-2021-daily-news/#Quiz",
    "https://currentaffairs.anujjindal.in/21st-june-2021-daily-news/#Quiz",
    "https://currentaffairs.anujjindal.in/19th-and-20th-june-2021-daily-news/#Quiz",
    "https://currentaffairs.anujjindal.in/18th-june-2021-daily-news/#Quiz",
    "https://currentaffairs.anujjindal.in/17th-june-2021-daily-news/#Quiz",
    "https://currentaffairs.anujjindal.in/15th-and-16th-june-2021-daily-news/#Quiz",
    "https://currentaffairs.anujjindal.in/14th-june-2021-daily-news/#Quiz",
    "https://currentaffairs.anujjindal.in/12th-and-13th-june-2021-daily-news/#Quiz",
    "https://currentaffairs.anujjindal.in/11th-june-2021-daily-news/#Quiz",
    "https://currentaffairs.anujjindal.in/10th-june-2021-daily-news/#Quiz",
    "https://currentaffairs.anujjindal.in/09th-june-2021-daily-news/#Quiz",
    "https://currentaffairs.anujjindal.in/08th-june-2021-daily-news/#Quiz",
    "https://currentaffairs.anujjindal.in/06th-and-07th-june-2021-daily-news/#Quiz",
    "https://currentaffairs.anujjindal.in/05th-june-2021-daily-news/#Quiz",
    "https://currentaffairs.anujjindal.in/04th-june-2021-daily-news/#Quiz",
    "https://currentaffairs.anujjindal.in/03rd-june-2021-daily-news/#Quiz",
    "https://currentaffairs.anujjindal.in/02nd-june-2021-daily-news/#Quiz",
    "https://currentaffairs.anujjindal.in/1st-june-2021-daily-news/#Quiz",
    "https://currentaffairs.anujjindal.in/30th-and-31st-may-2021-daily-news/#Quiz",
    "https://currentaffairs.anujjindal.in/29th-may-2021-daily-news/#Quiz",
    "https://currentaffairs.anujjindal.in/27th-and-28th-may-2021-daily-news/#Quiz",
    "https://currentaffairs.anujjindal.in/26th-may-2021-daily-news/#Quiz",
    "https://currentaffairs.anujjindal.in/25th-may-2021-daily-news/#Quiz",
    "https://currentaffairs.anujjindal.in/23rd-and-24th-may-2021-daily-news/#Quiz",
    "https://currentaffairs.anujjindal.in/22nd-may-2021-daily-news/#Quiz",
    "https://currentaffairs.anujjindal.in/21st-may-2021-daily-news/#Quiz",
    "https://currentaffairs.anujjindal.in/20th-may-2021-daily-news/#Quiz",
    "https://currentaffairs.anujjindal.in/19th-may-2021-daily-news/#Quiz",
    "https://currentaffairs.anujjindal.in/18th-may-2021-daily-news/#Quiz",
    "https://currentaffairs.anujjindal.in/16th-and-17th-may-2021-daily-news/#Quiz",
    "https://currentaffairs.anujjindal.in/15th-may-2021-daily-news/#Quiz",
    "https://currentaffairs.anujjindal.in/14th-may-2021-daily-news/#Quiz",
    "https://currentaffairs.anujjindal.in/13th-may-2021-daily-news/#Quiz",
    "https://currentaffairs.anujjindal.in/12th-may-2021-daily-news/#Quiz",
    "https://currentaffairs.anujjindal.in/11th-may-2021-daily-news/#Quiz",
    "https://currentaffairs.anujjindal.in/09th-and-10th-may-2021-daily-news/#Quiz",
    "https://currentaffairs.anujjindal.in/08th-may-2021-daily-news/#Quiz",
    "https://currentaffairs.anujjindal.in/07th-may-2021-daily-news/#Quiz",
    "https://currentaffairs.anujjindal.in/06th-may-2021-daily-news/#Quiz",
    "https://currentaffairs.anujjindal.in/5th-may-2021-daily-news/#Quiz",
    "https://currentaffairs.anujjindal.in/04th-may-2021-daily-news/#Quiz",
    "https://currentaffairs.anujjindal.in/03rd-may-2021-daily-news/#Quiz",
    "https://currentaffairs.anujjindal.in/01st-and-02nd-may-2021-daily-news/#Quiz",
    "https://currentaffairs.anujjindal.in/30th-april-2021-daily-news/",
    "https://currentaffairs.anujjindal.in/29th-april-2021-daily-news/",
    "https://currentaffairs.anujjindal.in/28th-april-2021-daily-news/",
    "https://currentaffairs.anujjindal.in/27th-april-2021-daily-news/",
    "https://currentaffairs.anujjindal.in/26th-april-2021-daily-news/",
    "https://currentaffairs.anujjindal.in/25th-april-2021-daily-news/",
    "https://currentaffairs.anujjindal.in/24th-april-2021-daily-news/",
    "https://currentaffairs.anujjindal.in/23rd-april-2021-daily-news/",
    "https://currentaffairs.anujjindal.in/22nd-april2021-daily-news/",
    "https://currentaffairs.anujjindal.in/21st-april-2021-daily-news/",
    "https://currentaffairs.anujjindal.in/09th-and-10th-june-2021-daily-news/",
    "https://currentaffairs.anujjindal.in/09th-and-10th-june-2021-daily-news/#rbi",
  ];
  const arr = [];
  // endPointList.length = 2;
  var c = 0;
  for (const endPoint of endPointList) {
    c++;
    console.log(c / endPointList.length);
    try {
      await driver.get(endPoint);
      let btn;
      await driver
        .wait(
          until.elementLocated(By.className("qsm-btn qsm-submit-btn qmn_btn"))
        )
        .then((el) => {
          btn = el;
        });

      if (!btn) throw new Error("Button not found");
      else btn.click();

      let allQuestions;
      await driver
        .wait(
          until.elementsLocated(By.className("qmn_question_answer_incorrect"))
        )
        .then((el) => {
          allQuestions = el;
        });

      let allCorrectAnswer;
      await driver
        .wait(until.elementsLocated(By.className("qsm-text-correct-option")))
        .then((el) => {
          allCorrectAnswer = el;
        });

      for (let index = 0; index < allQuestions.length; index++) {
        const question = allQuestions[index];
        const solutionEl = allCorrectAnswer[index];
        const questionInnerText = await question.getAttribute("innerText");
        const solutionInnerText = await solutionEl.getAttribute("innerText");
        const tt = {
          question: questionInnerText.split("\n\n")[0],
          a: questionInnerText.split("\n\n")[1].split("\n")[0],
          b: questionInnerText.split("\n\n")[1].split("\n")[1],
          c: questionInnerText.split("\n\n")[1].split("\n")[2],
          d: questionInnerText.split("\n\n")[1].split("\n")[3],
          e: questionInnerText.split("\n\n")[1].split("\n")[4],
          answer: solutionInnerText.replace(/\n/g, ""),
        };
        arr.push(tt);
        // console.log(tt);
      }
    } catch {
      continue;
    } finally {
      // await driver.quit();
    }
  }
  const csv = new ObjectsToCsv(arr);
  await csv.toDisk("./list.csv");
})();

(function () {
  function buildQuiz() {
    // variable to store the HTML output
    const output = [];

    // for each question...
    myQuestions.forEach((currentQuestion, questionNumber) => {
      // variable to store the list of possible answers
      const answers = [];

      // and for each available answer...
      for (letter in currentQuestion.answers) {
        // ...add an HTML radio button
        answers.push(
          `<label>
          <input type="radio" name="question${questionNumber}" value="${letter}">
          ${letter} :
          ${currentQuestion.answers[letter]}
        </label>`
        );
      }

      // add this question and its answers to the output
      output.push(
        `<div class="question"> ${currentQuestion.question} </div>
      <div class="answers"> ${answers.join("")} </div>`
      );
    });

    // finally combine our output list into one string of HTML and put it on the page
    quizContainer.innerHTML = output.join("");
  }

  function showResults() {
    // gather answer containers from our quiz
    const answerContainers = quizContainer.querySelectorAll(".answers");

    // keep track of user's answers
    let numCorrect = 0;

    // for each question...
    myQuestions.forEach((currentQuestion, questionNumber) => {
      // find selected answer
      const answerContainer = answerContainers[questionNumber];
      const selector = `input[name=question${questionNumber}]:checked`;
      const userAnswer = (answerContainer.querySelector(selector) || {}).value;

      // if answer is correct
      if (userAnswer === currentQuestion.correctAnswer) {
        // add to the number of correct answers
        numCorrect++;

        // color the answers green
        answerContainers[questionNumber].style.color = "lightgreen";
      }
      // if answer is wrong or blank
      else {
        // color the answers red
        answerContainers[questionNumber].style.color = "red";
      }
    });

    // show number of correct answers out of total
    resultsContainer.innerHTML = `${numCorrect} out of ${myQuestions.length}`;
  }

  function shuffle(array) {
    array.sort(() => Math.random() - 0.5);
  }
  const allQ = [
    {
      question:
        "Q.1) Where has Asia’s longest High-Speed Track (11.3 km) for vehicles’ testing – named as NATRAX (National Automotive Test Tracks) –been inaugurated?",
      a: "[a] Madhya Pradesh",
      b: "[b] Karnataka",
      c: "[c] Delhi",
      d: "[d] Uttar Pradesh",
      e: "[e] Gujarat",
      answer: "[a] Madhya Pradesh",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.2) Which state has launched a first-of-its-kind initiative - Chief Minister Dalit Empowerment Programme - to provide financial assistance of Rs 10 lakh to the eligible Dalit beneficiaries?",
      a: "[a] Karnataka",
      b: "[b] Tamil Nadu",
      c: "[c] Telangana",
      d: "[d] Andhra Pradesh",
      e: "[e] Odisha",
      answer: "[c] Telangana",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.3) Where did the G-20 Foreign Ministers meeting 2021 take place?",
      a: "[a] Venice",
      b: "[b] Milan",
      c: "[c] Naples",
      d: "[d] Bologna",
      e: "[e] Matera",
      answer: "[e] Matera",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.4) What is India’s rank in the Global Cybersecurity Index (GCI) 2020?",
      a: "[a] 10th",
      b: "[b] 55th",
      c: "[c] 87th",
      d: "[d] 63rd",
      e: "[e] 100th",
      answer: "[a] 10th",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.5) How much is the basic customs duty on crude palm oil in India?",
      a: "[a] 20%",
      b: "[b] 10%",
      c: "[c] 5%",
      d: "[d] 15%",
      e: "[e] 25%",
      answer: "[b] 10%",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.6) Who has been appointed as the US Charge’d Affairs in India?",
      a: "[a] Anil Yadav",
      b: "[b] B N Bhaskar",
      c: "[c] Atul Keshap",
      d: "[d] Binod Kumar",
      e: "[e] Astik Sinha",
      answer: "[c] Atul Keshap",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.7) When is the International Day of the Tropics observed?",
      a: "[a] June 29",
      b: "[b] June 20",
      c: "[c] June 18",
      d: "[d] June 13",
      e: "[e] June 11",
      answer: "[a] June 29",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.8) Which country does Sydney McLaughlin belong to?",
      a: "[a] Croatia",
      b: "[b] Australia",
      c: "[c] Poland",
      d: "[d] America",
      e: "[e] Serbia",
      answer: "[d] America",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.9) Who has made India's first ever entry to Olympics with 'A' qualification in swimming?",
      a: "[a] Gaurav Shukla",
      b: "[b] Suraj Prakash Sharma",
      c: "[c] Anil Yadav",
      d: "[d] Sajan Prakash",
      e: "[e] Sandeep Kumar",
      answer: "[d] Sajan Prakash",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.10) Who is the world number one archer at present in women’s category?",
      a: "[a] Dola Banerjee",
      b: "[b] Bombayla Devi Laishram",
      c: "[c] Chekrovolu Swuro",
      d: "[d] Deepika Kumari",
      e: "[e] Laxmi Rani Majhi",
      answer: "[d] Deepika Kumari",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.1) Where is Hemis Festival celebrated in India?",
      a: "[a] Assam",
      b: "[b] Tripura",
      c: "[c] Odisha",
      d: "[d] Ladakh",
      e: "[e] Nagaland",
      answer: "[d] Ladakh",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.2) Which of the following institution has partnered with Global Alliance for Mass Entrepreneurship (GAME) to help MSMEs address their challenges that arose during the pandemic?",
      a: "[a] NABARD",
      b: "[b] SIDBI",
      c: "[c] State Bank of India",
      d: "[d] Yes Bank",
      e: "[e] Ujjivan Small Finance Bank Limited",
      answer: "[b] SIDBI",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.3) Which company has invested in Instamojo for empowering millions of MSMEs and gig workers by helping them to digitize and set up online stores, digital payment acceptance infrastructure and reach out to customers, even during the pandemic?",
      a: "[a] Mastercard",
      b: "[b] Amazon",
      c: "[c] Flipkart",
      d: "[d] Google",
      e: "[e] Twitter",
      answer: "[a] Mastercard",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.4) In which state has World Bank launched SALT program?",
      a: "[a] Maharashtra",
      b: "[b] Gujarat",
      c: "[c] Andhra Pradesh",
      d: "[d] Tamil Nadu",
      e: "[e] Telangana",
      answer: "[c] Andhra Pradesh",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.5) Who has been appointed as the chairman of National Dairy Development Board?",
      a: "[a] Ashish Jaiswal",
      b: "[b] Sumit Verma",
      c: "[c] Sachin Vashisth",
      d: "[d] Vinita Sinha",
      e: "[e] Meenesh Shah",
      answer: "[e] Meenesh Shah",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.6) When was the Central Vigilance Commission established?",
      a: "[a] 1970",
      b: "[b] 1964",
      c: "[c] 1950",
      d: "[d] 1999",
      e: "[e] 1997",
      answer: "[b] 1964",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.7) Which airport from India has received Airport Council International’s (ACI) Roll of Excellence 2021?",
      a: "[a] Indira Gandhi International Airport",
      b: "[b] Chhatrapati Shivaji Maharaj International Airport",
      c: "[c] Kempegowda International Airport",
      d: "[d] Cochin International Airport Ltd",
      e: "[e] Netaji Subhash Chandra Bose International Airport",
      answer: "[d] Cochin International Airport Ltd",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.8) Who is the author of “Growing Up Biden: A Memoir”?",
      a: "[a] Christian Burno",
      b: "[b] Nandi Taylor",
      c: "[c] Zora Neale Hurston",
      d: "[d] Valerie Biden Owens",
      e: "[e] Mikki Kendall",
      answer: "[d] Valerie Biden Owens",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.9) Who is the chairperson of the taskforce formed by the govt under Mission Karamyogi?",
      a: "[a] Vijoy Kumar Singh",
      b: "[b] Sanjay Sharan",
      c: "[c] Jay Karan Singh",
      d: "[d] S D Shibu Lal",
      e: "[e] Gaurav Kumar",
      answer: "[d] S D Shibu Lal",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.10) Where is the headquarter of Airport Council International located?",
      a: "[a] Canada",
      b: "[b] Austria",
      c: "[c] Netherlands",
      d: "[d] Sweden",
      e: "[e] Denmark",
      answer: "[a] Canada",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.1) What is the name of the portal launched for enabling the parties to file their appeals, miscellaneous applications, documents, paper books, etc., related to income tax electronically?",
      a: "[a] iddat-e-dwar",
      b: "[b] vishwas-e-dwar",
      c: "[c] kar-e-dwar",
      d: "[d] itat-e-dwar",
      e: "[e] vikas-e-dwar",
      answer: "[d] itat-e-dwar",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.2) Which of the following statement is true about the Enforcing Contracts Portal?",
      a: "[a] It aims to promote the contract enforcement regime in the country",
      b: "[b] It aims to reinforce the contracts made by Exim Bank with other countries",
      c: "[c] It aims to increase the project exports",
      d: "[d] It aims to promote foreign direct investments in the country by strengthening contract enforcement",
      e: "[e] It aims to enforce the financial contracts solely",
      answer:
        "[a] It aims to promote the contract enforcement regime in the country",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.3) Where is Kudankulam nuclear power plant located?",
      a: "[a] Andhra Pradesh",
      b: "[b] Karnataka",
      c: "[c] Odisha",
      d: "[d] Kerala",
      e: "[e] Tamil Nadu",
      answer: "[e] Tamil Nadu",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.4) Which state has decided to set up district-level industry and investment promotion agencies to create more economic opportunities?",
      a: "[a] Madhya Pradesh",
      b: "[b] Odisha",
      c: "[c] Uttar Pradesh",
      d: "[d] Tamil Nadu",
      e: "[e] Telangana",
      answer: "[b] Odisha",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.5) Which of the following organization has launched the LowCarbon.Earth, in partnership with UNEP?",
      a: "[a] Society for Environment and Development",
      b: "[b] Forum of Activities for Community Environment",
      c: "[c] Centre for Environment Education",
      d: "[d] WWF India",
      e: "[e] Massive Earth Foundation",
      answer: "[e] Massive Earth Foundation",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.6) Who has won the Fukuoka Prize for 2021?",
      a: "[a] Vijoy Kumar Singh",
      b: "[b] Jogiranjan Panigrahi",
      c: "[c] Gaurav Kumar",
      d: "[d] P. Sainath",
      e: "[e] Kumar Padmapani Bora",
      answer: "[d] P. Sainath",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.7) How much interest rate will be applicable on loans taken by healthcare sector under the ₹1.1 lakh crore loan guarantee scheme for Covid-affected sectors of the govt?",
      a: "[a] 7.95%",
      b: "[b] 5.6%",
      c: "[c] 6.15%",
      d: "[d] 3.71%",
      e: "[e] 8.91%",
      answer: "[a] 7.95%",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.8) What is the total cap of Emergency Credit Line Guarantee scheme at present?",
      a: "[a] Rs 5 lakh crores",
      b: "[b] Rs 1 lakh crores",
      c: "[c] Rs 2.5 lakh crores",
      d: "[d] Rs 4.5 lakh crores",
      e: "[e] Rs 3 lakh crores",
      answer: "[d] Rs 4.5 lakh crores",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.9) How much loan will be provided to the tourist guides at 100% guarantee under the central govt’s economic relief measures?",
      a: "[a] Rs 2 lakh",
      b: "[b] Rs 5 lakh",
      c: "[c] Rs 4 lakh",
      d: "[d] Rs 1 lakh",
      e: "[e] Rs 3 lakh",
      answer: "[d] Rs 1 lakh",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.10) How much amount will be infused in the National Export Insurance Account (NEIA) as part of the economic relief measures to support project exporters?",
      a: "[a] ₹22,000 crore",
      b: "[b] ₹33,000 crore",
      c: "[c] ₹15,000 crore",
      d: "[d] ₹88,000 crore",
      e: "[e] ₹10,000 crore",
      answer: "[b] ₹33,000 crore",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.1) With which state has Triton Electric Vehicles (US firm) signed an MoU to set up its manufacturing facility of Rs 2100 crores for e-vehicles in the state?",
      a: "[a] Telangana",
      b: "[b] Madhya Pradesh",
      c: "[c] Maharashtra",
      d: "[d] Andhra Pradesh",
      e: "[e] Gujarat",
      answer: "[a] Telangana",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.2) Where was 16th Meeting of Security Council Secretaries of Shanghai Corporation Organisation (SCO) member states held?",
      a: "[a] Khujand",
      b: "[b] Kulob",
      c: "[c] Panjakent",
      d: "[d] Dushanbe",
      e: "[e] Nurek",
      answer: "[d] Dushanbe",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.3) Which agency has released the “Annual Report on Children and Armed Conflict” report?",
      a: "[a] UN",
      b: "[b] UNESCO",
      c: "[c] Kids Rights Foundation",
      d: "[d] Save the Children",
      e: "[e] UNICEF",
      answer: "[a] UN",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.4) Which university has topped the QS Executive MBA Rankings 2021?",
      a: "[a] HEC Paris",
      b: "[b] Stanford University",
      c: "[c] The University of Chicago Booth School of Business",
      d: "[d] Haas School of Business",
      e: "[e] IESE Business School",
      answer: "[a] HEC Paris",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.5) Which company has announced to set up India’s 1st Carbon Fibre Manufacturing Unit to cater to aerospace and defence needs?",
      a: "[a] Bharat Dynamics",
      b: "[b] BEML Limited",
      c: "[c] Ordnance Factory Board",
      d: "[d] Reliance Industries Ltd",
      e: "[e] Tata Advanced Systems",
      answer: "[d] Reliance Industries Ltd",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.6) Which company has launched a tailor-made insurance policy, “Women's cancer shield” for breast cancer female patients, in partnership with Alliance Insurance?",
      a: "[a] Fabindia",
      b: "[b] Unilever",
      c: "[c] Clovia",
      d: "[d] Pernod Ricard",
      e: "[e] Nykaa",
      answer: "[c] Clovia",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.7) Which of the following banks has approved the $125 million Kerala Resilient Program for supporting the state in preparing against natural disasters, climate change impacts, disease outbreaks, and pandemics?",
      a: "[a] Asian Infrastructure Investment Bank",
      b: "[b] New Development Bank",
      c: "[c] International Monetary Bank",
      d: "[d] European Bank for Reconstruction and Development",
      e: "[e] World Bank",
      answer: "[e] World Bank",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.8) When is the Day of the Seafarer observed?",
      a: "[a] June 17",
      b: "[b] June 13",
      c: "[c] June 25",
      d: "[d] June 11",
      e: "[e] June 15",
      answer: "[c] June 25",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.9) When is World Vitiligo Day observed?",
      a: "[a] June 11",
      b: "[b] June 13",
      c: "[c] June 14",
      d: "[d] June 25",
      e: "[e] June 10",
      answer: "[d] June 25",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.10) How many people were suffering from drug use disorders in 2020, as per the World Drug Report 2021 of United Nations' Office on Drugs and Crime (UNODC)?",
      a: "[a] 18 million",
      b: "[b] 24 million",
      c: "[c] 36 million",
      d: "[d] 20 million",
      e: "[e] 16 million",
      answer: "[c] 36 million",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.1) Which state has partnered with United Nations World Food Programme (WFP) to improve household food and nutritional security by strengthening livelihood initiatives, reaching thousands of state-supported Women's Self-Help Groups?",
      a: "[a] Odisha",
      b: "[b] Maharashtra",
      c: "[c] Andhra Pradesh",
      d: "[d] Gujarat",
      e: "[e] Telangana",
      answer: "[a] Odisha",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.2) Which of the following state / UT govt has announced to launch Mukhya Mantri Covid-19 Pariwar Aarthik Sahayata Yojana to provide financial aid to the families of victims of Covid-19?",
      a: "[a] Haryana",
      b: "[b] Punjab",
      c: "[c] Uttarakhand",
      d: "[d] Delhi",
      e: "[e] Puducherry",
      answer: "[d] Delhi",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.3) With which Caribbean country has India recently signed an MoU for the exchange of tax information and assistance in the tax collection?",
      a: "[a] Antigua and Barbuda",
      b: "[b] Dominica",
      c: "[c] Jamaica",
      d: "[d] Guyana",
      e: "[e] Saint Vincent and the Grenadines",
      answer: "[e] Saint Vincent and the Grenadines",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.4) In which country has Tax Inspectors Without Border Program been launched by India and UNDP?",
      a: "[a] Nepal",
      b: "[b] Papua New Guinea",
      c: "[c] Singapore",
      d: "[d] Thailand",
      e: "[e] Bhutan",
      answer: "[e] Bhutan",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.5) Which edition of the BRICS Young Scientist Conclave will be organized by India during 13-16 September 2021?",
      a: "[a] 6th",
      b: "[b] 3rd",
      c: "[c] 5th",
      d: "[d] 7th",
      e: "[e] 10th",
      answer: "[a] 6th",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.6) With which bank has Afthonia Lab (a fintech incubator) partnered to support fintech companies in India for transforming the Indian financial sector?",
      a: "[a] Bandhan Bank",
      b: "[b] Yes Bank",
      c: "[c] HDFC Bank",
      d: "[d] IndusInd Bank",
      e: "[e] RBL Bank",
      answer: "[b] Yes Bank",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.7) What is India’s GDP forecast for FY22 by S&P?",
      a: "[a] 9.5%",
      b: "[b] 10.1%",
      c: "[c] 8.5%",
      d: "[d] 8.8%",
      e: "[e] 7.8%",
      answer: "[a] 9.5%",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.8) What is the Global GDP forecast for FY23 by World Bank?",
      a: "[a] 4.3%",
      b: "[b] 5.6%",
      c: "[c] 3.1%",
      d: "[d] 5.5%",
      e: "[e] 4.6%",
      answer: "[a] 4.3%",
    },
    {
      question:
        'Q.9) Who is the singer of "Lakshya Tera Samne Hai", which is India\'s "Official Olympic Theme Song" for the upcoming Tokyo Olympics 2020?',
      a: "[a] Sonu Nigam",
      b: "[b] Shaan",
      c: "[c] Atif Aslam",
      d: "[d] Mohit Chauhan",
      e: "[e] Armaan Malik",
      answer: "[d] Mohit Chauhan",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.10) Who was the player of the match in the 1st edition of ICC World Test Championship 2021?",
      a: "[a] Kane Williamson",
      b: "[b] Devon Conway",
      c: "[c] Ross Taylor",
      d: "[d] Trent Boult",
      e: "[e] Kyle Jamieson",
      answer: "[e] Kyle Jamieson",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.1) Which has become India’s first rabies-free state?",
      a: "[a] Manipur",
      b: "[b] Tripura",
      c: "[c] Goa",
      d: "[d] Nagaland",
      e: "[e] Uttarakhand",
      answer: "[c] Goa",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.2) Which state has signed an MoU with the UK government to strengthen and support clean and green energy tech startups in the state?",
      a: "[a] Tamil Nadu",
      b: "[b] Maharashtra",
      c: "[c] Madhya Pradesh",
      d: "[d] Gujarat",
      e: "[e] Odisha",
      answer: "[b] Maharashtra",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.3) Which of the following institution developed world’s first genetically modified (GM) rubber plant?",
      a: "[a] Rubber Technology Institute",
      b: "[b] Rubber Research and Development Institute",
      c: "[c] IIT-Madras",
      d: "[d] Rubber Research Institute of India",
      e: "[e] Rubber Development Institute",
      answer: "[d] Rubber Research Institute of India",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.4) Which bank has launched 'Aarogyam Loan' business loan scheme for the healthcare sector to extend loan support in the wake of Covid-19 pandemic?",
      a: "[a] HDFC Bank",
      b: "[b] State Bank of India",
      c: "[c] Canara Bank",
      d: "[d] Axis Bank",
      e: "[e] ICICI Bank",
      answer: "[b] State Bank of India",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.5) Who heads the panel formed by International Financial Services Centres Authority to examine global best practices in ship financing and leasing, identify opportunities and prepare a roadmap to enable such activities from GIFT IFSC?",
      a: "[a] OM Prakash",
      b: "[b] Uttank Joshi",
      c: "[c] Vandana Agarwal",
      d: "[d] P. Rangarajan",
      e: "[e] Bidisha Sengupta",
      answer: "[c] Vandana Agarwal",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.6) When was Biotech-Krishi Innovation Science Application Network launched?",
      a: "[a] 2018",
      b: "[b] 2017",
      c: "[c] 2014",
      d: "[d] 2013",
      e: "[e] 2012",
      answer: "[b] 2017",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.7) Where is India’s largest solar carport located?",
      a: "[a] Pune",
      b: "[b] Cochin",
      c: "[c] Nagpur",
      d: "[d] Kanpur",
      e: "[e] Guwahati",
      answer: "[a] Pune",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.8) How much wealth was reduced in 2020 in India, as per the “Global Wealth Report” 2021?",
      a: "[a] 4.4%",
      b: "[b] 5.1%",
      c: "[c] 2.3%",
      d: "[d] 3.7%",
      e: "[e] 1.6%",
      answer: "[a] 4.4%",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.9) When is International Olympic Day observed?",
      a: "[a] June 25",
      b: "[b] June 23",
      c: "[c] June 17",
      d: "[d] June 15",
      e: "[e] June 12",
      answer: "[b] June 23",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.10) Who is the author of “It’s A Wonderful Life: Roads To Happiness”?",
      a: "[a] Devdutt Pattanaik",
      b: "[b] Anand Neelakantan",
      c: "[c] Vikram Chandra",
      d: "[d] Ruskin Bond",
      e: "[e] Upamanyu Chatterjee",
      answer: "[d] Ruskin Bond",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.1) Which company has received a contract from Ministry of Defence for the construction of two Pollution Control Vessels (PCVs) for the Indian Coast Guard?",
      a: "[a] L&T",
      b: "[b] Bharat Dynamic Ltd",
      c: "[c] GRSE Ltd",
      d: "[d] Goa Shipyard Ltd",
      e: "[e] Mahindra Defence Systems",
      answer: "[d] Goa Shipyard Ltd",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.2) With which European country has India formed a trilateral partnership to create stability in the Indo-Pacific region, along with Japan?",
      a: "[a] Germany",
      b: "[b] Belgium",
      c: "[c] Spain",
      d: "[d] UK",
      e: "[e] Italy",
      answer: "[e] Italy",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.3) How many integrated theatre commands are operating in India at present?",
      a: "[a] Five",
      b: "[b] Two",
      c: "[c] Three",
      d: "[d] Zero",
      e: "[e] One",
      answer: "[b] Two",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.4) With which country has India signed an MoU for cooperation in the field of agriculture and allied sectors?",
      a: "[a] Fiji",
      b: "[b] Cambodia",
      c: "[c] Laos",
      d: "[d] Vietnam",
      e: "[e] Philippines",
      answer: "[a] Fiji",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.5) The surplus transfer by RBI to Central Govt in FY21 is equivalent to __ percent of GDP, as per RBI’s State of Economy report?",
      a: "[a] 0.44%",
      b: "[b] 0.10%",
      c: "[c] 0.33%",
      d: "[d] 0.18%",
      e: "[e] 0.29%",
      answer: "[a] 0.44%",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.6) What is the GDP forecast for India for 2021 by Moody’s?",
      a: "[a] 10.5%",
      b: "[b] 9.3%",
      c: "[c] 8.8%",
      d: "[d] 11.5%",
      e: "[e] 9.6%",
      answer: "[e] 9.6%",
    },
    {
      question:
        'Q.7) Which ministry has launched "Jaan Hai To Jahan Hai" to create awareness about coronavirus vaccination and prevent apprehensions and rumours?',
      a: "[a] Ministry of Rural Development",
      b: "[b] Ministry of Minority Affairs",
      c: "[c] Ministry of Health and Family Welfare",
      d: "[d] Ministry of Tribal Affairs",
      e: "[e] Ministry of Panchayati Raj",
      answer: "[b] Ministry of Minority Affairs",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.8) Which state has signed an MoU with the Survey of India for implementing the Svamitva scheme in the state?",
      a: "[a] West Bengal",
      b: "[b] Odisha",
      c: "[c] Andhra Pradesh",
      d: "[d] Assam",
      e: "[e] Telangana",
      answer: "[d] Assam",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.9) Who has been appointed as the “Ambassador of Forest Frontline Heroes” by WWF India?",
      a: "[a] Lily Pal",
      b: "[b] Ashish Jaiswal",
      c: "[c] Upasana Kamineni",
      d: "[d] Deojeet Kumar",
      e: "[e] Nitesh Kumar",
      answer: "[c] Upasana Kamineni",
    },
    {
      question:
        'Q.10) Who is the author of "My Joys and Sorrows – as a Mother of a Special Child"?',
      a: "[a] Ravi Shanker",
      b: "[b] Vinita Sinha",
      c: "[c] Deojeet Kumar",
      d: "[d] Krishna Saksena",
      e: "[e] Sumit Verma",
      answer: "[d] Krishna Saksena",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.1) Where did Indian Navy and EU NAVFOR Somalia conduct a joint naval exercise?",
      a: "[a] Gulf of Berbera",
      b: "[b] Gulf of Tadjoura",
      c: "[c] Gulf of Aqaba",
      d: "[d] Gulf of Suez",
      e: "[e] Gulf of Aden",
      answer: "[e] Gulf of Aden",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.2) With which bank has National Small Industries Corporation (NSIC) recently signed an MoU to support MSMEs with credit requirements?",
      a: "[a] Indian Bank",
      b: "[b] DBS Bank India",
      c: "[c] Bandhan Bank",
      d: "[d] City Union Bank",
      e: "[e] Union Bank of India",
      answer: "[e] Union Bank of India",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.3) How much FDI flow did India receive in 2020, as per the World Investment Report 2021?",
      a: "[a] $64 billion",
      b: "[b] $51 billion",
      c: "[c] $80 billion",
      d: "[d] $35 billion",
      e: "[e] $20 billion",
      answer: "[a] $64 billion",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.4) Who is the chair of SEBI’s reconstituted Takeover Panel?",
      a: "[a] N Venkatram",
      b: "[b] Darius Khambata",
      c: "[c] Thomas Mathew T",
      d: "[d] NK Sodhi",
      e: "[e] K Kannan",
      answer: "[d] NK Sodhi",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.5) Who has been named as a member of a High-Level Advisory Group (HLAG) on Sustainable and Inclusive Recovery and Growth of World Bank-IMF from India?",
      a: "[a] Hardeep Singh Puri",
      b: "[b] Asoke Kumar Mukerji",
      c: "[c] Syed Akbaruddin",
      d: "[d] Montek Singh Ahluwalia",
      e: "[e] T. S. Tirumurti",
      answer: "[d] Montek Singh Ahluwalia",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.6) Who has won CEU’s Open Society Prize 2021?",
      a: "[a] Nirupam Sen",
      b: "[b] Vijay K. Nambiar",
      c: "[c] KK Shailaja",
      d: "[d] Kamalesh Sharma",
      e: "[e] Prakash Shah",
      answer: "[c] KK Shailaja",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.7) Where is the operational headquarter of Operation Atalanta located?",
      a: "[a] UK",
      b: "[b] Spain",
      c: "[c] Germany",
      d: "[d] Denmark",
      e: "[e] Norway",
      answer: "[b] Spain",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.8) As per the World Investment Report 2021, FDI inflows reduced by __ percent in 2020 to $1 trillion?",
      a: "[a] 35%",
      b: "[b] 40%",
      c: "[c] 20%",
      d: "[d] 10%",
      e: "[e] 15%",
      answer: "[a] 35%",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.9) Which state has launched ‘Ashirbad’ scheme for education, health and maintenance of Covid orphans?",
      a: "[a] Odisha",
      b: "[b] Andhra Pradesh",
      c: "[c] Karnataka",
      d: "[d] Kerala",
      e: "[e] Madhya Pradesh",
      answer: "[a] Odisha",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.10) Who is the author of 'The 7 Sins of Being A Mother'?",
      a: "[a] Aravind Adiga",
      b: "[b] Jeet Thayil",
      c: "[c] Tahira Kashyap Khurrana",
      d: "[d] Amit Chaudhuri",
      e: "[e] Kiran Desai",
      answer: "[c] Tahira Kashyap Khurrana",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.1) Recently, US-India hydrogen taskforce has been launched under the aegis of Strategic Clean Energy Partnership (SCEP) for the exploration of hydrogen. The taskforce has been launched by United States Department of Energy (DOE), the Indian Ministry of New and Renewable Energy (MNRE), along with the US India Strategic Partnership Forum (USISPF). US India Strategic Partnership Forum will act as the Secretariat for the Task Force. Dr Ken Vincent is the co-chair of US-India Hydrogen Task Force from US side, and director of Office of Asian Affairs, Office of International Affairs at Department of Energy (DOE). Who is the co-chair of this taskforce from India?",
      a: "[a] Madan Lal",
      b: "[b] Prakash Chandra Maithani",
      c: "[c] Bibhuti Bhushana Dash",
      d: "[d] Susheela Tigga",
      e: "[e] Banaja Behra",
      answer: "[b] Prakash Chandra Maithani",
    },
    {
      question:
        'Q.2) Which state government will constitute an "Economic Advisory Council to the Chief Minister" with leading economic experts like Esther Duflo and Raghuram Rajan as its members?',
      a: "[a] Maharashtra",
      b: "[b] Tamil Nadu",
      c: "[c] Karnataka",
      d: "[d] Odisha",
      e: "[e] Andhra Pradesh",
      answer: "[b] Tamil Nadu",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.3) Which country will get world's most powerful magnet?",
      a: "[a] Denmark",
      b: "[b] Germany",
      c: "[c] Italy",
      d: "[d] France",
      e: "[e] UK",
      answer: "[d] France",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.4) With which company has Bharti Airtel for implementing 5G network solutions for India?",
      a: "[a] HCL Technologies",
      b: "[b] Infosys",
      c: "[c] IBM",
      d: "[d] Tech Mahindra",
      e: "[e] Tata Consultancy Services",
      answer: "[e] Tata Consultancy Services",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.5) What is the name of the app launched by India, in partnership with WHO, to provide yoga training videos in different languages for people across the world?",
      a: "[a] m- Yoga app",
      b: "[b] v- Yoga app",
      c: "[c] t- Yoga app",
      d: "[d] u- Yoga app",
      e: "[e] w- Yoga app",
      answer: "[a] m- Yoga app",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.6) Who has become the first transgender athlete to compete at the Olympics?",
      a: "[a] Veronica Ivy",
      b: "[b] Chris Mosier",
      c: "[c] Andraya Yearwood",
      d: "[d] Laurel Hubbard",
      e: "[e] Hannah Mouncey",
      answer: "[d] Laurel Hubbard",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.7) When was India-US Strategic Energy Partnership launched?",
      a: "[a] 2017",
      b: "[b] 2015",
      c: "[c] 2010",
      d: "[d] 2018",
      e: "[e] 2019",
      answer: "[d] 2018",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.8) How many poor people (with income of $2 per day or less in purchasing power parity) have been estimated in India by Pew Research Centre and World Bank?",
      a: "[a] 100 million",
      b: "[b] 134 million",
      c: "[c] 80 million",
      d: "[d] 23 million",
      e: "[e] 90 million",
      answer: "[b] 134 million",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.9) What is the theme of World Refugee Day 2021?",
      a: "[a] Every Action Counts, All Lives Matter.",
      b: "[b] Together we heal, learn and shine",
      c: "[c] Now More Than Ever, We Need to Stand with Refugees",
      d: "[d] Understanding the Plight of Refugees",
      e: "[e] Act Now To Stop Displacement",
      answer: "[b] Together we heal, learn and shine",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.10) When is the World Hydrography Day observed?",
      a: "[a] June 21",
      b: "[b] June 28",
      c: "[c] June 11",
      d: "[d] June 18",
      e: "[e] June 19",
      answer: "[a] June 21",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.1) Who has won the UN Land for Life Award 2021?",
      a: "[a] Shyam Sunder Jyani",
      b: "[b] Vijoy Kumar Singh",
      c: "[c] Hemant Kumar Nanda",
      d: "[d] Ravi Shanker Shukla",
      e: "[e] Kumar Padmapani Bora",
      answer: "[a] Shyam Sunder Jyani",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.2) Which state has launched e-Pathsala and e-Mulyankan facilities for school students?",
      a: "[a] Madhya Pradesh",
      b: "[b] Odisha",
      c: "[c] Andhra Pradesh",
      d: "[d] Karnataka",
      e: "[e] Kerala",
      answer: "[b] Odisha",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.3) With which Indian Institute of Management has Central Institute of Road Transport signed an MoU to build competencies and generate industry-oriented knowledge in transport management?",
      a: "[a] IIM- Pune",
      b: "[b] IIM- Ahmedabad",
      c: "[c] IIM- Bangalore",
      d: "[d] IIM- Nagpur",
      e: "[e] IIM- Indore",
      answer: "[d] IIM- Nagpur",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.4) Which of the following institution is the lead agency for Polar-Areas Stellar-Imaging in Polarisation High-Accuracy Experiment (PASIPHAE)?",
      a: "[a] University of Crete, Greece",
      b: "[b] Inter-University Centre for Astronomy and Astrophysics, India",
      c: "[c] Caltech, USA",
      d: "[d] South African Astronomical Observatory",
      e: "[e] Institute of Astrophysics, Greece",
      answer: "[e] Institute of Astrophysics, Greece",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.5) Which of the following is the only state from North-East India to feature in the Top 5 performers list of the NITI Aayog’s Sustainable Development Index 2021?",
      a: "[a] Sikkim",
      b: "[b] Arunachal Pradesh",
      c: "[c] Mizoram",
      d: "[d] Tripura",
      e: "[e] Nagaland",
      answer: "[a] Sikkim",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.6) What is India’s rank in the Global Peace Index in 2020 and 2021?",
      a: "[a] 55 and 79",
      b: "[b] 143 and 144",
      c: "[c] 179 and 180",
      d: "[d] 139 and 135",
      e: "[e] 121 and 117",
      answer: "[d] 139 and 135",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.7) What is India’s score in the Sustainable Development Report 2021 of Sustainable Development Solutions Network?",
      a: "[a] 60.1",
      b: "[b] 78.2",
      c: "[c] 80.5",
      d: "[d] 75.5",
      e: "[e] 52.2",
      answer: "[a] 60.1",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.8) Who among the following has become the youngest player to win the US Women’s Open 2021 Golf tournament?",
      a: "[a] Yuka Saso",
      b: "[b] Kristi Albers",
      c: "[c] Helen Alfredsson",
      d: "[d] Amy Alcott",
      e: "[e] Danielle Ammaccapane",
      answer: "[a] Yuka Saso",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.9) Who has been chosen as the President of Iran?",
      a: "[a] Mohammad Khatami",
      b: "[b] Hassan Rouhani",
      c: "[c] Mahmoud Ahmadinejad",
      d: "[d] Ebrahim Raisi",
      e: "[e] Ali Khamenei",
      answer: "[d] Ebrahim Raisi",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.10) Who has become the first private person in India to be appointed at the Councillor, Permanent Mission of India at World Trade Organisation (WTO), Geneva?",
      a: "[a] Premjeet Singh",
      b: "[b] Aashish Chandorkar",
      c: "[c] Rajat Pal",
      d: "[d] Sumit Verma",
      e: "[e] Sachin Vashisth",
      answer: "[b] Aashish Chandorkar",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.1) What is the name of the portal launched by Minister of Tribal Affairs as the Central Repository of all training programs conducted by Tribal Research Institutes (TRIs), different divisions of the Ministry, National Society for Education of Tribal Students (NESTS), Centre of Excellences funded by Ministry of Tribal Affairs and National Tribal Research Institute?",
      a: "[a] Adi Prashikshan",
      b: "[b] Adi Prekshak",
      c: "[c] Adi Prerna",
      d: "[d] Adi Parakh",
      e: "[e] Adi Pareeksha",
      answer: "[a] Adi Prashikshan",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.2) Which edition of the NATO Summit took place in Brussels recently?",
      a: "[a] 41st",
      b: "[b] 52nd",
      c: "[c] 23rd",
      d: "[d] 31st",
      e: "[e] 70th",
      answer: "[d] 31st",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.3) Which of the following is not a founding member of Non-Aligned Movement countries?",
      a: "[a] Indonesia",
      b: "[b] Yugoslavia",
      c: "[c] India",
      d: "[d] Egypt",
      e: "[e] Sri Lanka",
      answer: "[e] Sri Lanka",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.4) How many children are working at the e-waste dumpsites every year, as per WHO’s “Children and Digital Dumpsites” report?",
      a: "[a] 18 million",
      b: "[b] 23 million",
      c: "[c] 19 million",
      d: "[d] 33 million",
      e: "[e] 40 million",
      answer: "[a] 18 million",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.5) What is India’s rank in the “Government Efficiency” sub-index of IMD’s World Competitiveness Index 2021?",
      a: "[a] 32",
      b: "[b] 18",
      c: "[c] 46",
      d: "[d] 20",
      e: "[e] 54",
      answer: "[c] 46",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.6) How many industrial corridors are being developed in India under the National Industrial Corridor Program?",
      a: "[a] Five",
      b: "[b] Ten",
      c: "[c] Eleven",
      d: "[d] Nine",
      e: "[e] Seven",
      answer: "[c] Eleven",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.7) What is CII’s forecast for India’s GDP for FY22?",
      a: "[a] 9.5%",
      b: "[b] 10.5%",
      c: "[c] 8.8%",
      d: "[d] 11.2%",
      e: "[e] 13.5%",
      answer: "[a] 9.5%",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.8) What is NSO’s GDP forecast (contraction) for India for FY21?",
      a: "[a] 8.9%",
      b: "[b] 5.4%",
      c: "[c] 6.6%",
      d: "[d] 7.3%",
      e: "[e] 7.7%",
      answer: "[d] 7.3%",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.9) Who has been chosen as the SDG Pioneers 2021 from India by UNGC?",
      a: "[a] Rajni Sharma",
      b: "[b] Bibhuti Bhushana Dash",
      c: "[c] Ujjaval Srivastava",
      d: "[d] Sumant Sinha",
      e: "[e] Vinod Kumar",
      answer: "[d] Sumant Sinha",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.10) As per the Global Assessment Report on Drought 2021, impact of severe droughts on India’s GDP can be about ____ per cent per annum, despite decreasing contribution of agriculture in the country’s expanding economy?",
      a: "[a] 2-5%",
      b: "[b] 3-6%",
      c: "[c] 4-8%",
      d: "[d] 3-7%",
      e: "[e] 5-10%",
      answer: "[a] 2-5%",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.1) How many components are there in Deep Ocean Mission?",
      a: "[a] Six",
      b: "[b] Ten",
      c: "[c] Five",
      d: "[d] Four",
      e: "[e] Three",
      answer: "[a] Six",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.2) How many Van Dhan Vikas Kendras are expected to be established through the “Sankalp Se Siddhi – Mission Van Dhan”?",
      a: "[a] 50,000",
      b: "[b] 10,000",
      c: "[c] 20,000",
      d: "[d] 30,000",
      e: "[e] 15,000",
      answer: "[a] 50,000",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.3) Which of the following statement is untrue about the India Interagency Expert Committee (IEC) on Malaria and Climate?",
      a: "[a] It has been launched by IMD, ICMR, and Malaria No More",
      b: "[b] It will explore and advance climate-based solutions for accelerating the elimination of the vector-borne disease from the country",
      c: "[c] India aims to eliminate Malaria by 2030",
      d: "[d] IMD will be providing weather data for issuing malaria forecasts",
      e: "[e] The IEC will receive technical assistance from WHO",
      answer: "[e] The IEC will receive technical assistance from WHO",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.4) Which state has launched ‘Yuva Shakti Corona Mukti Abhiyan’ to create awareness about the COVID pandemic?",
      a: "[a] Chhattisgarh",
      b: "[b] Madhya Pradesh",
      c: "[c] Karnataka",
      d: "[d] Punjab",
      e: "[e] Himachal Pradesh",
      answer: "[b] Madhya Pradesh",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.5) The GI- certified Jalgaon bananas belong to which state?",
      a: "[a] Tamil Nadu",
      b: "[b] Kerala",
      c: "[c] Maharashtra",
      d: "[d] Punjab",
      e: "[e] Gujarat",
      answer: "[c] Maharashtra",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.6) Emirates Group Security and GMR Aviation Academy signed a Memorandum of Understanding to promote cooperation for the development and exchange of information, technical expertise, and experiences in aviation security. Which country does the Emirates Group Security belong to?",
      a: "[a] Saudi Arabia",
      b: "[b] Israel",
      c: "[c] Oman",
      d: "[d] Qatar",
      e: "[e] UAE",
      answer: "[e] UAE",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.7) Which country has received Line of Credit (LOC) worth USD 108.28 million from India for construction of its new Parliament building?",
      a: "[a] Eswatini",
      b: "[b] Somalia",
      c: "[c] Ghana",
      d: "[d] Albania",
      e: "[e] Namibia",
      answer: "[a] Eswatini",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.8) When is the ASEAN Dengue Day observed?",
      a: "[a] June 18",
      b: "[b] June 15",
      c: "[c] June 17",
      d: "[d] June 20",
      e: "[e] June 23",
      answer: "[b] June 15",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.9) Which country organized the ASEAN Regional Forum on Dengue on the occasion of ASEAN Dengue Day?",
      a: "[a] Vietnam",
      b: "[b] Thailand",
      c: "[c] Laos",
      d: "[d] Brunei",
      e: "[e] Philippines",
      answer: "[e] Philippines",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.10) When is the International Day of Family Remittances observed?",
      a: "[a] June 15",
      b: "[b] June 16",
      c: "[c] June 17",
      d: "[d] June 20",
      e: "[e] June 5",
      answer: "[b] June 16",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.1) Which state has received GI tag for Jardalu mangoes?",
      a: "[a] Bihar",
      b: "[b] Maharashtra",
      c: "[c] Andhra Pradesh",
      d: "[d] Kerala",
      e: "[e] Odisha",
      answer: "[a] Bihar",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.2) European Space Agency (ESA) has planned to launch the world’s first wooden satellite, WISA Woodsat, on Earth’s orbit by the end of 2021. The mission will test the applicability of wooden materials like plywood in spacecraft structures and expose it to extreme space conditions, such as heat, cold, vacuum and radiation, for an extended period of time. The satellite will be launched on a Rocket Lab Electron rocket from the Mahia Peninsula launch complex. In which country is the complex located?",
      a: "[a] Belgium",
      b: "[b] Netherlands",
      c: "[c] Luxembourg",
      d: "[d] New Zealand",
      e: "[e] Croatia",
      answer: "[d] New Zealand",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.3) Who will deliver the 17th Raúl Prebisch lecture at UN Trade Forum 2021?",
      a: "[a] Ragnar Frisch",
      b: "[b] Jan Tinbergen",
      c: "[c] Elinor Ostrom",
      d: "[d] Esther Duflo",
      e: "[e] Paul Milgrom",
      answer: "[d] Esther Duflo",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.4) Which company produces the Advanced Light Helicopters ALH Mk-III for Indian Armed Forces?",
      a: "[a] Bharat Electronics",
      b: "[b] Kalyani Group",
      c: "[c] Larsen & Toubro",
      d: "[d] Hindustan Aeronautics Ltd",
      e: "[e] Tata Group",
      answer: "[d] Hindustan Aeronautics Ltd",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.5) Who is the ambassador of Audi in India?",
      a: "[a] Virat Kohli",
      b: "[b] Akshay Kumar",
      c: "[c] Rishabh Pant",
      d: "[d] Shahrukh Khan",
      e: "[e] Shahid Kapoor",
      answer: "[a] Virat Kohli",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.6) Who is the Prime Minister of Israel?",
      a: "[a] Benjamin Netanyahu",
      b: "[b] Naftali Bennett",
      c: "[c] Peretz Naftali",
      d: "[d] Ayman Odeh",
      e: "[e] Shlomo Molla",
      answer: "[b] Naftali Bennett",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.7) When is the International Albinism Awareness Day observed?",
      a: "[a] June 13",
      b: "[b] June 19",
      c: "[c] June 15",
      d: "[d] June 20",
      e: "[e] June 8",
      answer: "[a] June 13",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.8) What is the slogan of World Blood Donor Day 2021?",
      a: "[a] Blood donation and universal access to safe blood transfusion",
      b: "[b] Safe blood saves lives",
      c: "[c] Be there for someone else. Give blood",
      d: "[d] Give blood. Give now. Give often",
      e: "[e] Give blood and keep the world beating",
      answer: "[e] Give blood and keep the world beating",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.9) Who is the winner of French Open 2021 women’s singles?",
      a: "[a] Barbora Krejčíková",
      b: "[b] Evonne Goolagong",
      c: "[c] Justine Henin",
      d: "[d] Venus Williams",
      e: "[e] Margaret Court",
      answer: "[a] Barbora Krejčíková",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.10) Tsitsi Dangarembga has won the PEN Pinter Prize 2021. Which country does she belong to?",
      a: "[a] Albania",
      b: "[b] Monaco",
      c: "[c] Croatia",
      d: "[d] Cyprus",
      e: "[e] Zimbabwe",
      answer: "[e] Zimbabwe",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.1) Which of the following organization is funding the India-Russia Joint Technology Assessment and Accelerated Commercialisation Programme from Russia’s side?",
      a: "[a] FASIE",
      b: "[b] Rostec",
      c: "[c] Sberbank of Russia",
      d: "[d] Gazprom",
      e: "[e] Transneft",
      answer: "[a] FASIE",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.2) Which of the following Indian Navy Ship has participated in the India-Thailand coordinated patrol?",
      a: "[a] INS Cheetah",
      b: "[b] INS Magar",
      c: "[c] INS Shardul",
      d: "[d] INS Gharial",
      e: "[e] INS Saryu",
      answer: "[e] INS Saryu",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.3) With which country’s Security and Defence Industry Association has Society of Indian Defence Manufacturers signed an MoU to promote and strengthen the bilateral defence industrial relations?",
      a: "[a] Germany",
      b: "[b] Denmark",
      c: "[c] Israel",
      d: "[d] Sweden",
      e: "[e] France",
      answer: "[d] Sweden",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.4) Which bank has launched a collateral-free loan scheme called the ‘KAVACH Personal Loan' for the families affected by COVID-19?",
      a: "[a] HDFC Bank",
      b: "[b] Axis Bank",
      c: "[c] ICICI Bank",
      d: "[d] SBI",
      e: "[e] Kotak Mahindra Bank",
      answer: "[d] SBI",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.5) Who has been appointed as the chair of the Grievance Redressal Board of the recently formed Digital Publisher Content Grievances Council by IAMAI?",
      a: "[a] Justice R. Subhash Reddy",
      b: "[b] Justice Ajay Rastogi",
      c: "[c] Justice Sanjiv Khanna",
      d: "[d] Justice Bhushan Ramkrishna Gavai",
      e: "[e] Justice Arjan Kumar Sikri",
      answer: "[e] Justice Arjan Kumar Sikri",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.6) What is the capital of Central Africa Republic?",
      a: "[a] Freetown",
      b: "[b] Mogadishu",
      c: "[c] Accra",
      d: "[d] Bangui",
      e: "[e] Windhoek",
      answer: "[d] Bangui",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.7) Who has won Pulitzer Prize 2021 in Fiction for The Night Watchman?",
      a: "[a] Louise Erdrich",
      b: "[b] Armando Lucas Correa",
      c: "[c] Megan Miranda",
      d: "[d] Haruki Murakami",
      e: "[e] Kiley Reid",
      answer: "[a] Louise Erdrich",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.8) With which steel PSU has Energy Efficiency Services Limited signed an MoU for implementation of various energy efficiency and resources conservation measures in the steel sector and associated mining industry?",
      a: "[a] NMDC Ltd.",
      b: "[b] KIOCL Ltd.",
      c: "[c] Rashtriya Ispat Nigam Ltd.",
      d: "[d] MECON Ltd",
      e: "[e] SAIL",
      answer: "[d] MECON Ltd",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.9) Who has been appointed as the new brand ambassador of Mylab Discovery Solutions?",
      a: "[a] Alia Bhatt",
      b: "[b] Akshay Kumar",
      c: "[c] Varun Dhawan",
      d: "[d] Hrithik Roshan",
      e: "[e] Deepika Padukone",
      answer: "[b] Akshay Kumar",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.10) Which Indian journalist has received the Pulitzer Prize 2021 for exposing China’s detention camps?",
      a: "[a] P. Haridasan Pilllai",
      b: "[b] Rajesh Kumar Sahu",
      c: "[c] R. K. Bhati",
      d: "[d] Surendra Prasad",
      e: "[e] Megha Rajagoplan",
      answer: "[e] Megha Rajagoplan",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.1) What is the venue of G7 Summit 2021?",
      a: "[a] Carbis Bay",
      b: "[b] Montebello",
      c: "[c] Halifax",
      d: "[d] Williamsburg",
      e: "[e] Denver",
      answer: "[a] Carbis Bay",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.2) How many times has PM Narendra Modi been invited to the G7 summits?",
      a: "[a] Five",
      b: "[b] Three",
      c: "[c] One",
      d: "[d] Two",
      e: "[e] Four",
      answer: "[d] Two",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.3) Which of the following statement is not true about the TRIPS agreement?",
      a: "[a] TRIPS is an international legal agreement between all the member nations of the World Trade Organization",
      b: "[b] TRIPS stands for Agreement on Trade-Related Aspects of Intellectual Property Rights",
      c: "[c] TRIPS came into being, along with WTO, in 1997.",
      d: "[d] In 2001, Doha Declaration on the TRIPS Agreement and Public Health was adopted",
      e: "[e] In 2005, India came into compliance of TRIPS agreement.",
      answer: "[c] TRIPS came into being, along with WTO, in 1997.",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.4) Which country will establish a centre to develop vaccines for prevention of zoonotic disease, spreading from animals to humans, under the Carbis Bay Declaration?",
      a: "[a] Canada",
      b: "[b] US",
      c: "[c] UK",
      d: "[d] France",
      e: "[e] Italy",
      answer: "[c] UK",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.5) How much debt of developing countries will be reduced by the Build Back Better World (B3W) initiative?",
      a: "[a] $40 trillion",
      b: "[b] $2 trillion",
      c: "[c] $10 trillion",
      d: "[d] $15 trillion",
      e: "[e] $20 trillion",
      answer: "[a] $40 trillion",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.6) Which country hosted the 1st summit of G7?",
      a: "[a] France",
      b: "[b] Germany",
      c: "[c] Japan",
      d: "[d] Italy",
      e: "[e] USA",
      answer: "[a] France",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.7) Which institute has produced a 10-episode series on various aspects of Common Yoga Protocol which would be telecast on DD India at 7 pm from today till the 21st of this month?",
      a: "[a] Indian Institute Of Yoga And Naturopathy",
      b: "[b] Central Council for Research in Yoga & Naturopathy",
      c: "[c] The Yoga Institute Delhi",
      d: "[d] Morarji Desai National Institute of Yoga",
      e: "[e] All India Naturopathy and Yoga Education Council",
      answer: "[d] Morarji Desai National Institute of Yoga",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.8) Indian Coast Guard has been conducting “Operation Olivia”, every year since the early 1980s, to protect Olive Ridley turtles as they congregate along the ___ coast?",
      a: "[a] Karnataka",
      b: "[b] Kerala",
      c: "[c] Odisha",
      d: "[d] Tamil Nadu",
      e: "[e] Maharashtra",
      answer: "[c] Odisha",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.9) Which of the following is the proposed mission of European Space Agency for Venus?",
      a: "[a] Venus Express",
      b: "[b] Cassini",
      c: "[c] Akatsuki",
      d: "[d] EnVision",
      e: "[e] Venera",
      answer: "[d] EnVision",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.10) What is the theme of World Day Against Child Labour 2021?",
      a: "[a] Protect children from child labour, now more than ever",
      b: "[b] Act Now: End Child Labour",
      c: "[c] Children shouldn't work in fields, but on dreams",
      d: "[d] Generation Safe & Healthy",
      e: "[e] End child labour in supply chains – It's everyone's business!",
      answer: "[b] Act Now: End Child Labour",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.1) With which state has Flipkart partnered for ‘Medicines from the Sky’ project to deliver medicines by using drones to remote areas of state?",
      a: "[a] Telangana",
      b: "[b] Maharashtra",
      c: "[c] Madhya Pradesh",
      d: "[d] Kerala",
      e: "[e] Karnataka",
      answer: "[a] Telangana",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.2) How much increment was seen in the exports of organic products in 2020-21, as per the data of Ministry of Commerce?",
      a: "[a] 40%",
      b: "[b] 60%",
      c: "[c] 25%",
      d: "[d] 51%",
      e: "[e] 30%",
      answer: "[d] 51%",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.3) With which country has India signed an MoU to bring Indian domestic workers in the country within the ambit of a legal framework that streamlines their recruitment and provides them with the protection of the law?",
      a: "[a] Bahrain",
      b: "[b] Kuwait",
      c: "[c] Oman",
      d: "[d] Qatar",
      e: "[e] Saudi Arabia",
      answer: "[b] Kuwait",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.4) What is India’s rank in the Global House Price Index - Q1 2021 report of Knight Frank?",
      a: "[a] 60th",
      b: "[b] 88th",
      c: "[c] 35th",
      d: "[d] 55th",
      e: "[e] 20th",
      answer: "[d] 55th",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.5) How much wind capacity will be added by 2025 as per the “India Wind Energy Market Outlook 2025”?",
      a: "[a] 10 GW",
      b: "[b] 30 GW",
      c: "[c] 5.2 GW",
      d: "[d] 20 GW",
      e: "[e] 2.3 GW",
      answer: "[d] 20 GW",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.6) Google has announced to develop an open subsea cable to provide robust internet connectivity between US, Brazil, ___ and ___?",
      a: "[a] Uruguay",
      b: "[b] Argentina",
      c: "[c] Costa Rica",
      d: "[d] Both A and B",
      e: "[e] Both B and C",
      answer: "[d] Both A and B",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.7) Who has become the first woman to be appointed secretary-general of the United Nations Conference on Trade and Development?",
      a: "[a] Rebeca Grynspan",
      b: "[b] Betty Boothroy",
      c: "[c] Gwyneth Dunwoody",
      d: "[d] Doris Fisher",
      e: "[e] Peggy Fenner",
      answer: "[a] Rebeca Grynspan",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.8) Who is the chairperson of North-Eastern Council?",
      a: "[a] Secretary of Home Affairs",
      b: "[b] Union Minister of Home Affairs",
      c: "[c] Secretary of Ministry of Development of North Eastern Region",
      d: "[d] Union Minister of Ministry of Development of North Eastern Region",
      e: "[e] Secretary of Union Cabinet",
      answer: "[b] Union Minister of Home Affairs",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.9) When was UNCTAD established?",
      a: "[a] 1964",
      b: "[b] 1988",
      c: "[c] 2001",
      d: "[d] 2004",
      e: "[e] 1956",
      answer: "[a] 1964",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.10) Which of the following UN organ is not situated in New York?",
      a: "[a] Trusteeship Council",
      b: "[b] International Court of Justice",
      c: "[c] UN Economic and Social Council",
      d: "[d] Both A and B",
      e: "[e] Both B and C",
      answer: "[b] International Court of Justice",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.1) Which of the following is not a member of Confederation of Hospitality, Technology and Tourism Industry?",
      a: "[a] Oyo",
      b: "[b] Yatra",
      c: "[c] Airbnb",
      d: "[d] EaseMyTrip",
      e: "[e] MakeMyTrip",
      answer: "[e] MakeMyTrip",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.2) Which IIT has developed Early Cyclone Detection Technique for early detection of development or strengthening of tropical cyclones in the North Indian Ocean region?",
      a: "[a] IIT-Kanpur",
      b: "[b] IIT-Bombay",
      c: "[c] IIT-Delhi",
      d: "[d] IIT-Kharagpur",
      e: "[e] IIT-Madras",
      answer: "[d] IIT-Kharagpur",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.3) Which has become the first country in the world to adopt bitcoin as the legal tender?",
      a: "[a] Brazil",
      b: "[b] Mexico",
      c: "[c] El Salvador",
      d: "[d] Colombia",
      e: "[e] Puerto Rico",
      answer: "[c] El Salvador",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.4) How many children are into child labour at present, according to the “Child Labour: Global estimates 2020, trends and the road forward” report of ILO and UNICEF?",
      a: "[a] 110 million",
      b: "[b] 160 million",
      c: "[c] 230 million",
      d: "[d] 80 million",
      e: "[e] 70 million",
      answer: "[b] 160 million",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.5) Climate change would increase the poverty in India by __ percent in 2040, as per the ‘The Costs of Climate Change in India’ report?",
      a: "[a] 3.5%",
      b: "[b] 4.4%",
      c: "[c] 2.7%",
      d: "[d] 5.4%",
      e: "[e] 6.3%",
      answer: "[a] 3.5%",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.1) Which company has created the DNA matching software in Interpol’s ‘I-Familia’ global database?",
      a: "[a] Mellanox",
      b: "[b] Aladdin Knowledge Systems",
      c: "[c] NICE Systems",
      d: "[d] Smart Research",
      e: "[e] Tadiran Telecom",
      answer: "[d] Smart Research",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.2) Which of the following countries has been elected to the UN Economic and Social Council for the 2022-24 term, in the Asia-Pacific category, along with India?",
      a: "[a] Afghanistan",
      b: "[b] Oman",
      c: "[c] Kazakhstan",
      d: "[d] Only A and B",
      e: "[e] All of the Above",
      answer: "[e] All of the Above",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.3) As per the new tax pact agreed by G7 for taxing multinational companies, the minimum corporate tax threshold should be at least __ per cent?",
      a: "[a] 15%",
      b: "[b] 20%",
      c: "[c] 25%",
      d: "[d] 10%",
      e: "[e] 12%",
      answer: "[a] 15%",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.4) Which company has announced to develop world’s first carbon-neutral cement plant?",
      a: "[a] LafargeHolcim",
      b: "[b] Anhui Conch",
      c: "[c] Heidelberg Cement",
      d: "[d] Cemex",
      e: "[e] Italcementi",
      answer: "[c] Heidelberg Cement",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.5) Who has been appointed as the CEO of HSBC Bank India?",
      a: "[a] Anand Mohan Bajaj",
      b: "[b] Hitendra Dave",
      c: "[c] Sunita Sharma",
      d: "[d] N. Srinivasan",
      e: "[e] Baldeo Purushartha",
      answer: "[b] Hitendra Dave",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.1) Which is the expense sharing ratio between centre and state in the Seed Minikit Program respectively?",
      a: "[a] 60:40",
      b: "[b] 70:30",
      c: "[c] 20:80",
      d: "[d] 100:0",
      e: "[e] 50:50",
      answer: "[d] 100:0",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.2) What is the total food grain production estimate for 2020-21 as per the 3rd Advance Estimate of Principal Crops for 2020-21?",
      a: "[a] 277.20 million tonnes",
      b: "[b] 560.18 million tonnes",
      c: "[c] 333.89 million tonnes",
      d: "[d] 305.44 million tonnes",
      e: "[e] 102.29 million tonnes",
      answer: "[d] 305.44 million tonnes",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.3) How many total indicators were used in the Performance Grading Index (PGI) 2019-20?",
      a: "[a] 70",
      b: "[b] 100",
      c: "[c] 40",
      d: "[d] 25",
      e: "[e] 10",
      answer: "[a] 70",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.4) What is India’s rank in the State of India’s Environment Report 2021 of CSE?",
      a: "[a] 117",
      b: "[b] 58",
      c: "[c] 103",
      d: "[d] 166",
      e: "[e] 120",
      answer: "[a] 117",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.5) Who has been appointed as the President of FINA?",
      a: "[a] Husain Al Musallam",
      b: "[b] Sam Ramsamy",
      c: "[c] Daichi Suzuki",
      d: "[d] Algernon Cargill",
      e: "[e] Veronica Stanham",
      answer: "[a] Husain Al Musallam",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.1) How much assistance will be provided to the selected start-ups under the SAGE (Senior-care Aging Growth Engine) initiative of the govt?",
      a: "[a] Rs 1 crore",
      b: "[b] Rs 50 lakhs",
      c: "[c] Rs 2 crore",
      d: "[d] Rs 10 lakhs",
      e: "[e] Rs 90 lakhs",
      answer: "[a] Rs 1 crore",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.2) Recently, Indian Navy has decommissioned ‘INS Sandhayak’, after 40 years of service, at Naval Dockyard in Visakhapatnam. What kind of ship INS Sandhayak is?",
      a: "[a] Container Ships",
      b: "[b] Offshore Ships",
      c: "[c] Tanker Ships",
      d: "[d] Bulk Carrier",
      e: "[e] Hydrographic Survey Ship",
      answer: "[e] Hydrographic Survey Ship",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.3) Who is the MD and CEO of RBL Bank?",
      a: "[a] Vijoy Kumar Singh",
      b: "[b] Shashi Ranjan Kumar",
      c: "[c] Nihar Ranjan Dash",
      d: "[d] Vishwavir Ahuja",
      e: "[e] Sanjay Sharan",
      answer: "[d] Vishwavir Ahuja",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.4) Who has been elected to the board of the International Dairy Federation (IDF) from India?",
      a: "[a] RS Sodhi",
      b: "[b] Jogiranjan Panigrahi",
      c: "[c] Gaurav Kumar",
      d: "[d] Jenny Kiloung",
      e: "[e] Dipankar Dutta",
      answer: "[a] RS Sodhi",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.5) Which country is the global host of World Environment Day 2021?",
      a: "[a] Spain",
      b: "[b] India",
      c: "[c] Pakistan",
      d: "[d] Nepal",
      e: "[e] Vietnam",
      answer: "[c] Pakistan",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.1) How much financial assistance is provided to the patients under the Rashtriya Aarogya Nidhi for medical treatment at Government hospitals?",
      a: "[a] Rs 20 lakhs",
      b: "[b] Rs 15 lakhs",
      c: "[c] Rs 10 lakhs",
      d: "[d] Rs 25 lakhs",
      e: "[e] Rs 30 lakhs",
      answer: "[b] Rs 15 lakhs",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.2) When was the Central Govt Health Scheme launched?",
      a: "[a] 1983",
      b: "[b] 1999",
      c: "[c] 1954",
      d: "[d] 2001",
      e: "[e] 1993",
      answer: "[c] 1954",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.3) Which state has announced the creation of Special Purpose Vehicle (SPV) to ensure supply of potable water on a long term sustainable basis in rural areas of water quality affected districts?",
      a: "[a] Punjab",
      b: "[b] Maharashtra",
      c: "[c] Gujarat",
      d: "[d] Andhra Pradesh",
      e: "[e] Kerala",
      answer: "[a] Punjab",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.4) Which company has received a contract from Ministry of Defence for 11 airport surveillance radars for the Indian Navy and the Indian Coast Guard?",
      a: "[a] Hindustan Aeronautics Ltd.",
      b: "[b] Bharat Electronics Ltd",
      c: "[c] Mahindra Telephonics",
      d: "[d] Apollo Micro Systems",
      e: "[e] Astra Microwave Products",
      answer: "[c] Mahindra Telephonics",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.5) What is the Global unemployment rate forecast for 2021 by “World Employment and Social Outlook: Trends 2021” report of ILO?",
      a: "[a] 6.3%",
      b: "[b] 5.4%",
      c: "[c] 7.7%",
      d: "[d] 2.3%",
      e: "[e] 4.5%",
      answer: "[a] 6.3%",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.6) How much investment is being put in the nature-based solutions worldwide at present, as per the State of Finance for Nature report?",
      a: "[a] $145 billion",
      b: "[b] $180 billion",
      c: "[c] $170 billion",
      d: "[d] $133 billion",
      e: "[e] $203 billion",
      answer: "[d] $133 billion",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.7) Who heads the Expert Committee on Variable Capital Company set up by IFSCA to explore the potential for allowing variable capital company (VCC) to operate in the IFSCA?",
      a: "[a] Nihar Ranjan Dash",
      b: "[b] Sanjay Sharan",
      c: "[c] Dipankar Dutta",
      d: "[d] Kumar Padmapani Bora",
      e: "[e] K.P. Krishnan",
      answer: "[e] K.P. Krishnan",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.8) Which of the following statement is incorrect with respect to Rural Infrastructure Development Fund?",
      a: "[a] Government of India created the RIDF in NABARD in 1995-96, with an initial corpus of Rs.2,000 crore",
      b: "[b] There are 37 eligible activities under RIDF. The eligible activities are classified under four broad categories",
      c: "[c] The interest rates payable to banks on deposits placed with NABARD and loans disbursed by NABARD from RIDF have been linked to the Bank Rate",
      d: "[d] RIDF Loan is to be repaid in equal annual instalments within seven years from the date of withdrawal, including a grace period of two years",
      e: "[e] The implementation phase for projects sanctioned is spread over 2-5 years, varying with type of the project and also location of the State",
      answer:
        "[b] There are 37 eligible activities under RIDF. The eligible activities are classified under four broad categories",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.9) What is the corpus of on-tap liquidity set up by RBI for contact intensive sectors at repo rate?",
      a: "[a] Rs 10,000 crore",
      b: "[b] Rs 15,000 crore",
      c: "[c] Rs 25,000 crore",
      d: "[d] Rs 30,000 crore",
      e: "[e] Rs 40,000 crore",
      answer: "[b] Rs 15,000 crore",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.10) When is the International Day of Innocent Children Victims of Aggression observed?",
      a: "[a] June 4",
      b: "[b] June 20",
      c: "[c] June 6",
      d: "[d] June 15",
      e: "[e] June 10",
      answer: "[a] June 4",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.1) On which committee’s recommendation was the Financial Stability and Development Council created?",
      a: "[a] Y M Deosthalee Committee",
      b: "[b] Raghuram Rajan committee",
      c: "[c] U.C. Banerjee Commission",
      d: "[d] Thakkar Commission",
      e: "[e] Srikrishna Commission",
      answer: "[b] Raghuram Rajan committee",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.2) Who heads the expert group formed by Ministry of Labour and Employment to provide technical inputs and recommendations on fixation of minimum wages and national floor minimum wages?",
      a: "[a] Rahul Jain",
      b: "[b] Shoeb Samad",
      c: "[c] Arun Srivastava",
      d: "[d] Ajit Mishra",
      e: "[e] Sanjay Singh",
      answer: "[d] Ajit Mishra",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.3) Who is the convenor of 8 member group of ministers of the Goods and Services Tax (GST) Council?",
      a: "[a] Pankaj Kumar Devrani",
      b: "[b] Subrata Halder",
      c: "[c] R. N. Bharti",
      d: "[d] Conrad Sangma",
      e: "[e] Shyam Sundar Verma",
      answer: "[d] Conrad Sangma",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.4) Which country has launched Fengyun-4B weather satellite?",
      a: "[a] Japan",
      b: "[b] France",
      c: "[c] Republic of Korea",
      d: "[d] China",
      e: "[e] Saudi Arabia",
      answer: "[d] China",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.5) Davinci+ and Veritas are the planned mission of NASA to which planet?",
      a: "[a] Venus",
      b: "[b] Neptune",
      c: "[c] Saturn",
      d: "[d] Jupiter",
      e: "[e] Mars",
      answer: "[a] Venus",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.6) Who has been appointed as Chair of WHO Executive Board 2021-22?",
      a: "[a] Charles Michel",
      b: "[b] Alexander De Croo",
      c: "[c] Andrej Plenković Croatia",
      d: "[d] Patrick Amoth",
      e: "[e] Sebastian Kurz",
      answer: "[d] Patrick Amoth",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.7) Who has won the International Booker Prize 2021?",
      a: "[a] Mette Frederiksen",
      b: "[b] Rumen Radev",
      c: "[c] David Diop",
      d: "[d] Alexander De Croo",
      e: "[e] Mario Draghi",
      answer: "[c] David Diop",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.1) Which IIT has developed a first-of-its-kind Internet of Things (IoT) device – AmbiTag?",
      a: "[a] IIT-Delhi",
      b: "[b] IIT-Ropar",
      c: "[c] IIT-Kharagpur",
      d: "[d] IIT-Roorkie",
      e: "[e] IIT-Hyderabad",
      answer: "[b] IIT-Ropar",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.2) With which airline company has J&K UT govt signed an MoU for the transportation of perishable horticulture and agricultural produce to various destinations across the country?",
      a: "[a] Daman & Diu and Dadra & Haveli",
      b: "[b] Puducherry",
      c: "[c] Andaman and Nicobar",
      d: "[d] Delhi",
      e: "[e] Jammu and Kashmir",
      answer: "[e] Jammu and Kashmir",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.3) Who has become the first Indian to be elected as the president of the International Narcotics Control Board?",
      a: "[a] Jagjit Pavadia",
      b: "[b] Nivedita Pandey",
      c: "[c] Kirti Sharma",
      d: "[d] Akansha Singh",
      e: "[e] Purvi Chandela",
      answer: "[a] Jagjit Pavadia",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.4) Who has won the men’s singles at the 2021 Emilia-Romagna Open (Tennis) held in Italy?",
      a: "[a] Rafael Nadal",
      b: "[b] Novak Djokovic",
      c: "[c] Sebastian Korda",
      d: "[d] Andre Agassi",
      e: "[e] Andy Murray",
      answer: "[c] Sebastian Korda",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.5) Who is the author of “All Roads Lead North: Nepal's Turn to China”?",
      a: "[a] Jay Karan Singh",
      b: "[b] Shakuntla",
      c: "[c] Amish Raj Mulmi",
      d: "[d] Gaurav Kumar",
      e: "[e] Hemant kumar Nanda",
      answer: "[c] Amish Raj Mulmi",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.1) Which of the following statement is not true about PM CARES for Children scheme?",
      a: "[a] PM CARES will contribute through a specially designed scheme to create a corpus of Rs 10 lakh for each child when he or she reaches 18 years of age",
      b: "[b] The child will be given admission in any Central Government residential school such as Sainik School, Navodaya Vidyalaya etc.",
      c: "[c] If the child is admitted in a private school, the fees as per the RTE norms will be given from the PM CARES",
      d: "[d] All children will be enrolled as a beneficiary under Ayushman Bharat Scheme (PM-JAY) with a health insurance cover of Rs. 5 lakhs.",
      e: "[e] None of the Above",
      answer: "[e] None of the Above",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.2) What is the GDP forecast for India for FY22?",
      a: "[a] 8.9%",
      b: "[b] 6.7%",
      c: "[c] 4.5%",
      d: "[d] 9.9%",
      e: "[e] 10.2%",
      answer: "[d] 9.9%",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.3) Who has been appointed as the interim chief of the Central Board of Direct Taxes?",
      a: "[a] Sadanand",
      b: "[b] Agam Mittal",
      c: "[c] V.D Jaswani",
      d: "[d] J.B. Mohapatra",
      e: "[e] Vikash Sheel",
      answer: "[d] J.B. Mohapatra",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.4) Who is the President of CII for 2021-22?",
      a: "[a] Rakesh Kumar",
      b: "[b] Manohar Agnani",
      c: "[c] T V Narendran",
      d: "[d] B.Shobha",
      e: "[e] Harish Lugani",
      answer: "[c] T V Narendran",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.5) How many defence goods will be indigenously produced in India by 2025 as per the 2nd list of Defence Indigenization Goods?",
      a: "[a] 141",
      b: "[b] 150",
      c: "[c] 108",
      d: "[d] 123",
      e: "[e] 167",
      answer: "[c] 108",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.1) What is the name of the online tracking portal launched by National Commission for Protection of Child Rights for children in need of care and protection?",
      a: "[a] Bal Swaraj",
      b: "[b] Bal Suraksha",
      c: "[c] Bal Abhiyan",
      d: "[d] Bal Vikas",
      e: "[e] Bal Protsahan",
      answer: "[a] Bal Swaraj",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.2) Who heads the Empowered Group on Vaccination formed by Central Govt?",
      a: "[a] Amitabh Kant",
      b: "[b] Ajay Seth",
      c: "[c] VK Paul",
      d: "[d] Amit Khare",
      e: "[e] Balram Bhargava",
      answer: "[c] VK Paul",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.3) Which state has launched Udaan scheme to provide free sanitary napkins to needy girls and women across the state?",
      a: "[a] Punjab",
      b: "[b] Maharashtra",
      c: "[c] Gujarat",
      d: "[d] West Bengal",
      e: "[e] Karnataka",
      answer: "[a] Punjab",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.4) National Security Advisor (NSA) Ajit Doval has commissioned the Indian Coast Guard (ICG) Offshore Patrol Vessel (OPV) Sajag, which has been constructed by Goa Shipyard Limited. Sajag is the ___ in a series of five offshore patrol vessels indigenously designed by GSL?",
      a: "[a] first",
      b: "[b] fifth",
      c: "[c] fourth",
      d: "[d] third",
      e: "[e] second",
      answer: "[d] third",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.5) Who has been elected as the Asia-Oceania representative at the 2021 International Association of Ultrarunners (IAU) Congress?",
      a: "[a] Radha Venkatesan",
      b: "[b] Nagraj Adiga",
      c: "[c] D. K. OJHA",
      d: "[d] Charan Jeet Singh Nirman",
      e: "[e] Nivedita Gupta",
      answer: "[b] Nagraj Adiga",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.) Who has won the International Dublin Literary Award 2021 for 'Lost Children Archive' novel?",
      a: "[a] Valeria Luiselli",
      b: "[b] Hilary Mantel",
      c: "[c] Eleanor Catton",
      d: "[d] Howard Jacobson",
      e: "[e] Aravind Adiga",
      answer: "[a] Valeria Luiselli",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.2) Which IIT has developed the unique detector named ‘FakeBuster’, along with Australia based Monash University, to detect imposters attending a virtual conference without anybody’s knowledge?",
      a: "[a] IIT-Bombay",
      b: "[b] IIT-Madras",
      c: "[c] IIT-Delhi",
      d: "[d] IIT-Kharagpur",
      e: "[e] IIT-Ropar",
      answer: "[e] IIT-Ropar",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.3) Which of the following organizations collaborated to develop world’s first satellite-based monitoring system for coral reefs?",
      a: "[a] Arizona State University",
      b: "[b] National Geographic Society",
      c: "[c] Vulcan",
      d: "[d] University of Queensland",
      e: "[e] All of the Above",
      answer: "[e] All of the Above",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.4) Which company has developed “first of its kind” crypto lending model in India?",
      a: "[a] Binance India",
      b: "[b] WazirX",
      c: "[c] Coinbase",
      d: "[d] ZebPay",
      e: "[e] Bitfinex",
      answer: "[d] ZebPay",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.5) When is the International Day of UN Peacekeepers observed?",
      a: "[a] May 29",
      b: "[b] October 10",
      c: "[c] August 13",
      d: "[d] June 14",
      e: "[e] July 17",
      answer: "[a] May 29",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.1) Which IIM has partnered with German companies - GIZ and BMZ - to identify the challenges caused by Covid-19 pandemic across various sectors and find measures for them?",
      a: "[a] IIM-Calcutta",
      b: "[b] IIM-Ahmedabad",
      c: "[c] IIM-Bangalore",
      d: "[d] IIM-Lucknow",
      e: "[e] IIM-Indore",
      answer: "[e] IIM-Indore",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.2) Which of the following organization is getting support from the Department of Biotechnology under Mission Covid Suraksha for developing Covid vaccine?",
      a: "[a] Haffkine Biopharmaceutical Corporation",
      b: "[b] Bharat biotech International Ltd",
      c: "[c] Biological E.",
      d: "[d] Biomed Pvt. Ltd",
      e: "[e] Cadila healthcare",
      answer: "[a] Haffkine Biopharmaceutical Corporation",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.3) Which state has launched an online portal named “Akansha” to provide details of all the Corporate Social Responsibility projects or activities, being carried out, in the state?",
      a: "[a] Uttar Pradesh",
      b: "[b] Bihar",
      c: "[c] Uttarakhand",
      d: "[d] Himachal Pradesh",
      e: "[e] Karnataka",
      answer: "[e] Karnataka",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.4) Which state has launched Ankur scheme to reward citizens for planting trees during monsoon?",
      a: "[a] Madhya Pradesh",
      b: "[b] Arunachal Pradesh",
      c: "[c] Odisha",
      d: "[d] Telangana",
      e: "[e] West Bengal",
      answer: "[a] Madhya Pradesh",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.5) Which state / UT has launched the Special Assistance Scheme for Covid Mortalities (SASCM) scheme for providing financial assistance to families, who lost their only bread earner to the Coronavirus pandemic?",
      a: "[a] Ladakh",
      b: "[b] Delhi",
      c: "[c] Lakshadweep",
      d: "[d] Jammu & Kashmir",
      e: "[e] Andaman and Nicobar",
      answer: "[d] Jammu & Kashmir",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.6) National Technology Centre for Ports Waterways and Coasts - the technology arm of the Ministry of Ports, Shipping and Waterways – is located at which IIT?",
      a: "[a] IIT-Kanpur",
      b: "[b] IIT-Delhi",
      c: "[c] IIT-Madras",
      d: "[d] IIT-Bombay",
      e: "[e] IIT-Kharagpur",
      answer: "[c] IIT-Madras",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.7) Which country’s Met Office has partnered World Meteorological Organization for releasing the Global Annual to Decadal Climate Update?",
      a: "[a] UK",
      b: "[b] Germany",
      c: "[c] Sweden",
      d: "[d] Norway",
      e: "[e] Netherland",
      answer: "[a] UK",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.8) Which team won the UEFA Women’s Champions League 2021?",
      a: "[a] Arsenal",
      b: "[b] Barcelona FC",
      c: "[c] Manchester City",
      d: "[d] Birmingham City",
      e: "[e] Tottenham Hotspur",
      answer: "[b] Barcelona FC",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.9) Who among the following is known as the China's 'father of hybrid rice'?",
      a: "[a] Ba Denian",
      b: "[b] Cai Xitao",
      c: "[c] Chang Chi-yun",
      d: "[d] T. T. Chang",
      e: "[e] Yuan Longping",
      answer: "[e] Yuan Longping",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.10) Who is the author of “India and Asian Geopolitics: The Past, Present” book?",
      a: "[a] Amar Pal",
      b: "[b] Shivshankar Menon",
      c: "[c] Kimjamlhing Changloi",
      d: "[d] Sharad Saxena",
      e: "[e] K R Shyam Babu",
      answer: "[b] Shivshankar Menon",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.1) When was One-Stop Centres (OSC) — Sakhi – scheme launched?",
      a: "[a] 2013",
      b: "[b] 2015",
      c: "[c] 2009",
      d: "[d] 2011",
      e: "[e] 2016",
      answer: "[b] 2015",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.2) Where is India's first city-wide environmental surveillance platform for COVID -‘Precision Health Platform’ - launched?",
      a: "[a] Ajmer",
      b: "[b] Agra",
      c: "[c] Bengaluru",
      d: "[d] Guwahati",
      e: "[e] Imphal",
      answer: "[c] Bengaluru",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.3) NASA is planning to send its first mobile robot named Volatiles Investigating Polar Exploration Rover (VIPER) to which planet?",
      a: "[a] Solar",
      b: "[b] Lunar",
      c: "[c] Jupiter",
      d: "[d] Neptune",
      e: "[e] Venus",
      answer: "[b] Lunar",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.4) Who has become the first-ever Indian medical practitioner to receive the Rudolf V. Schindler Award from the American Society of Gastrointestinal Endoscopy?",
      a: "[a] D Nageshwar Reddy",
      b: "[b] Uttank Joshi",
      c: "[c] P. Rangarajan",
      d: "[d] Bharti Kashyap Sharma",
      e: "[e] Rajesh Talwar",
      answer: "[a] D Nageshwar Reddy",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.5) Who has won the 13th International Eni Award 2020 from India?",
      a: "[a] C.N.R. Rao",
      b: "[b] Tuntuni Chowdhry",
      c: "[c] R. K. Bhati",
      d: "[d] Bidisha Sengupta",
      e: "[e] Pranav Prakash",
      answer: "[a] C.N.R. Rao",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.1) Who is the President of Indian Broadcasting Foundation?",
      a: "[a] R. K. Dhawan",
      b: "[b] Sanjay Pandey",
      c: "[c] Anita Baghel",
      d: "[d] K Madhavan",
      e: "[e] Gyan Bhushan",
      answer: "[d] K Madhavan",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.2) How much financial assistance will be provided to the authors selected under the YUVA scheme for six months?",
      a: "[a] Rs 15,000 per month",
      b: "[b] Rs 20,000 per month",
      c: "[c] Rs 50,000 per month",
      d: "[d] Rs 30,000 per month",
      e: "[e] Rs 40,000 per month",
      answer: "[c] Rs 50,000 per month",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.3) Who is the convener of the 7- member Panel of State Ministers set up by GOI for better valuation of services of casinos, online gaming portal and race courses for levying Goods and Services Tax?",
      a: "[a] Madan Lal",
      b: "[b] Fakhre Alam",
      c: "[c] Bibhuti Bhushana Dash",
      d: "[d] Nitin Patel",
      e: "[e] Santosh Shilpokar",
      answer: "[d] Nitin Patel",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.4) How much GST is levied on services of casinos, horse racing and online gaming at present?",
      a: "[a] 18%",
      b: "[b] 12%",
      c: "[c] 5%",
      d: "[d] 28%",
      e: "[e] 20%",
      answer: "[a] 18%",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.5) Who has recorded the world’s fastest ascent of Everest by a woman with a time of just 25 hours and 50 minutes?",
      a: "[a] Tsang Yin-hung",
      b: "[b] Melissa Arnot",
      c: "[c] Junko Tabei",
      d: "[d] Pasang Lhamu Sherpa",
      e: "[e] Lydia Bradey",
      answer: "[a] Tsang Yin-hung",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.6) What is the name of the exercise conducted by NATO members across the Atlantic, through Europe and into the Black Sea region?",
      a: "[a] Mainbrace- 21",
      b: "[b] Steadfast Defender 21",
      c: "[c] Grand Repulse 21",
      d: "[d] Italic Weld 21",
      e: "[e] Longstep 21",
      answer: "[b] Steadfast Defender 21",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.7) How much amount is RBI transferring to the Central Government for 2020-21, as per its Annual Report for 2020-21?",
      a: "[a] Rs 57,000 crores",
      b: "[b] Rs. 99,122 crores",
      c: "[c] Rs 80,000 crores",
      d: "[d] Rs 60,190 crores",
      e: "[e] Rs 45,150 crores",
      answer: "[b] Rs. 99,122 crores",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.8) Bashar Al-Assad has sworn in as the President of which country?",
      a: "[a] South Africa",
      b: "[b] Syria",
      c: "[c] Oman",
      d: "[d] Kenya",
      e: "[e] Morocco",
      answer: "[b] Syria",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.9) Which section of RBI Act, 1934 allows the transfer of surplus RBI funds to the Central Govt?",
      a: "[a] Section 47",
      b: "[b] Section 75",
      c: "[c] Section 90",
      d: "[d] Section 30",
      e: "[e] Section 55",
      answer: "[a] Section 47",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.10) What is the capital of Syria?",
      a: "[a] Damascus",
      b: "[b] Nairobi",
      c: "[c] Accra",
      d: "[d] Dodoma",
      e: "[e] Kinshasa",
      answer: "[a] Damascus",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.1) Which is the first Indian state to join the global COVAX alliance for sourcing the immunisation shots at the best price?",
      a: "[a] Telangana",
      b: "[b] Tamil Nadu",
      c: "[c] Punjab",
      d: "[d] Maharashtra",
      e: "[e] Gujarat",
      answer: "[c] Punjab",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.2) Which state has launched “Swasthya Aahar Yojana” for providing healthy food to the covid-19 patients?",
      a: "[a] Madhya Pradesh",
      b: "[b] Karnataka",
      c: "[c] Kerala",
      d: "[d] Assam",
      e: "[e] Uttarakhand",
      answer: "[a] Madhya Pradesh",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.3) Who has created a world record by scaling Mount Everest twice in the just 4 days?",
      a: "[a] Junko Tabei",
      b: "[b] Nawang Gombu",
      c: "[c] Lhakpa Sherpa",
      d: "[d] Mingma Tenji Sherpa",
      e: "[e] Sungdare Sherpa",
      answer: "[d] Mingma Tenji Sherpa",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.4) When was the Special Window for Affordable and Mid-Income Housing (SWAMIH) Fund scheme launched?",
      a: "[a] 2018",
      b: "[b] 2019",
      c: "[c] 2020",
      d: "[d] 2017",
      e: "[e] 2016",
      answer: "[b] 2019",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.5) Which of the following company has acquired Indiabulls Asset Management Company Ltd and Indiabulls Trustee Company Ltd?",
      a: "[a] Nextbillion Technology Pvt. Ltd",
      b: "[b] HCL Infosystems",
      c: "[c] CK Birla Group",
      d: "[d] Intex Technologies",
      e: "[e] Iris Computers",
      answer: "[a] Nextbillion Technology Pvt. Ltd",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.6) Which football club has won the Premier League 2020-21 (football)?",
      a: "[a] Arsenal",
      b: "[b] Manchester City",
      c: "[c] Bayern München",
      d: "[d] Manchester United",
      e: "[e] Paris Saint-Germain",
      answer: "[b] Manchester City",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.7) With which field Roman Khassanov related to?",
      a: "[a] Archery",
      b: "[b] Badminton",
      c: "[c] Volleyball",
      d: "[d] Tennis",
      e: "[e] Baseball",
      answer: "[d] Tennis",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.8) What is the corpus of SWAMIH Fund?",
      a: "[a] Rs 50,000 crores",
      b: "[b] Rs 25,000 crores",
      c: "[c] Rs 35,000 crores",
      d: "[d] Rs 30,000 crores",
      e: "[e] Rs 40,000 crores",
      answer: "[b] Rs 25,000 crores",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.9) What is the theme of International Day of Families 2021?",
      a: "[a] Families and New Technologies",
      b: "[b] Families in Development: Copenhagen & Beijing + 25",
      c: "[c] Families and Climate Action: Focus on SDG13",
      d: "[d] Families and inclusive societies",
      e: "[e] Families, education and well-being",
      answer: "[a] Families and New Technologies",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.10) Which year is International Year of the Family?",
      a: "[a] 2021",
      b: "[b] 2024",
      c: "[c] 2027",
      d: "[d] 2025",
      e: "[e] 2030",
      answer: "[b] 2024",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.1) What is the name of the helpline launched by National Commission for Protection of Child Rights to provide psychological first-aid and emotional support to children affected during COVID-19 Pandemic?",
      a: "[a] SAMVEDNA",
      b: "[b] DRISHTI",
      c: "[c] SANYAM",
      d: "[d] JYOTI",
      e: "[e] PRAGATI",
      answer: "[a] SAMVEDNA",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.2) Which of the following university collaborated with Department of Science and Technology for conducting the BRICS Astronomy Working Group (BAWG)?",
      a: "[a] Indian Institute of Science",
      b: "[b] Indian Institute of Astrophysics",
      c: "[c] Inter-University Centre for Astronomy and Astrophysics",
      d: "[d] National Centre for Radio Astrophysics",
      e: "[e] Indian Institute of Space Science and Technology",
      answer: "[c] Inter-University Centre for Astronomy and Astrophysics",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.3) As per the Indian Insurance Companies (Foreign Investment) Rules, 2021, the foreign direct investment limit in the insurance sector has been increased from __ to ___?",
      a: "[a] 49% to 74%",
      b: "[b] 23% to 55%",
      c: "[c] 37% to 65%",
      d: "[d] 45% to 66%",
      e: "[e] 71% to 100%",
      answer: "[a] 49% to 74%",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.4) Which company has launched 'School of Hope and Empowerment' (S.H.E.) as its CSR project at the 2021 UNESCO World Conference on Education for Sustainable Development?",
      a: "[a] Larsen and Toubro",
      b: "[b] Alphabet Inc",
      c: "[c] JSW Steel Ltd",
      d: "[d] Tata Communications",
      e: "[e] IBM",
      answer: "[d] Tata Communications",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.5) Which has become the first Small Finance Bank to offer online account opening services to its NRI customers?",
      a: "[a] Ujjivan Small Finance Bank",
      b: "[b] Janalakshmi Small Finance Bank",
      c: "[c] A U Small Finance Bank",
      d: "[d] Equitas Small Finance Bank",
      e: "[e] Utkarsh Small Finance Bank",
      answer: "[d] Equitas Small Finance Bank",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.1) Which of the following helpline has been launched by Ministry of Social Justice & Empowerment to address the problems of elders in the context of the ongoing COVID pandemic?",
      a: "[a] Elderline",
      b: "[b] Helpdesk",
      c: "[c] Ask Eld",
      d: "[d] Vayo Mitra",
      e: "[e] Vayovridha",
      answer: "[a] Elderline",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.2) MyGov has partnered with Department of Higher Education to launch an innovation challenge for creating ___ App?",
      a: "[a] Startup Incubation App",
      b: "[b] Covid Response App",
      c: "[c] Vaccine Registration App",
      d: "[d] Indian Language Learning App",
      e: "[e] International Scholarship Information App",
      answer: "[d] Indian Language Learning App",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.3) With which country has India renewed its MoU on military cooperation and maritime cooperation?",
      a: "[a] Qatar",
      b: "[b] Oman",
      c: "[c] Saudi Arabia",
      d: "[d] Israel",
      e: "[e] Egypt",
      answer: "[b] Oman",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.4) According to the latest estimates published by the WHO and International Labour Organization (ILO) in Environment International, working ___ hours or more per week is a serious health hazard?",
      a: "[a] 55 hours",
      b: "[b] 35 hours",
      c: "[c] 60 hours",
      d: "[d] 45 hours",
      e: "[e] 70 hours",
      answer: "[a] 55 hours",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.5) Which has become the world’s first country to ban all synthetic cannabinoid substances?",
      a: "[a] Japan",
      b: "[b] South Korea",
      c: "[c] Russia",
      d: "[d] China",
      e: "[e] Israel",
      answer: "[d] China",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.1) Which state has launched ‘Sanjeevani Pariyojana’ to provide medical care to people in district in home isolation and having mild and moderate Covid-19 symptoms?",
      a: "[a] Maharashtra",
      b: "[b] Gujarat",
      c: "[c] Tamil Nadu",
      d: "[d] Haryana",
      e: "[e] Punjab",
      answer: "[d] Haryana",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.2) Who is the President of FIH?",
      a: "[a] Thierry Weil",
      b: "[b] Fumio Ogura",
      c: "[c] Narinder Batra",
      d: "[d] Marijke Fleuren",
      e: "[e] Clare Prideaux",
      answer: "[c] Narinder Batra",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.3) Who has been appointed as the CEO of Reserve Bank Innovation Hub?",
      a: "[a] Gyan Bhushan",
      b: "[b] Rajesh Bansal",
      c: "[c] R. K. Bhati",
      d: "[d] Pranav Prakash",
      e: "[e] Susheela Tigga",
      answer: "[b] Rajesh Bansal",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.4) Which of the following has won the Best Biodiversity Management Committee award at the 5th edition of India Biodiversity Awards?",
      a: "[a] Shergaon BMC",
      b: "[b] Changlang BMC",
      c: "[c] Kra Daadi BMC",
      d: "[d] Kurung Kumey BMC",
      e: "[e] Itanagar BMC",
      answer: "[a] Shergaon BMC",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.5) Which lab of DRDO has developed 'DIPCOVAN' - an antibody detection kit for SARS-CoV-2 virus?",
      a: "[a] Defence Avionics Research Establishment",
      b: "[b] Defence Institute of Bio-Energy Research",
      c: "[c] Defence Institute of High Altitude Research",
      d: "[d] Defence Institute of Physiology and Allied Sciences",
      e: "[e] Defence Scientific Information & Documentation Centre",
      answer: "[d] Defence Institute of Physiology and Allied Sciences",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.1) Which country hosted the Summit on Financing African Economies 2021?",
      a: "[a] France",
      b: "[b] Russia",
      c: "[c] Poland",
      d: "[d] Nigeria",
      e: "[e] Ethiopia",
      answer: "[a] France",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.2) What is India’s rank in the “Renewable Energy Country Attractiveness Index” (RECAI) 2021?",
      a: "[a] 103",
      b: "[b] 3",
      c: "[c] 57",
      d: "[d] 88",
      e: "[e] 15",
      answer: "[b] 3",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.3) What is the total number of internally displaced people at the end of 2020, as per the 2021 Global Report on Internal Displacement (GRID): Internal Displacement in Changing Climate report?",
      a: "[a] 30 million",
      b: "[b] 23 million",
      c: "[c] 40 million",
      d: "[d] 55 million",
      e: "[e] 60 million",
      answer: "[d] 55 million",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.4) Which is the top ranked Indian city in the “Prime Global Cities Index: Q1 2021” report of Knight Frank?",
      a: "[a] Bangalore",
      b: "[b] Ahmedabad",
      c: "[c] Delhi",
      d: "[d] Mumbai",
      e: "[e] Chennai",
      answer: "[c] Delhi",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.5) When is the World Bee Day observed?",
      a: "[a] May 23",
      b: "[b] May 20",
      c: "[c] May 11",
      d: "[d] May 6",
      e: "[e] May 10",
      answer: "[b] May 20",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.6) Which country has developed Simurgh supercomputer?",
      a: "[a] Turkey",
      b: "[b] Israel",
      c: "[c] Lebanon",
      d: "[d] Iran",
      e: "[e] Egypt",
      answer: "[d] Iran",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.7) Where is the Megalithic site of Hire Benkal located?",
      a: "[a] Madhya Pradesh",
      b: "[b] Gujarat",
      c: "[c] Karnataka",
      d: "[d] Kerala",
      e: "[e] Odisha",
      answer: "[c] Karnataka",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.8) Malerkotla is the 23rd district of which state?",
      a: "[a] Karnataka",
      b: "[b] Odisha",
      c: "[c] Andhra Pradesh",
      d: "[d] Telangana",
      e: "[e] Punjab",
      answer: "[e] Punjab",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.9) What is the maximum value limit of a prepaid Gift PPI instrument?",
      a: "[a] Rs 2,000",
      b: "[b] Rs 6,000",
      c: "[c] Rs 7,000",
      d: "[d] Rs 5,000",
      e: "[e] Rs 10,000",
      answer: "[e] Rs 10,000",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.10) Which bank has launched Loan Processing System (LPS), a fully digitised loan processing system, for MSME and Agri products?",
      a: "[a] HDFC Bank",
      b: "[b] IDBI Bank",
      c: "[c] SBI",
      d: "[d] PNB",
      e: "[e] Kotak Mahindra Bank",
      answer: "[b] IDBI Bank",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.1) Which state has launched Amrit Vahini website, app and the related chatbot to help people book hospital beds online?",
      a: "[a] Tripura",
      b: "[b] Jharkhand",
      c: "[c] Himachal Pradesh",
      d: "[d] Uttarakhand",
      e: "[e] Odisha",
      answer: "[b] Jharkhand",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.2) Which state has signed an MoU with the National Health Authority (NHA) for the implementation of Ayushman Bharat (Pradhan Mantri Jan Arogya Yojana) scheme in the State?",
      a: "[a] Telangana",
      b: "[b] Delhi",
      c: "[c] West Bengal",
      d: "[d] Odisha",
      e: "[e] Jammu and Kashmir",
      answer: "[a] Telangana",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.3) Which nation has launched the Haiyang-2D satellite?",
      a: "[a] Republic of Korea",
      b: "[b] China",
      c: "[c] Japan",
      d: "[d] Mongolia",
      e: "[e] Russia",
      answer: "[b] China",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.4) Who has won the 2020 Millennium Technology Prize?",
      a: "[a] Shankar Balasubramanian",
      b: "[b] David Klenerman",
      c: "[c] Shankar Maheshwari",
      d: "[d] Both A and B",
      e: "[e] Both B and C",
      answer: "[d] Both A and B",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.5) Which state has topped in establishing Health and Wellness Centres under Ayushman Bharat Program in 2020-21?",
      a: "[a] Karnataka",
      b: "[b] Kerala",
      c: "[c] Maharashtra",
      d: "[d] Assam",
      e: "[e] Uttar Pradesh",
      answer: "[a] Karnataka",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.1) Recently, India renewed its Cultural Exchange Programme (CEP) with a country till 2023?",
      a: "[a] Afghanistan",
      b: "[b] Mongolia",
      c: "[c] Philippines",
      d: "[d] Thailand",
      e: "[e] Maldives",
      answer: "[b] Mongolia",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.2) Which city is the healthiest city in the country as per the “State Of Indian Healthcare Indian Cities Through The Lens Of Healthcare 2021” report?",
      a: "[a] Kolkata",
      b: "[b] Pune",
      c: "[c] Ahmedabad",
      d: "[d] Mumbai",
      e: "[e] Delhi",
      answer: "[b] Pune",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.3) Where is the India's first Agriculture Export Facilitation Centre established?",
      a: "[a] Nagpur",
      b: "[b] Amravati",
      c: "[c] Aurangabad",
      d: "[d] Pune",
      e: "[e] Nashik",
      answer: "[d] Pune",
    },
    {
      question:
        'Q.4) Which bank has launched “I choose my number" feature for all its customers across India?',
      a: "[a] Capital Small Finance Bank",
      b: "[b] Jana Small Finance Bank",
      c: "[c] Equitas Small Finance Bank",
      d: "[d] A U Small Finance Bank",
      e: "[e] Suryoday Small Finance Bank",
      answer: "[b] Jana Small Finance Bank",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.5) What is the theme of UN Global Road Safety Week 2021?",
      a: "[a] SpeakUp to save lives",
      b: "[b] Improving global road safety",
      c: "[c] Leadership for RoadSafety",
      d: "[d] Save Lives – #SlowDown",
      e: "[e] Streets for Life",
      answer: "[e] Streets for Life",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.1) How many Indian cities are most vulnerable cities as per Verisk Maplecroft Global Risk Analytics Dataset?",
      a: "[a] 57",
      b: "[b] 30",
      c: "[c] 43",
      d: "[d] 40",
      e: "[e] 25",
      answer: "[c] 43",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.2) Which multilateral bank has made its highest ever annual lending commitment of USD 3.92 billion to India in 2020?",
      a: "[a] European Investment Bank",
      b: "[b] Asian Development Bank",
      c: "[c] International Monetary Fund",
      d: "[d] World Bank",
      e: "[e] European Central Bank",
      answer: "[b] Asian Development Bank",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.3) Who has been appointed as the CEO of BATA India?",
      a: "[a] Gunjan Shah",
      b: "[b] Santosh Kumar",
      c: "[c] Anita Baghel",
      d: "[d] Gyan Bhushan",
      e: "[e] Madan Lal",
      answer: "[a] Gunjan Shah",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.4) Who has topped the Fortune’s world’s 50 greatest leaders 2021 list?",
      a: "[a] Justin Trudeau",
      b: "[b] Emmanuel Macron",
      c: "[c] Jacinda Ardern",
      d: "[d] Shimon Peres",
      e: "[e] Joe Biden",
      answer: "[c] Jacinda Ardern",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.5) Who has won the Whitley Award 2021?",
      a: "[a] Ridhima Pandey",
      b: "[b] Aditya Mukarji",
      c: "[c] Licypriya Kangujam",
      d: "[d] Nuklu Phom",
      e: "[e] Anadish Pal",
      answer: "[d] Nuklu Phom",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.1) With which company has Ministry of Tribal Affairs signed an MoU for digital transformation of Tribal Schools such as Eklavya Model Residential Schools and Ashram Schools?",
      a: "[a] IBM",
      b: "[b] Intel",
      c: "[c] Adobe",
      d: "[d] Microsoft",
      e: "[e] Apple",
      answer: "[d] Microsoft",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.2) Who among the following has become the first Indian woman to summit Mount Pumori?",
      a: "[a] Baljeet Kaur",
      b: "[b] Gunbala Sharma",
      c: "[c] Nitu Pathak",
      d: "[d] Both A and B",
      e: "[e] Both B and C",
      answer: "[d] Both A and B",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.3) Which company has launched world’s first private digital court?",
      a: "[a] Intello Labs",
      b: "[b] HyperVerge",
      c: "[c] Niki.ai",
      d: "[d] Jupitice Justice Technologies",
      e: "[e] Artivatic.ai",
      answer: "[d] Jupitice Justice Technologies",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.4) In which state is 'Vaidya Aapke Dwar' scheme launched by Department of AYUSH to provide free medical consultation through video call?",
      a: "[a] Uttarakhand",
      b: "[b] Madhya Pradesh",
      c: "[c] Maharashtra",
      d: "[d] Gujarat",
      e: "[e] Tamil Nadu",
      answer: "[b] Madhya Pradesh",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.5) In which state has AYUSH Department launched 'AYUSH Ghar Dwar' for COVID-19 patients?",
      a: "[a] Odisha",
      b: "[b] Telangana",
      c: "[c] Andhra Pradesh",
      d: "[d] Himachal Pradesh",
      e: "[e] Arunachal Pradesh",
      answer: "[d] Himachal Pradesh",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.1) COVID-19 Crisis Through a Migration Lens report?",
      a: "[a] $83 billion",
      b: "[b] $97 billion",
      c: "[c] $67 billion",
      d: "[d] $102 billion",
      e: "[e] $23 billion",
      answer: "[a] $83 billion",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.2) What is the name of the portal launched by NITI Aayog to monitor the aid received by the govt of India for fighting the Covid-19 pandemic?",
      a: "[a] CovAid",
      b: "[b] CovShield",
      c: "[c] Def-Cov",
      d: "[d] Covax-Aid",
      e: "[e] Covin",
      answer: "[a] CovAid",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.3) Which organization has partnered with OneWeb for mutual cooperation to promote OneWeb's satellite communication services in the global and Japan markets?",
      a: "[a] Mitsubishi UFJ Financial Group",
      b: "[b] Sumitomo Mitsui Financial Group",
      c: "[c] Norinchukin Bank",
      d: "[d] Mizuho Financial Group",
      e: "[e] SoftBank Corp",
      answer: "[e] SoftBank Corp",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.4) Where is United Co-operative Bank Ltd located?",
      a: "[a] West Bengal",
      b: "[b] Maharashtra",
      c: "[c] Madhya Pradesh",
      d: "[d] Gujarat",
      e: "[e] Odisha",
      answer: "[a] West Bengal",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.5) Which company has launched DigiGold platform?",
      a: "[a] NSDL Payments Bank.",
      b: "[b] Jio Payments Bank",
      c: "[c] Fino Payments Bank",
      d: "[d] Airtel Payments Bank",
      e: "[e] India Post Payments Bank",
      answer: "[d] Airtel Payments Bank",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.1) Which state has launched “Mission Oxygen” to encourage the private sector to generate liquid medical oxygen?",
      a: "[a] West Bengal",
      b: "[b] Karnataka",
      c: "[c] Kerala",
      d: "[d] Maharashtra",
      e: "[e] Delhi",
      answer: "[d] Maharashtra",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.2) As per the International Energy Agency’s “Renewable Energy Market Update Outlook for 2021 and 2022” report, the renewable energy capacity addition increased by 45% in 2020 to ______ which is the highest year on year increase since 1999?",
      a: "[a] 190 GW",
      b: "[b] 450 GW",
      c: "[c] 280 GW",
      d: "[d] 370 GW",
      e: "[e] 540 GW",
      answer: "[c] 280 GW",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.3) With which bank has Geojit Financial Services partnered to offer 3-in-1 account services to its retail customers?",
      a: "[a] Bank of Baroda",
      b: "[b] State Bank of India",
      c: "[c] Canara Bank",
      d: "[d] Punjab National Bank",
      e: "[e] Axis Bank",
      answer: "[d] Punjab National Bank",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.4) Which of the following company has launched the Farmizo Khata, a B2C Farm accounting mobile application, in partnership with Yono app?",
      a: "[a] Agrowave",
      b: "[b] BharatAgri",
      c: "[c] BigHaat",
      d: "[d] Shivrai Technologies",
      e: "[e] Clover Ventures",
      answer: "[d] Shivrai Technologies",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.5) Who has been appointed as the CEO of the National Asset Reconstruction Company Ltd?",
      a: "[a] Arvind Singh",
      b: "[b] Padmakumar M Nair",
      c: "[c] R. K. Dhawan",
      d: "[d] Sanjay Pandey",
      e: "[e] S.Prasannan",
      answer: "[b] Padmakumar M Nair",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.6) What is the GDP forecast for India for FY22, as per the UN’s World Economic Situation and Prospects report?",
      a: "[a] 7.5%",
      b: "[b] 8.8%",
      c: "[c] 9.3%",
      d: "[d] 10.2%",
      e: "[e] 5.4%",
      answer: "[a] 7.5%",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.7) Who has become the first woman of Asian descent to win the 2021 World Food Prize?",
      a: "[a] Saroj Chooramani Gopal",
      b: "[b] Mirudhubashini Govindarajan",
      c: "[c] Shakuntala Haraksingh Thilsted",
      d: "[d] Janaki Ammal",
      e: "[e] Asima Chatterjee",
      answer: "[c] Shakuntala Haraksingh Thilsted",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.8) Which of the following has won the “Green Urja Award”?",
      a: "[a] Energy Efficiency Services Limited",
      b: "[b] Coal India Ltd",
      c: "[c] National Thermal Power Corporation",
      d: "[d] Indian Renewable Energy Development Agency Ltd.",
      e: "[e] Powergrid Corporation of India",
      answer: "[d] Indian Renewable Energy Development Agency Ltd.",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.9) Who is the author of “1971: The Beginning of India's Cricketing Greatness” book?",
      a: "[a] Boria Majumdar",
      b: "[b] Gautam Bhattacharya",
      c: "[c] Sarojini Shekhar",
      d: "[d] Both A and B",
      e: "[e] Both B and C",
      answer: "[d] Both A and B",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.10) What is the GDP growth rate forecasted by Nomura for FY22?",
      a: "[a] 11.2%",
      b: "[b] 10.6%",
      c: "[c] 5.2%",
      d: "[d] 9.8%",
      e: "[e] 10.8%",
      answer: "[e] 10.8%",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.1) Which IIT has partnered with Mobile Payment Forum of India (MPFI) to develop voice-based solutions in multiple vernacular languages to enable larger adoption of digital money transactions in the country?",
      a: "[a] IIT- Madras",
      b: "[b] IIT- Guwahati",
      c: "[c] IIT- Kanpur",
      d: "[d] IIT- Bombay",
      e: "[e] IIT- Varanasi",
      answer: "[a] IIT- Madras",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.2) With which organization has NASA collaborated for first private astronaut mission to the International Space Station?",
      a: "[a] Virgin Galactic",
      b: "[b] SpaceX",
      c: "[c] Axiom Space",
      d: "[d] Blue Origin",
      e: "[e] Bigelow Aerospace",
      answer: "[c] Axiom Space",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.3) Who has been appointed as the chairman and managing director of Bharat Petroleum Corporation Ltd?",
      a: "[a] Neerja Sekhar",
      b: "[b] Arun Kumar Singh",
      c: "[c] P C Bodh",
      d: "[d] Vikram Sahay",
      e: "[e] Anju Nigam",
      answer: "[b] Arun Kumar Singh",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.4) What is the theme of International Nurses Day 2021?",
      a: "[a] Achieving the Sustainable Development Goals",
      b: "[b] Health is a Human right",
      c: "[c] Health for All",
      d: "[d] Nursing the World to Health",
      e: "[e] A Vision for future healthcare",
      answer: "[e] A Vision for future healthcare",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.5) Who has become the first person from India to win the 15th Sheikh Zayed Book Award?",
      a: "[a] Tahera Qutbuddin",
      b: "[b] Iman Mersal",
      c: "[c] Mizouni Bannani",
      d: "[d] Asma Muqbil",
      e: "[e] Khelil Gouia",
      answer: "[a] Tahera Qutbuddin",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.6) Who has become the first Indian to receive the Arline Pacht Global Vision Award for 2021?",
      a: "[a] Gita Mittal",
      b: "[b] Fathima Beevi",
      c: "[c] Sujata Manohar",
      d: "[d] Ruma Pal",
      e: "[e] Gyan Sudha Misra",
      answer: "[a] Gita Mittal",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.7) Which company has collaborated with NIRA (Bengaluru-based fintech) to strengthen its digital footprint?",
      a: "[a] HDB Finance Services",
      b: "[b] Bajaj Finance Limited",
      c: "[c] Muthoot Finance Limited",
      d: "[d] Mahindra & Mahindra Financial Services",
      e: "[e] Power Finance Corporation",
      answer: "[c] Muthoot Finance Limited",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.8) Which bank has partnered with Mashreq Bank (based in UAE) to facilitate money transfers from the UAE?",
      a: "[a] ICICI Bank",
      b: "[b] Axis Bank",
      c: "[c] State Bank of India",
      d: "[d] Federal Bank",
      e: "[e] Punjab National Bank",
      answer: "[d] Federal Bank",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.9) With which organization has NITI Aayog partnered to release the ‘Connected Commerce: Creating a Roadmap for a Digitally Inclusive Bharat’ report?",
      a: "[a] The Lancet",
      b: "[b] Bloomberg",
      c: "[c] Paytm",
      d: "[d] Cornell University",
      e: "[e] Mastercard",
      answer: "[e] Mastercard",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.10) Who heads the committee formed by Maharashtra govt for studying the Supreme Court's order striking down quota for the Maratha community in Maharashtra?",
      a: "[a] Rajkumar Singh Thakur",
      b: "[b] Dilip Bhosale",
      c: "[c] Bibhuti Bhushana Dash",
      d: "[d] Fakhre Alam",
      e: "[e] Kimjamlhing Changloi",
      answer: "[b] Dilip Bhosale",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.1) Recently, India, Israel and the UAE have signed their first ever trilateral pact. This is the first such arrangement since Israel and UAE established diplomatic ties. The agreement facilitates development of an innovative robotic solar cleaning technology in India for a landmark project in the UAE. The trilateral partnership has been initiated by the International Federation of Indo-Israel Chambers of Commerce. Which company will produce this technology?",
      a: "[a] Light IT",
      b: "[b] Solvd Inc",
      c: "[c] Aalpha Information Systems",
      d: "[d] Ecoppia",
      e: "[e] NIX",
      answer: "[d] Ecoppia",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.2) Which state has started a new Mukhyamantri Seva Sankalp Helpline Number 1100 for public grievance addressal in the state?",
      a: "[a] Maharashtra",
      b: "[b] Uttar Pradesh",
      c: "[c] Himachal Pradesh",
      d: "[d] Uttarakhand",
      e: "[e] Rajasthan",
      answer: "[c] Himachal Pradesh",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.3) What is the venue of G7 Foreign Minister’s Meeting 2021?",
      a: "[a] London",
      b: "[b] Vienna",
      c: "[c] Sofia",
      d: "[d] Minsk",
      e: "[e] Brussels",
      answer: "[a] London",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.4) Who is the CEO of Deloitte?",
      a: "[a] Tammy Baldwin",
      b: "[b] Gary Peters",
      c: "[c] Catherine Cortez Masto",
      d: "[d] Punit Renjen",
      e: "[e] Jeff Merkley",
      answer: "[d] Punit Renjen",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.5) As per the “Global Methane Assessment 2021”, __ percent reduction in methane emissions by 2030 would reduce global warming by 0.3º C by 2040s?",
      a: "[a] 50%",
      b: "[b] 45%",
      c: "[c] 30%",
      d: "[d] 25%",
      e: "[e] 60%",
      answer: "[b] 45%",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.6) Which bank has won five awards (Lead to Leap, APY Makers of Excellence, Game Changers, Leadership Capital and Amazing Achievers) from the Pension Fund Regulatory and Development Authority?",
      a: "[a] Andhra Pradesh Grameena Vikas Bank",
      b: "[b] Bangiya Gramin Vikash Bank",
      c: "[c] Karnataka Vikas Grameen Bank",
      d: "[d] Baroda Rajasthan Kshetriya Gramin Bank",
      e: "[e] Baroda Gujarat Gramin Bank",
      answer: "[c] Karnataka Vikas Grameen Bank",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.7) Under which section of Companies Act 2013 was National Financial Reporting Authority created?",
      a: "[a] Section 101",
      b: "[b] Section 279",
      c: "[c] Section 338",
      d: "[d] Section 420",
      e: "[e] Section 132",
      answer: "[e] Section 132",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.8) Who is the Chairperson of National Financial Reporting Authority?",
      a: "[a] Prasenjit Mukherjee",
      b: "[b] Vivek Narayan",
      c: "[c] Venkateswarlu Peri",
      d: "[d] R. Sridharan",
      e: "[e] Arun Kumar",
      answer: "[d] R. Sridharan",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.9) Who has become the CM of Puducherry?",
      a: "[a] A.K. Sai J Saravanan Kumar",
      b: "[b] N Rangasamy",
      c: "[c] A. Johnkumar",
      d: "[d] A. Namassivayam",
      e: "[e] V. Saminathan",
      answer: "[b] N Rangasamy",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.10) Which company introduced world’s first 2-nanometre chipmaking technology?",
      a: "[a] IBM",
      b: "[b] Intel",
      c: "[c] Qualcomm",
      d: "[d] TSMC",
      e: "[e] Micron Technology",
      answer: "[a] IBM",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.1) Which state has launched the 'Mukhyamantri COVID Upchar Yojana'?",
      a: "[a] Uttar Pradesh",
      b: "[b] Jharkhand",
      c: "[c] Chhattisgarh",
      d: "[d] Madhya Pradesh",
      e: "[e] Punjab",
      answer: "[d] Madhya Pradesh",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.2) What is the name of the app launched by Interpol to help identify stolen cultural property, reduce illicit trafficking, and increase the chances of recovering stolen works and artefacts?",
      a: "[a] Trace",
      b: "[b] ID-Art",
      c: "[c] Path",
      d: "[d] Stalk-Art",
      e: "[e] Track-Art",
      answer: "[b] ID-Art",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.3) Who heads the RBI’s six-member Advisory Group set up under the Regulations Review Authority (RRA 2.0)?",
      a: "[a] S Janakiraman",
      b: "[b] T. Rabi Sankar",
      c: "[c] M. Rajeshwar Rao",
      d: "[d] M. D. Patra",
      e: "[e] M. K. Jain",
      answer: "[a] S Janakiraman",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.4) How much percentage of investible surplus is the Employees Provident Fund Organisation allowed to invest in alternate investment funds?",
      a: "[a] 10%",
      b: "[b] 3%",
      c: "[c] 5%",
      d: "[d] 12%",
      e: "[e] 20%",
      answer: "[c] 5%",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.5) Which company has launched 'Savdhan Rahein. Safe Rahein' public awareness campaign to educate customers and public at large on financial fraud risks?",
      a: "[a] Muthoot Finance Ltd",
      b: "[b] HDB Finance Services",
      c: "[c] Tata Capital Financial Services",
      d: "[d] Power Finance Corporation",
      e: "[e] Bajaj Finserv",
      answer: "[e] Bajaj Finserv",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.6) Who has been appointed as the 38th President of the FICCI Ladies Organization?",
      a: "[a] Sarojini Shekhar",
      b: "[b] Anita Baghel",
      c: "[c] Ujjwala Singhania",
      d: "[d] Rajni Sharma",
      e: "[e] Radhika Shah",
      answer: "[c] Ujjwala Singhania",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.7) Who has been awarded the Laureus World Sportsman of The Year 2021?",
      a: "[a] Naomi Osaka",
      b: "[b] Patrick Mahomes",
      c: "[c] Max Parrot",
      d: "[d] Rafael Nadal",
      e: "[e] Billie Jean King",
      answer: "[d] Rafael Nadal",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.8) Which country organized the 3rd Arctic Science Ministerial?",
      a: "[a] Japan",
      b: "[b] Iceland",
      c: "[c] Norway",
      d: "[d] Both A and B",
      e: "[e] Both B and C",
      answer: "[d] Both A and B",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.9) Who among the following is the convener of the 12-member National Task Force set up by Supreme Court to streamline the process of oxygen distribution between states and UT on the basis of scientific and specialised domain knowledge?",
      a: "[a] Devender Singh Rana",
      b: "[b] Bhabatosh Biswas",
      c: "[c] Gagandeep Kang",
      d: "[d] Rajiv Gauba",
      e: "[e] Naresh Trehan",
      answer: "[d] Rajiv Gauba",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.10) Who has won the women’s singles title at Madrid Open tennis?",
      a: "[a] Lesia Tsurenko",
      b: "[b] Elina Svitolina",
      c: "[c] Simona Halep",
      d: "[d] Aryna Sabalenka",
      e: "[e] Ashleigh Barty",
      answer: "[d] Aryna Sabalenka",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.1) Which state has become India’s first state to adopt online flood forecasting system?",
      a: "[a] Madhya Pradesh",
      b: "[b] Arunachal Pradesh",
      c: "[c] Assam",
      d: "[d] Odisha",
      e: "[e] West Bengal",
      answer: "[c] Assam",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.2) Which bank has partnered with Common Services Centres to launch the chatbot ‘Eva’ on CSCs Digital Seva Portal to support the Village Level Entrepreneurs?",
      a: "[a] ICICI Bank",
      b: "[b] HDFC Bank",
      c: "[c] Axis Bank",
      d: "[d] Yes Bank",
      e: "[e] DCB Bank",
      answer: "[b] HDFC Bank",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.3) What is the theme of National Technology Day 2021?",
      a: "[a] Rebooting the Economy through Science, Technology and Research Translations",
      b: "[b] Space Technologies and ISRO",
      c: "[c] Technology for inclusive and sustainable growth",
      d: "[d] Science and Technology for a Sustainable Future",
      e: "[e] Technology Enablers of Startup India",
      answer: "[d] Science and Technology for a Sustainable Future",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.4) Whose debut book is titled as ‘Life in the Clock Tower Valley’?",
      a: "[a] Amar Pal",
      b: "[b] Rajkumar Singh Thakur",
      c: "[c] R. K. Dhawan",
      d: "[d] S.Prasannan",
      e: "[e] Shakoor Rather",
      answer: "[e] Shakoor Rather",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.5) With which country has India jointly launched the Neev Fund I?",
      a: "[a] Germany",
      b: "[b] Finland",
      c: "[c] France",
      d: "[d] Japan",
      e: "[e] UK",
      answer: "[e] UK",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.1) Which of the following IIT has launched Mission Bharat O2?",
      a: "[a] IIT Madras",
      b: "[b] IIT Delhi",
      c: "[c] IIT Bombay",
      d: "[d] IIT Kanpur",
      e: "[e] IIT Kharagpur",
      answer: "[d] IIT Kanpur",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.2) With which company has National Dairy Development Board signed an agreement to promote efficient renewable technologies in the dairy industry?",
      a: "[a] National Thermal Power Corporation",
      b: "[b] Energy Efficiency Services Ltd",
      c: "[c] North Eastern Electric Power Corporation",
      d: "[d] National Hydroelectric Power Corporation",
      e: "[e] Power Grid Corporation of India",
      answer: "[b] Energy Efficiency Services Ltd",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.3) With which country has India signed an MoU on Migration and Mobility Partnership (MMP) to facilitate legal movement of students and professionals, and combating illegal migration and organised immigration crime?",
      a: "[a] Thailand",
      b: "[b] UK",
      c: "[c] Japan",
      d: "[d] USA",
      e: "[e] Australia",
      answer: "[b] UK",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.4) With which of the following entity has Telecom Equipment Manufacturers Association of India signed an MoU to cooperate on a series of mutually beneficial matters?",
      a: "[a] Indo-Italy Chamber of Commerce",
      b: "[b] Indo-Germany Chamber of Commerce",
      c: "[c] Indo-Canada Chamber of Commerce",
      d: "[d] Indo-US Chamber of Commerce",
      e: "[e] Indo-Singapore Chamber of Commerce",
      answer: "[c] Indo-Canada Chamber of Commerce",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.5) Which country will host the European Council meeting 2021?",
      a: "[a] Austria",
      b: "[b] Croatia",
      c: "[c] Belgium",
      d: "[d] Bulgaria",
      e: "[e] Portugal",
      answer: "[e] Portugal",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.1) Which state has launched CLAP to promote cleanliness in the state?",
      a: "[a] Andhra Pradesh",
      b: "[b] Maharashtra",
      c: "[c] Tamil Nadu",
      d: "[d] Telangana",
      e: "[e] Punjab",
      answer: "[a] Andhra Pradesh",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.2) Which company has partnered with the Indian government to launch a Vaccine Finder Tool on its mobile app in India?",
      a: "[a] Mobikwik",
      b: "[b] Amazon",
      c: "[c] Facebook",
      d: "[d] Twitter",
      e: "[e] Google",
      answer: "[c] Facebook",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.3) What is the GDP forecast for India for FY22 by S&P?",
      a: "[a] 11.9%",
      b: "[b] 12.3%",
      c: "[c] 10.5%",
      d: "[d] 9.8%",
      e: "[e] 8.7%",
      answer: "[d] 9.8%",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.4) What is LIC’s rank in Brand Finance Insurance 100 2021 report in terms of value?",
      a: "[a] 10th",
      b: "[b] 8th",
      c: "[c] 5th",
      d: "[d] 20th",
      e: "[e] 15th",
      answer: "[a] 10th",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.5) Who is the director of Jungle Cry?",
      a: "[a] Kamal Haasan",
      b: "[b] Dibakar Banerjee",
      c: "[c] Mani Ratnam",
      d: "[d] Sagar Ballary",
      e: "[e] Anurag Kashyap",
      answer: "[d] Sagar Ballary",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.6) What is India’s rank in ICC’s annual rankings in the category of Test matches?",
      a: "[a] 1st",
      b: "[b] 4th",
      c: "[c] 5th",
      d: "[d] 10th",
      e: "[e] 3rd",
      answer: "[a] 1st",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.7) “The Bench” is the first children’s book of which of the following?",
      a: "[a] Paul Mendez",
      b: "[b] Abi Daré",
      c: "[c] Deepa Anappara",
      d: "[d] Elaine Feeney",
      e: "[e] Meghan Markel",
      answer: "[e] Meghan Markel",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.8) Who is the writer of “BENGAL 2021: An Election Diary”?",
      a: "[a] Megha Majumdar",
      b: "[b] Deep Halder",
      c: "[c] Kunal Basu",
      d: "[d] Deepa Anappara",
      e: "[e] Jayasree Kalathil",
      answer: "[b] Deep Halder",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.9) What is the outlay of liquidity facility window provided by RBI to banks for on-lending to health services, as part of the relief measure for Covid-19?",
      a: "[a] Rs 10,000 crores",
      b: "[b] Rs 20,000 crores",
      c: "[c] Rs 35,000 crores",
      d: "[d] Rs 50,000 crores",
      e: "[e] Rs 60,000 crores",
      answer: "[d] Rs 50,000 crores",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.10) As per the State of the World’s Midwifery 2021 report, there is a global shortage of around _____ midwives, which is 1/3rd of the required global midwife workforce?",
      a: "[a] 2 lakh",
      b: "[b] 9 lakh",
      c: "[c] 7 lakh",
      d: "[d] 10 lakh",
      e: "[e] 3 lakh",
      answer: "[b] 9 lakh",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.1) Where is the 'Auro Scholarship Programme' launched?",
      a: "[a] Maharashtra",
      b: "[b] Tripura",
      c: "[c] Tamil Nadu",
      d: "[d] West Bengal",
      e: "[e] Manipur",
      answer: "[b] Tripura",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.2) On which ICGS has the Hindustan Aeronautics Limited's (HAL) Advanced Light Helicopter Dhruv Mk III MR completed deck operation trials?",
      a: "[a] ICGS Vajra",
      b: "[b] ICGS Samrat",
      c: "[c] ICGS Sujay",
      d: "[d] ICGS Sankalp",
      e: "[e] ICGS Samarth",
      answer: "[c] ICGS Sujay",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.3) Online sales accounted for ___ percent of the total retail sales in 2020, according to the UNCTAD’s “Estimates Of Global E-Commerce 2019 And Preliminary Assessment Of Covid-19 Impact On Online Retail 2020” report?",
      a: "[a] 19%",
      b: "[b] 23%",
      c: "[c] 17%",
      d: "[d] 11%",
      e: "[e] 10%",
      answer: "[a] 19%",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.4) What is the GDP forecast for India for FY22 by Goldman Sachs?",
      a: "[a] 10.3%",
      b: "[b] 11.1%",
      c: "[c] 9.3%",
      d: "[d] 8.5%",
      e: "[e] 12.7%",
      answer: "[b] 11.1%",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.5) Who have been nominated as athlete ambassador for International Olympic Committee’s ‘Believe in Sports’ campaign?",
      a: "[a] PV Sindhu",
      b: "[b] Pullela Gopichand",
      c: "[c] Saina Nehwal",
      d: "[d] Parupalli Kashyap",
      e: "[e] Aparna Popat",
      answer: "[a] PV Sindhu",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.6) Who has become the First woman Officer Executive Engineer (Civil) taking over as Officer Commanding of a Road Construction Company in BRO?",
      a: "[a] Sneha Vashisth",
      b: "[b] Vinita Sinha",
      c: "[c] Vaishali S Hiwase",
      d: "[d] Kavita Shanker",
      e: "[e] Priya Pal",
      answer: "[c] Vaishali S Hiwase",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.7) When is the International Firefighters' Day 2021 observed?",
      a: "[a] May 23",
      b: "[b] May 16",
      c: "[c] May 4",
      d: "[d] May 7",
      e: "[e] May 10",
      answer: "[c] May 4",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.8) What is the theme of World Asthma Day 2021?",
      a: "[a] Enough Asthma Deaths",
      b: "[b] Uncovering Asthma Misconceptions",
      c: "[c] STOP for asthma",
      d: "[d] Allergy and Asthma",
      e: "[e] You Can Control Your Asthma",
      answer: "[b] Uncovering Asthma Misconceptions",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.9) What is the cash prize given under the 'Satyajit Ray Lifetime Achievement Award for Excellence in Cinema'?",
      a: "[a] ₹30 lakh",
      b: "[b] ₹15 lakh",
      c: "[c] ₹20 lakh",
      d: "[d] ₹10 lakh",
      e: "[e] ₹5 lakh",
      answer: "[d] ₹10 lakh",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.10) Where is the National Museum of Indian Cinema located?",
      a: "[a] Mumbai",
      b: "[b] Kolkata",
      c: "[c] Delhi",
      d: "[d] Chandigarh",
      e: "[e] Bangalore",
      answer: "[a] Mumbai",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.1) Which of the following operation has been launched by the Indian Navy for procuring oxygen from different countries to India in the wake of Covid-19?",
      a: "[a] Operation Vayu II",
      b: "[b] Operation Samudra Setu II",
      c: "[c] Operation Sagar I",
      d: "[d] Operation Sanjeevani I",
      e: "[e] Operation Jeevan Raksha II",
      answer: "[b] Operation Samudra Setu II",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.2) Recently, Indian Army has inaugurated the First Green Solar Energy harnessing plant of 56 KVA using Vanadium based battery technology in ____ at an altitude of 16000 ft?",
      a: "[a] Arunachal Pradesh",
      b: "[b] Himachal Pradesh",
      c: "[c] Assam",
      d: "[d] Sikkim",
      e: "[e] Jammu and Kashmir",
      answer: "[d] Sikkim",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.3) How much food grain production target has been set up by the Central govt for 2021-22?",
      a: "[a] 170.77 million tonnes",
      b: "[b] 181.90 million tonnes",
      c: "[c] 307.31 million tonnes",
      d: "[d] 108.76 million tonnes",
      e: "[e] 223.11 million tonnes",
      answer: "[c] 307.31 million tonnes",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.4) Which bank has launched a special deposit scheme named “Immune India Deposit Scheme” to encourage people to get COVID-19 vaccines?",
      a: "[a] Central Bank of India",
      b: "[b] Indian Overseas Bank",
      c: "[c] Punjab and Sind Bank",
      d: "[d] Bank of Maharashtra",
      e: "[e] UCO Bank",
      answer: "[a] Central Bank of India",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.5) Which bank has acquired stake in two companies – India INX and India ICC – in GIFT City?",
      a: "[a] Union Bank of India",
      b: "[b] Bandhan Bank",
      c: "[c] Axis Bank",
      d: "[d] DCB Bank",
      e: "[e] Federal Bank",
      answer: "[d] DCB Bank",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.6) Which bank has launched two new quick credit delivery schemes –– SHWAS and AROG?",
      a: "[a] SIDBI",
      b: "[b] South Indian Bank",
      c: "[c] SBI",
      d: "[d] CSB Bank",
      e: "[e] Saurashtra Gramin Bank",
      answer: "[a] SIDBI",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.7) Who has been chosen for the post of CMD of BEML Limited?",
      a: "[a] Amit Banerjee",
      b: "[b] Upendra Prasad Singh",
      c: "[c] Vijoy Kumar Singh",
      d: "[d] Shashi Ranjan Kumar",
      e: "[e] Nihar Ranjan Dash",
      answer: "[a] Amit Banerjee",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.8) Who has been appointed as the MD of Kotak Mahindra Life Insurance Company Limited?",
      a: "[a] Sanjay Sharan",
      b: "[b] Jay Karan Singh",
      c: "[c] Gaurav Kumar",
      d: "[d] Mahesh Balasubramanian",
      e: "[e] Hemant kumar Nanda",
      answer: "[d] Mahesh Balasubramanian",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.9) Where will the 2021 ASBC Asian Elite Men and Women Boxing Championships be held?",
      a: "[a] Doha",
      b: "[b] Dubai",
      c: "[c] Cairo",
      d: "[d] Beirut",
      e: "[e] İstanbul",
      answer: "[b] Dubai",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.10) How much Central govt will give to state for capital expenditure under the “Scheme of Financial Assistance to States for Capital Expenditure” for 2021-22?",
      a: "[a] Rs 15,000 crore",
      b: "[b] Rs 25,000 crore",
      c: "[c] Rs 10,000 crore",
      d: "[d] Rs 12,000 crore",
      e: "[e] Rs 9,000 crore",
      answer: "[a] Rs 15,000 crore",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.1) Who chairs the Capacity Building Commission of India?",
      a: "[a] Rahul Chhabra",
      b: "[b] Vikas Swarup",
      c: "[c] Riva Ganguly Das",
      d: "[d] Adil Zainulbhai",
      e: "[e] Sanjay Bhattacharyya",
      answer: "[d] Adil Zainulbhai",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.2) In which state is the KVIC’s RE-HAB (Reducing Elephant-Human Attacks using Bees) pilot project launched?",
      a: "[a] Karnataka",
      b: "[b] Odisha",
      c: "[c] Andhra Pradesh",
      d: "[d] Maharashtra",
      e: "[e] Madhya Pradesh",
      answer: "[a] Karnataka",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.3) Where is Nagarahole National Park and Tiger Reserve located?",
      a: "[a] Odisha",
      b: "[b] Andhra Pradesh",
      c: "[c] Telangana",
      d: "[d] Tamil Nadu",
      e: "[e] Karnataka",
      answer: "[e] Karnataka",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.4) Which bank has partnered with Axis Securities to offer its customers the perfect mix of banking and investing through 3-in-1 account?",
      a: "[a] Ujjivan Small Finance Bank",
      b: "[b] Janalakshmi Small Finance Bank",
      c: "[c] Jana Small Finance Bank",
      d: "[d] Capital Small Finance Bank",
      e: "[e] Utkarsh Small Finance Bank",
      answer: "[c] Jana Small Finance Bank",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.5) What is India’s debt to GDP ratio according to the International Monetary Fund?",
      a: "[a] 80%",
      b: "[b] 90%",
      c: "[c] 75%",
      d: "[d] 60%",
      e: "[e] 95%",
      answer: "[b] 90%",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.6) Who has been appointed as the brand ambassador of Vivo?",
      a: "[a] Ravindra Jadeja",
      b: "[b] Virat Kohli",
      c: "[c] Rohit Sharma",
      d: "[d] KL Rahul",
      e: "[e] Rishabh Pant",
      answer: "[b] Virat Kohli",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.7) Who has made two Guinness World Records for fastest solo cycling from India?",
      a: "[a] Bharat Pannu",
      b: "[b] Sushil R Gaikwad",
      c: "[c] Gurpreet Singh",
      d: "[d] K.K. Singh",
      e: "[e] Suraj C. Naik",
      answer: "[a] Bharat Pannu",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.8) Which field does Fatima R Zakaria belong to? (She passed away recently.)",
      a: "[a] Journalist",
      b: "[b] Author",
      c: "[c] Professor",
      d: "[d] Both A and B",
      e: "[e] Both B and C",
      answer: "[d] Both A and B",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.9) Who is the author of ‘Odisha Itihaas’?",
      a: "[a] Harekrushna Mahatab",
      b: "[b] Vaidya Rajesh Kotecha",
      c: "[c] Dinesh Setia",
      d: "[d] Pramod Kumar Pathak",
      e: "[e] Dharmendra Singh Gangwar",
      answer: "[a] Harekrushna Mahatab",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.10) Where is Valley of Flowers National Park located?",
      a: "[a] Arunachal Pradesh",
      b: "[b] Assam",
      c: "[c] Madhya Pradesh",
      d: "[d] Uttarakhand",
      e: "[e] Himachal Pradesh",
      answer: "[d] Uttarakhand",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.1) Where is the secretariate of Codex Alimentarius Commission located?",
      a: "[a] Rome",
      b: "[b] Geneva",
      c: "[c] Amsterdam",
      d: "[d] Davos",
      e: "[e] Vienna",
      answer: "[a] Rome",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.2) How much is the maximum sum assured under the new Employees’ Deposit Linked Insurance Scheme, 2021?",
      a: "[a] Rs 5 lakh",
      b: "[b] Rs 6 lakh",
      c: "[c] Rs 1.5 lakh",
      d: "[d] Rs 7 lakh",
      e: "[e] Rs 2 lakh",
      answer: "[d] Rs 7 lakh",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.3) How much FDI has the govt allowed in the road sector?",
      a: "[a] 49%",
      b: "[b] 100%",
      c: "[c] 74%",
      d: "[d] 80%",
      e: "[e] 50%",
      answer: "[b] 100%",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.4) Which of the following institute has developed a high-yielding and pest-resistant variety of soybean, called MACS 1407?",
      a: "[a] Agharkar Research Institute",
      b: "[b] Indian Council of Agricultural Research",
      c: "[c] Indian Agricultural Research Institute",
      d: "[d] Both A and B",
      e: "[e] Both A and C",
      answer: "[d] Both A and B",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.5) Which edition of the G7 Summit will take place in UK?",
      a: "[a] 45th",
      b: "[b] 50th",
      c: "[c] 47th",
      d: "[d] 70th",
      e: "[e] 20th",
      answer: "[c] 47th",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.6) On which river is the World’s longest pedestrian suspension bridge located?",
      a: "[a] Danube",
      b: "[b] Rhine",
      c: "[c] Seine",
      d: "[d] Elbe",
      e: "[e] Paiva",
      answer: "[e] Paiva",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.7) On how many Global Forest Goals does the Global Forest Goals 2021 Report assesses the performance of countries?",
      a: "[a] Six",
      b: "[b] Ten",
      c: "[c] Twelve",
      d: "[d] Fifteen",
      e: "[e] Five",
      answer: "[a] Six",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.8) Which company has launched a first-of-its-kind $200 million Restore Fund to remove 1 million metric tons of carbon dioxide annually from the atmosphere?",
      a: "[a] Apple",
      b: "[b] Amazon",
      c: "[c] Upgrad",
      d: "[d] Byju’s",
      e: "[e] Tesla",
      answer: "[a] Apple",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.9) Who has become the first Indian-American to be appointed as the US' Associate Attorney General?",
      a: "[a] Vanita Gupta",
      b: "[b] Premjeet Singh",
      c: "[c] Rajat Pal",
      d: "[d] Sumit Verma",
      e: "[e] Sachin Vashisth",
      answer: "[a] Vanita Gupta",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.10) Who has won the singles at the Porsche Tennis Grand Prix 2021?",
      a: "[a] Naomi Osaka",
      b: "[b] Simona Halep",
      c: "[c] Sofia Kenin",
      d: "[d] Ashleigh Barty",
      e: "[e] Aryna Sabalenka",
      answer: "[d] Ashleigh Barty",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.1) Which state has signed an MoU with Microsoft for imparting digital skills to 1.62 lakh students and unemployed youth across 300 plus colleges and skill development centres in the state?",
      a: "[a] Maharashtra",
      b: "[b] Gujarat",
      c: "[c] West Bengal",
      d: "[d] Andhra Pradesh",
      e: "[e] Tamil Nadu",
      answer: "[d] Andhra Pradesh",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.2) Which state’s Urja Vikas Nigam has signed a first of its kind power purchase agreement with Coal India?",
      a: "[a] Arunachal Pradesh",
      b: "[b] Gujarat",
      c: "[c] Chhattisgarh",
      d: "[d] West Bengal",
      e: "[e] Odisha",
      answer: "[b] Gujarat",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.3) Singapore Indian Chamber of Commerce and Industry (SICCI) and Start-up Incubation and Innovation Centre (SIIC) to provide opportunities to tech-based start-ups for a circular economy and an entrepreneurial ecosystem. Both organisations have launched “SICCI-SIIC INNOVATION LAUNCHPAD” challenge for startups. Start-up Incubation and Innovation Centre is located at which IIT?",
      a: "[a] IIT-Kanpur",
      b: "[b] IIT- Kharagpur",
      c: "[c] IIT- Bombay",
      d: "[d] IIT- Madras",
      e: "[e] IIT-Ropar",
      answer: "[a] IIT-Kanpur",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.4) Which IIT has Ministry of Housing & Urban Affairs signed an MoU to set up an Accelerator Centre for Research & Development at the institute?",
      a: "[a] IIT- Dharwad",
      b: "[b] IIT- Goa",
      c: "[c] IIT- Jammu",
      d: "[d] IIT-Kharagpur",
      e: "[e] IIT- Dhanbad",
      answer: "[d] IIT-Kharagpur",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.5) Which has become the second African country to eliminate Trachoma?",
      a: "[a] Ghana",
      b: "[b] Kenya",
      c: "[c] Tanzania",
      d: "[d] Gambia",
      e: "[e] Morocco",
      answer: "[d] Gambia",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.6) When is International Day of Multilateralism and Diplomacy for Peace observed?",
      a: "[a] April 24",
      b: "[b] April 5",
      c: "[c] April 29",
      d: "[d] April 13",
      e: "[e] April 11",
      answer: "[a] April 24",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.7) Who has won the League Cup 2021 (English football tournament)?",
      a: "[a] Arsenal",
      b: "[b] Chelsea",
      c: "[c] Barcelona",
      d: "[d] Atletico Madrid",
      e: "[e] Manchester City",
      answer: "[e] Manchester City",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.8) Where will the ITTF World Table Tennis Championships be held?",
      a: "[a] Brasília, Brazil",
      b: "[b] Sucre, Bolivia",
      c: "[c] Houston, USA",
      d: "[d] Santiago, Chile",
      e: "[e] Bogotá, Colombia",
      answer: "[c] Houston, USA",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.9) Where are the Maui Dolphins found?",
      a: "[a] Philippines",
      b: "[b] Singapore",
      c: "[c] Myanmar",
      d: "[d] Australia",
      e: "[e] New Zealand",
      answer: "[e] New Zealand",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.10) Who is the author of “Living Mountain” book?",
      a: "[a] Amitav Ghosh",
      b: "[b] Hari Kunzru",
      c: "[c] Ashok K. Banker",
      d: "[d] Devdutt Pattanaik",
      e: "[e] Ashwin Sanghi",
      answer: "[a] Amitav Ghosh",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.1) Which IIT has created India’s first 3D printed house?",
      a: "[a] IIT- Delhi",
      b: "[b] IIT- Bombay",
      c: "[c] IIT- Kharagpur",
      d: "[d] IIT- Ropar",
      e: "[e] IIT-Madras",
      answer: "[e] IIT-Madras",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.2) How much is India’s target for the Indian chemicals industry by 2025?",
      a: "[a] $304 billion",
      b: "[b] $178 billion",
      c: "[c] $145 billion",
      d: "[d] $220 billion",
      e: "[e] $180 billion",
      answer: "[a] $304 billion",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.3) Which edition of Varuna exercise was conducted by India and France in 2021?",
      a: "[a] 21st",
      b: "[b] 35th",
      c: "[c] 19th",
      d: "[d] 11th",
      e: "[e] 10th",
      answer: "[c] 19th",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.4) Which country does Tianhe space station module belong to?",
      a: "[a] Japan",
      b: "[b] South Korea",
      c: "[c] Vietnam",
      d: "[d] China",
      e: "[e] Philippines",
      answer: "[d] China",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.5) What is the corpus of Mastercard Impact Fund launched by Mastercard to address the COVID-19 crisis in India?",
      a: "[a] USD 2 million",
      b: "[b] USD 10 million",
      c: "[c] USD 60 million",
      d: "[d] USD 50 million",
      e: "[e] USD 30 million",
      answer: "[b] USD 10 million",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.6) Who has been designated as the Finance Secretary?",
      a: "[a] Kaptan Singh",
      b: "[b] Arvind Singh",
      c: "[c] R. K. Dhawan",
      d: "[d] Sanjay Pandey",
      e: "[e] T V Somanathan",
      answer: "[e] T V Somanathan",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.7) When is the World Day for Safety and Health at Work observed?",
      a: "[a] April 10",
      b: "[b] April 21",
      c: "[c] April 28",
      d: "[d] April 12",
      e: "[e] April 11",
      answer: "[c] April 28",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.8) Who has been chosen as the first Indian and Asian woman for the 2021 'WILD Innovator Award'?",
      a: "[a] Sarojini Shekhar",
      b: "[b] Neha Baghel",
      c: "[c] Krithi K Karanth",
      d: "[d] Priyanka Mishra",
      e: "[e] Reshma Bhushan",
      answer: "[c] Krithi K Karanth",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.9) Which of the following Indian company has entered TIME’s 100 Most Influential Companies 2021 list?",
      a: "[a] Byju’s",
      b: "[b] Razorpay",
      c: "[c] Jio Platform",
      d: "[d] Both A and B",
      e: "[e] Both A and C",
      answer: "[e] Both A and C",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.10) With which field is Manoj Das related to?",
      a: "[a] Badminton player",
      b: "[b] Author",
      c: "[c] Singer",
      d: "[d] Sitarist",
      e: "[e] Environment Conservationist",
      answer: "[b] Author",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.1) On which aircraft has the 5th generation Python-5 Air-to-Air Missile been equipped?",
      a: "[a] Tejas",
      b: "[b] Mirage 2000",
      c: "[c] MiG-29",
      d: "[d] Boeing 737",
      e: "[e] Ilyushin Il-76",
      answer: "[a] Tejas",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.2) With which country has India signed an MoU for Customs Cooperation and Mutual Administrative Assistance in Customs Matters?",
      a: "[a] UK",
      b: "[b] USA",
      c: "[c] France",
      d: "[d] Germany",
      e: "[e] Japan",
      answer: "[a] UK",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.3) Blue Nature Alliance aims to conserve at least ___ percent of the world’s ocean by 2030?",
      a: "[a] 40%",
      b: "[b] 50%",
      c: "[c] 20%",
      d: "[d] 30%",
      e: "[e] 15%",
      answer: "[d] 30%",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.4) NEO-01 is the robot prototype for clean the orbit off the debris left behind by other spacecraft. Which country does the prototype belong to?",
      a: "[a] Germany",
      b: "[b] France",
      c: "[c] China",
      d: "[d] Russia",
      e: "[e] Finland",
      answer: "[c] China",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.5) What is India’s rank in the Chandler Good Government Index 2021?",
      a: "[a] 75th",
      b: "[b] 49th",
      c: "[c] 68th",
      d: "[d] 83rd",
      e: "[e] 91st",
      answer: "[b] 49th",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.6) Which company has launched India’s first Wealth Community based on video?",
      a: "[a] Google Pay",
      b: "[b] BHIM Axis Pay",
      c: "[c] Mobikwik",
      d: "[d] Paytm",
      e: "[e] PhonePe",
      answer: "[d] Paytm",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.7) What is India’s GDP growth rate for FY22 by Asian Development Outlook?",
      a: "[a] 11%",
      b: "[b] 7.7%",
      c: "[c] 8%",
      d: "[d] 9.5%",
      e: "[e] 10.3%",
      answer: "[a] 11%",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.8) Where is the Khelo India State Centre of Excellence (KISCEs) for rowing located?",
      a: "[a] Chandigarh",
      b: "[b] Ranakpur",
      c: "[c] Kausani",
      d: "[d] Patnitop",
      e: "[e] Srinagar",
      answer: "[e] Srinagar",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.9) Recently, Prime Minister Narendra Modi condoled the demise of Dadudan Gadhvi. Which field did he belong to?",
      a: "[a] Literature",
      b: "[b] Sports",
      c: "[c] Politics",
      d: "[d] Environmentalist",
      e: "[e] Orator",
      answer: "[a] Literature",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.10) Non-deposit taking NBFCs with asset size below ___ have the option to not follow the 'Guidelines for Appointment of Statutory Central Auditors / Statutory Auditors of Commercial Banks (excluding RRBs), UCBs and NBFCs (including HFCs)'?",
      a: "[a] ₹1,500 crore",
      b: "[b] ₹1,000 crore",
      c: "[c] ₹2,500 crore",
      d: "[d] ₹2,000 crore",
      e: "[e] ₹500 crore",
      answer: "[b] ₹1,000 crore",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.1) Where has India's first Floating Storage and Regasification Unit (FSRU) of LNG arrived from Singapore?",
      a: "[a] Kerala",
      b: "[b] Gujarat",
      c: "[c] Andhra Pradesh",
      d: "[c] Andhra Pradesh",
      e: "[e] Maharashtra",
      answer: "[e] Maharashtra",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.2) With which company has Indian Army partnered for Ladakh Ignited Minds: A Centre of Excellence and Wellness project to provide better educational opportunities for Ladakhi students?",
      a: "[a] National Thermal Power Corporation",
      b: "[b] Hindustan Petroleum Corporation Limited",
      c: "[c] Coal India Limited",
      d: "[d] Bharat Heavy Electricals Limited",
      e: "[e] Steel Authority of India Limited",
      answer: "[b] Hindustan Petroleum Corporation Limited",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.3) How much fund will be provided to the youth to recover from the Covid-19 pandemic under the UN “Global Youth Mobilization Local Solutions” campaign?",
      a: "[a] $5 million",
      b: "[b] $3 million",
      c: "[c] $4 million",
      d: "[d] $2 million",
      e: "[e] $1 million",
      answer: "[d] $2 million",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.4) Zhurong is the first Mars rover of which country?",
      a: "[a] China",
      b: "[b] Russia",
      c: "[c] Philippines",
      d: "[d] Japan",
      e: "[e] Singapore",
      answer: "[a] China",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.5) Which country has partnered with Microsoft to build the world’s most powerful supercomputer to forecast weather and climate-change?",
      a: "[a] Israel",
      b: "[b] UK",
      c: "[c] Japan",
      d: "[d] Singapore",
      e: "[e] US",
      answer: "[b] UK",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.6) According to Stockholm International Peace Research Institute’s (SIPRI) “Trends In World Military Expenditure, 2020” report, India accounts for ___ percent of world’s military expenditure?",
      a: "[a] 8.9%",
      b: "[b] 3.7%",
      c: "[c] 4.5%",
      d: "[d] 1.5%",
      e: "[e] 10.3%",
      answer: "[b] 3.7%",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.7) What is the prescribed tenure for MD and CEO of banks as per the new guidelines of RBI?",
      a: "[a] 15 years",
      b: "[b] 10 years",
      c: "[c] 12 years",
      d: "[d] 5 years",
      e: "[e] 20 years",
      answer: "[a] 15 years",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.8) Who has been appointed as the new MD and CEO of National Commodity and Derivatives Exchange Ltd?",
      a: "[a] Sharad Goklani",
      b: "[b] Matam Venkata Rao",
      c: "[c] Pramod Chandra Mody",
      d: "[d] Arun Raste",
      e: "",
      answer: "[d] Arun Raste",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.9) How many countries were supported by the E-2020 campaign of WHO for the elimination of malaria?",
      a: "[a] 21",
      b: "[b] 25",
      c: "[c] 32",
      d: "[d] 15",
      e: "[e] 10",
      answer: "[a] 21",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.10) Which picture has received the Best Picture award at the Oscars 2021?",
      a: "[a] The Father",
      b: "[b] Nomadland",
      c: "[c] Another Round",
      d: "[d] Judas and the Black Messiah",
      e: "[e] A Shaun the Sheep",
      answer: "[b] Nomadland",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.1) Which is India’s first city to have a cycling policy?",
      a: "[a] Pune",
      b: "[b] Delhi",
      c: "[c] Mumbai",
      d: "[d] Chandigarh",
      e: "[e] Puducherry",
      answer: "[d] Chandigarh",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.2) What is the target of mustard cultivation set up by Ministry of Agriculture and Family Welfare for 2025-26?",
      a: "[a] 20 million tonnes",
      b: "[b] 19 million tonnes",
      c: "[c] 30 million tonnes",
      d: "[d] 17 million tonnes",
      e: "[e] 29 million tonnes",
      answer: "[d] 17 million tonnes",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.3) Where will the 6th Global Forum on TB Vaccine be held?",
      a: "[a] Bern, Switzerland",
      b: "[b] Toulouse, France",
      c: "[c] San Marino",
      d: "[d] Warsaw, Poland",
      e: "[e] Kyiv, Ukraine",
      answer: "[b] Toulouse, France",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.4) Who among the following will be representing India at the World Cities Culture Forum 2021?",
      a: "[a] Sarbananda Sonowal",
      b: "[b] Pramod Sawant",
      c: "[c] Vijay Rupani",
      d: "[d] Arvind Kejriwal",
      e: "[e] Jai Ram Thakur",
      answer: "[d] Arvind Kejriwal",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.5) Which of the following mission has been sent by NASA to study the interstellar particles in the heliosphere?",
      a: "[a] ARCTAS",
      b: "[b] CHAMP",
      c: "[c] BARREL",
      d: "[d] SHIELDS",
      e: "[e] ATTREX",
      answer: "[d] SHIELDS",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.6) Which university has topped in the The Times Higher Education (THE) Impact Rankings 2021?",
      a: "[a] University of Manchester",
      b: "[b] RMIT University",
      c: "[c] University of Sydney",
      d: "[d] Massachusetts Institute of Technology",
      e: "[e] University of Cambridge",
      answer: "[a] University of Manchester",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.7) Which company has executed world’s first blockchain-enabled paperless trade transaction in the steel industry?",
      a: "[a] ArcelorMittal",
      b: "[b] China Baowu Group",
      c: "[c] Nippon Steel Corporation",
      d: "[d] HBIS Group",
      e: "[e] Tata Steel",
      answer: "[e] Tata Steel",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.8) Who has been chosen as the external auditor of the Organisation for the Prohibition of Chemical Weapons from India?",
      a: "[a] Riva Ganguly Das",
      b: "[b] GC Murmu",
      c: "[c] Satwant Khanalia",
      d: "[d] Harsh Vardhan Shringla",
      e: "[e] Rahul Chhabra",
      answer: "[b] GC Murmu",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.9) Who has been appointed as the chairperson of NASSCOM for 2021-22?",
      a: "[a] Akhilesh Mishra",
      b: "[b] Reenat Sandhu",
      c: "[c] Nagma M. Mallick",
      d: "[d] Rekha M. Menon",
      e: "[e] Prabhat Kumar",
      answer: "[d] Rekha M. Menon",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.10) When is the International Girls in ICT (Information & Communications Technology) Day observed?",
      a: "[a] April 10",
      b: "[b] April 16",
      c: "[c] April 22",
      d: "[d] April 18",
      e: "[e] April 13",
      answer: "[c] April 22",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.1) Which state has signed an MoU with Microsoft for imparting digital skills to 1.62 lakh students and unemployed youth across 300 plus colleges and skill development centres in the state?",
      a: "[a] Maharashtra",
      b: "[b] Gujarat",
      c: "[c] West Bengal",
      d: "[d] Andhra Pradesh",
      e: "[e] Tamil Nadu",
      answer: "[d] Andhra Pradesh",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.2) Which state’s Urja Vikas Nigam has signed a first of its kind power purchase agreement with Coal India?",
      a: "[a] Arunachal Pradesh",
      b: "[b] Gujarat",
      c: "[c] Chhattisgarh",
      d: "[d] West Bengal",
      e: "[e] Odisha",
      answer: "[b] Gujarat",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.3) Singapore Indian Chamber of Commerce and Industry (SICCI) and Start-up Incubation and Innovation Centre (SIIC) to provide opportunities to tech-based start-ups for a circular economy and an entrepreneurial ecosystem. Both organisations have launched “SICCI-SIIC INNOVATION LAUNCHPAD” challenge for startups. Start-up Incubation and Innovation Centre is located at which IIT?",
      a: "[a] IIT-Kanpur",
      b: "[b] IIT- Kharagpur",
      c: "[c] IIT- Bombay",
      d: "[d] IIT- Madras",
      e: "[e] IIT-Ropar",
      answer: "[a] IIT-Kanpur",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.4) Which IIT has Ministry of Housing & Urban Affairs signed an MoU to set up an Accelerator Centre for Research & Development at the institute?",
      a: "[a] IIT- Dharwad",
      b: "[b] IIT- Goa",
      c: "[c] IIT- Jammu",
      d: "[d] IIT-Kharagpur",
      e: "[e] IIT- Dhanbad",
      answer: "[d] IIT-Kharagpur",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.5) Which has become the second African country to eliminate Trachoma?",
      a: "[a] Ghana",
      b: "[b] Kenya",
      c: "[c] Tanzania",
      d: "[d] Gambia",
      e: "[e] Morocco",
      answer: "[d] Gambia",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.6) When is International Day of Multilateralism and Diplomacy for Peace observed?",
      a: "[a] April 24",
      b: "[b] April 5",
      c: "[c] April 29",
      d: "[d] April 13",
      e: "[e] April 11",
      answer: "[a] April 24",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.7) Who has won the League Cup 2021 (English football tournament)?",
      a: "[a] Arsenal",
      b: "[b] Chelsea",
      c: "[c] Barcelona",
      d: "[d] Atletico Madrid",
      e: "[e] Manchester City",
      answer: "[e] Manchester City",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.8) Where will the ITTF World Table Tennis Championships be held?",
      a: "[a] Brasília, Brazil",
      b: "[b] Sucre, Bolivia",
      c: "[c] Houston, USA",
      d: "[d] Santiago, Chile",
      e: "[e] Bogotá, Colombia",
      answer: "[c] Houston, USA",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.9) Where are the Maui Dolphins found?",
      a: "[a] Philippines",
      b: "[b] Singapore",
      c: "[c] Myanmar",
      d: "[d] Australia",
      e: "[e] New Zealand",
      answer: "[e] New Zealand",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.10) Who is the author of “Living Mountain” book?",
      a: "[a] Amitav Ghosh",
      b: "[b] Hari Kunzru",
      c: "[c] Ashok K. Banker",
      d: "[d] Devdutt Pattanaik",
      e: "[e] Ashwin Sanghi",
      answer: "[a] Amitav Ghosh",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.1) Who has become the first Indian woman to scale Mt Annapurna, the 10th highest mountain peak in the world?",
      a: "[a] Rakhi Shekhar",
      b: "[b] Anita Verma",
      c: "[c] Parul Baghel",
      d: "[d] Priyanka Mohite",
      e: "[e] Chanchal Sharma",
      answer: "[d] Priyanka Mohite",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.2) Which state has launched HARIHAR policy for providing employment, educational and financial benefits to abandoned and surrendered children?",
      a: "[a] Haryana",
      b: "[b] Chhattisgarh",
      c: "[c] Jharkhand",
      d: "[d] West Bengal",
      e: "[e] Tripura",
      answer: "[a] Haryana",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.3) What is the total foodgrain production estimate for 2020-21 as per the second advance estimates of production of principal crops by the Ministry of Agriculture & Farmers Welfare?",
      a: "[a] 120.32 million tonnes",
      b: "[b] 109.24 million tonnes",
      c: "[c] 49.36 million tonnes",
      d: "[d] 397.66 million tonnes",
      e: "[e] 303.34 million tonnes",
      answer: "[e] 303.34 million tonnes",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.4) Where did the Indian Army conducted ‘ARMEX-21’ exercise?",
      a: "[a] Ladakh",
      b: "[b] Uttarakhand",
      c: "[c] Himachal Pradesh",
      d: "[d] Both A and B",
      e: "[e] Both B and C",
      answer: "[d] Both A and B",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.5) Which city is the UNESCO’s World Book Capital for the 2021?",
      a: "[a] San Diego",
      b: "[b] Seattle",
      c: "[c] Boston",
      d: "[d] Tbilisi",
      e: "[e] Chicago",
      answer: "[d] Tbilisi",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.6) Which bank has collaborated with Google Pay and VISA to enable secured tokenisation on its credit cards?",
      a: "[a] Bank of Baroda",
      b: "[b] HSBC India",
      c: "[c] Bank of Maharashtra",
      d: "[d] Canara Bank",
      e: "[e] Bank of India",
      answer: "[b] HSBC India",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.7) Who has been appointed as the part-time chairman of HDFC Bank?",
      a: "[a] Atanu Chakraborty",
      b: "[b] Sharad Goklani",
      c: "[c] Matam Venkata Rao",
      d: "[d] Arun Kumar Singh",
      e: "[e] Pramod Chandra Mody",
      answer: "[a] Atanu Chakraborty",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.8) Who has won the ‘Nelson Mandela World Humanitarian Award 2021’?",
      a: "[a] Nitesh Kumar Mishra",
      b: "[b] Gyan Bhushan",
      c: "[c] Madan Lal",
      d: "[d] Rumana Sinha Sehgal",
      e: "[e] Bibhuti Bhushana Dash",
      answer: "[d] Rumana Sinha Sehgal",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.9) Which bank has signed an MOU with The Chennai Angles (angel investment group) to finance startups?",
      a: "[a] Indian Overseas Bank",
      b: "[b] Indian Bank",
      c: "[c] State Bank of India",
      d: "[d] UCO Bank",
      e: "[e] Union Bank of India",
      answer: "[b] Indian Bank",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.10) With which company has Mastercard partnered to launch ConQR - a Mastercard QR on Card solution - a payment solution for cardholders?",
      a: "[a] SREI Infrastructure Finance Limited",
      b: "[b] BOB Financial Solutions Limited",
      c: "[c] Religare Finvest Limited",
      d: "[d] PTC India Financial Services Limited",
      e: "[e] JM Financial Credit Solutions Limited",
      answer: "[b] BOB Financial Solutions Limited",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.1) In how many states has the govt launched the Unique Land Parcel Identification Number (ULPIN) scheme?",
      a: "[a] 15",
      b: "[b] 22",
      c: "[c] 35",
      d: "[d] 18",
      e: "[e] 10",
      answer: "[e] 10",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.2) How many digits will the Unique Land Parcel Identification Number – “the Aadhaar for land” – contain?",
      a: "[a] Twelve",
      b: "[b] Fourteen",
      c: "[c] Ten",
      d: "[d] Fifteen",
      e: "[e] Seven",
      answer: "[b] Fourteen",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.3) Who heads the Expert Committee for Factories and Dock Works?",
      a: "[a] Pankaj Kumar Devrani",
      b: "[b] Subrata Halder",
      c: "[c] R. K. Elangovan",
      d: "[d] Surendra Kumar",
      e: "[e] R. N. Bharti",
      answer: "[c] R. K. Elangovan",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.4) Who heads the Expert Committees on Fire Safety formed by Ministry of Labour?",
      a: "[a] Ram Lakhan Gupta",
      b: "[b] D. K. Shami",
      c: "[c] Shyam Sundar Verma",
      d: "[d] OM Prakash",
      e: "[e] Uttank Joshi",
      answer: "[b] D. K. Shami",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.5) Recently formed Expert Committees for the Building & Other Construction Works will review the Building and Other Construction Workers (Regulation of Employment and Conditions of Service) Central Rules. When were these ruled implemented?",
      a: "[a] 1889",
      b: "[b] 1980",
      c: "[c] 1998",
      d: "[d] 2001",
      e: "[e] 1999",
      answer: "[c] 1998",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.6) Which country chaired the 17th Bay of Bengal Initiative for Multi-Sectoral Technical and Economic Cooperation (BIMSTEC) Ministerial Meeting?",
      a: "[a] Bangladesh",
      b: "[b] Thailand",
      c: "[c] India",
      d: "[d] Sri Lanka",
      e: "[e] Myanmar",
      answer: "[d] Sri Lanka",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.7) Which country is hosting the BIMSTEC Centre for Weather and Climate?",
      a: "[a] Bangladesh",
      b: "[b] Thailand",
      c: "[c] India",
      d: "[d] Sri Lanka",
      e: "[e] Myanmar",
      answer: "[c] India",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.8) According to the “Prime Time for Real Time” report, more than 70.3 billion real-time payments transactions were processed globally in 2020, which highlights a surge of 41% as compared to the previous year. Worldwide the mobile wallet adoption rose to a historic high of 46% in 2020, up from 40.6% in 2019 and 18.9% in 2018. As far as India is concerned, the report exuberates confidence in the growth of real time payments transactions which, according to the report, are expected to account for 50% of the overall electronic transactions by 2024. Which of the following organizations has released this report?",
      a: "[a] Niti Aayog",
      b: "[b] Rocky Mountain Institute",
      c: "[c] Grant Thornton",
      d: "[d] ACI Worldwide",
      e: "[e] Brookings Institution",
      answer: "[d] ACI Worldwide",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.9) How much is the paid share capital of NPCI Bharat BillPay Ltd?",
      a: "[a] Rs 25 lakh",
      b: "[b] Rs 50 lakh",
      c: "[c] Rs 20 lakh",
      d: "[d] Rs 5 lakh",
      e: "[e] Rs 10 lakh",
      answer: "[d] Rs 5 lakh",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.10) Who has been appointed as the chairperson of the Public Enterprises Selection Board?",
      a: "[a] Rajesh Talwar",
      b: "[b] Mallika Srinivasan",
      c: "[c] Bharti Kashyap Sharma",
      d: "[d] Tuntuni Chowdhry",
      e: "[e] R. K. Bhati",
      answer: "[b] Mallika Srinivasan",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.11) With which company has UK-based CDC Group company partnered to conduct its first-ever pooled bond issuance (PBI) transaction in India worth Rs 320 crore?",
      a: "[a] Magma Fincorp Limited",
      b: "[b] SREI Infrastructure Finance Limited",
      c: "[c] PTC India Financial Services Limited",
      d: "[d] SBI DFHI Limited",
      e: "[e] Northern Arc Capital",
      answer: "[e] Northern Arc Capital",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.12) Who has been appointed as the brand ambassador of the Digit Insurance?",
      a: "[a] Harbhajan Singh",
      b: "[b] Geeta Basra",
      c: "[c] Mahendra Singh Dhoni",
      d: "[d] Virat Kohli",
      e: "[e] Yuvraj Singh",
      answer: "[c] Bratislava",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.13) What is the capital of Slovakia?",
      a: "[a] Tirana",
      b: "[b] Andorra la Vella",
      c: "[c] Bratislava",
      d: "[d] Yerevan",
      e: "[e] Yaounde",
      answer: "[a] Mukhmeet S. Bhatia",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.14) Who has been appointed as the new director general of Employees State Insurance Corporation?",
      a: "[a] Mukhmeet S. Bhatia",
      b: "[b] Bidisha Sengupta",
      c: "[c] Pranav Prakash",
      d: "[d] Susheela Tigga",
      e: "[e] Harpal Singh",
      answer: "[d] Rajnikanth",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.15) Who will be receiving the 51st edition of Dadasaheb Phalke award for the year 2020?",
      a: "[a] Dilip Kumar",
      b: "[b] Mumtaz Begum",
      c: "[c] Late Rishi Kapoor",
      d: "[d] Rajnikanth",
      e: "[e] Amitabh Bachchan",
      answer: "[a] Carmen Maria Machado",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.16) Who is the author of 'In The Dream House: A Memoir'?",
      a: "[a] Carmen Maria Machado",
      b: "[b] Armando Lucas Correa",
      c: "[c] Martha McPhee",
      d: "[d] Megan Miranda",
      e: "[e] Helen Phillips",
      answer: "[c] Mohan Kanda",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.17) Who is the author of Agriculture in India: Contemporary Challenges - in the Context of Doubling Farmers Income book?",
      a: "[a] Niraj Sharan",
      b: "[b] Kirti Nandkishor Gaikwad",
      c: "[c] Mohan Kanda",
      d: "[d] Sharad Saxena",
      e: "[e] Surendra Prasad",
      answer: "[d] April 2",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.18) When is World Autism Awareness Day celebrated?",
      a: "[a] April 20",
      b: "[b] April 11",
      c: "[c] April 12",
      d: "[d] April 2",
      e: "[e] April 3",
      answer: "[e] Kshama Fernandes",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.19) Who is the CEO of Northern Arc Capital?",
      a: "[a] Peter Simpson",
      b: "[b] Andrew Haines",
      c: "[c] Craig Donaldson",
      d: "[d] Juergen Maier",
      e: "[e] Kshama Fernandes",
      answer: "[a] Dilip Asbe",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.1) Which IIT has successfully commercialised COVIRAP - the novel diagnostic technology?",
      a: "[a] IIT-Kharagpur",
      b: "[b] IIT-Hyderabad",
      c: "[c] IIT-Gandhinagar",
      d: "[d] IIT-Delhi",
      e: "[e] IIT-Kanpur",
      answer: "[a] IIT-Kharagpur",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.2) How much is the Agriculture Infrastructure and Development Cess on Petrol?",
      a: "[a] Rs 5 per litre",
      b: "[b] Rs 3 per litre",
      c: "[c] Rs 0.5 per litre",
      d: "[d] Rs 2.5 per litre",
      e: "[e] Rs 1 per litre",
      answer: "[d] Rs 2.5 per litre",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.3) Which has become the first state in India to have uniform civil code?",
      a: "[a] Mizoram",
      b: "[b] Sikkim",
      c: "[c] Nagaland",
      d: "[d] Tripura",
      e: "[e] Goa",
      answer: "[e] Goa",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.4) Which state has signed an MoU with World Trade Centre to provide a conclusive environment in the state for bringing investment through the new modes and operations?",
      a: "[a] Gujarat",
      b: "[b] Telangana",
      c: "[c] Odisha",
      d: "[d] Andhra Pradesh",
      e: "[e] Haryana",
      answer: "[e] Haryana",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.5) With which IIT has National Cooperative Development Corporation (NCDC) signed an MoU for collaboration in areas related to the development of cooperatives, agriculture and allied sectors for sustainable development?",
      a: "[a] IIT Patna",
      b: "[b] IIT Kharagpur",
      c: "[c] IIT Bhuvneshwar",
      d: "[d] IIT Guwahati",
      e: "[e] IIT Ropar",
      answer: "[b] IIT Kharagpur",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.6) Which has become the first country in the world to ratify the Regional Comprehensive Economic Partnership (RCEP) agreement?",
      a: "[a] Australia",
      b: "[b] South Korea",
      c: "[c] China",
      d: "[d] Japan",
      e: "[e] Singapore",
      answer: "[e] Singapore",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.7) What is the name of the instruments used by NASA to generate oxygen on Mars?",
      a: "[a] Moxie",
      b: "[b] Max",
      c: "[c] Skylab",
      d: "[d] Ingenuity",
      e: "[e] Ceres",
      answer: "[a] Moxie",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.8) Which of the following country has been recommended as the Countries of Particular Concern by U.S. Commission on International Religious Freedom (USCIRF)?",
      a: "[a] India",
      b: "[b] Russia",
      c: "[c] Vietnam",
      d: "[d] Syria",
      e: "[e] All of the Above",
      answer: "[e] All of the Above",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.9) What is the 2021 Global average score in the World Economic Forum’s Global Energy Transition Index 2021?",
      a: "[a] 59",
      b: "[b] 60",
      c: "[c] 80",
      d: "[d] 43",
      e: "[e] 72",
      answer: "[a] 59",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.10) What is India’s rank in the Global Energy Transition Index 2021?",
      a: "[a] 87",
      b: "[b] 142",
      c: "[c] 102",
      d: "[d] 98",
      e: "[e] 67",
      answer: "[a] 87",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.1) With which country’s Administrative Council for Economic Defense has Competition Commission of India signed an MoU for cooperation?",
      a: "[a] Brazil",
      b: "[b] New Papua Guinea",
      c: "[c] Vanuatu",
      d: "[d] Fiji",
      e: "[e] New Caledonia",
      answer: "[a] Brazil",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.2) According to the Global Energy Review 2021 by International Energy Agency (IEA), global carbon dioxide (CO2) emissions would rise to ___ this year?",
      a: "[a] 20 billion tonnes",
      b: "[b] 40 billion tonnes",
      c: "[c] 33 billion tonnes",
      d: "[d] 50 billion tonnes",
      e: "[e] 13 billion tonnes",
      answer: "[c] 33 billion tonnes",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.3) What is the total corpus of the RBI’s government securities acquisition programme (G-SAP) 1.0?",
      a: "[a] ₹4 trillion",
      b: "[b] ₹1 trillion",
      c: "[c] ₹2 trillion",
      d: "[d] ₹10 trillion",
      e: "[e] ₹5 trillion",
      answer: "[b] ₹1 trillion",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.4) Asian Development Bank (ADB) has partnered with Habitat for Humanity International to help microfinance institutions (MFIs) deliver housing loans to low-income families in rural and peri-urban areas of India, Bangladesh, ____ , and the _____?",
      a: "[a] Indonesia",
      b: "[b] Philippines",
      c: "[c] Malaysia",
      d: "[d] Both A and B",
      e: "[e] Both B and C",
      answer: "[d] Both A and B",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.5) Who has been appointed as the new chairman of Credit Suisse?",
      a: "[a] Warren East",
      b: "[b] Horta-Osorio",
      c: "[c] Andy Ransom",
      d: "[d] Liv Garfield",
      e: "[e] Emma Walmsley",
      answer: "[b] Horta-Osorio",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.6) Who is the MD and CEO of DCB Bank?",
      a: "[a] Karnam Sekar",
      b: "[b] Sandeep Bakhshi",
      c: "[c] V. Vaidyananthan",
      d: "[d] Murali M. Natrajan",
      e: "[e] R. Seshasayee",
      answer: "[d] Murali M. Natrajan",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.7) When is National Civil Services Day observed?",
      a: "[a] April 20",
      b: "[b] April 21",
      c: "[c] April 18",
      d: "[d] April 10",
      e: "[e] April 11",
      answer: "[b] April 21",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.8) G Venkata Subbaiah is related to which field?",
      a: "[a] Writer",
      b: "[b] Journalism",
      c: "[c] Environmentalist",
      d: "[d] Banker",
      e: "[e] Shuttler",
      answer: "[a] Writer",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.9) Where is the headquarters of Universal Postal Union (UPU)?",
      a: "[a] Helsinki",
      b: "[b] Riga",
      c: "[c] Tallinn",
      d: "[d] Berne",
      e: "[e] Warsaw",
      answer: "[d] Berne",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.10) Who among the following is known as the Father of Banking Reforms in India?",
      a: "[a] M. Narasimham",
      b: "[b] Raghuram Rajan",
      c: "[c] D. Subbarao",
      d: "[d] H. V. R. Iyengar",
      e: "[e] P. C. Bhattacharya",
      answer: "[a] M. Narasimham",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.1) Where has Asia’s longest High-Speed Track (11.3 km) for vehicles’ testing – named as NATRAX (National Automotive Test Tracks) –been inaugurated?",
      a: "[a] Madhya Pradesh",
      b: "[b] Karnataka",
      c: "[c] Delhi",
      d: "[d] Uttar Pradesh",
      e: "[e] Gujarat",
      answer: "[a] Madhya Pradesh",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.2) Which state has launched a first-of-its-kind initiative - Chief Minister Dalit Empowerment Programme - to provide financial assistance of Rs 10 lakh to the eligible Dalit beneficiaries?",
      a: "[a] Karnataka",
      b: "[b] Tamil Nadu",
      c: "[c] Telangana",
      d: "[d] Andhra Pradesh",
      e: "[e] Odisha",
      answer: "[c] Telangana",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.3) Where did the G-20 Foreign Ministers meeting 2021 take place?",
      a: "[a] Venice",
      b: "[b] Milan",
      c: "[c] Naples",
      d: "[d] Bologna",
      e: "[e] Matera",
      answer: "[e] Matera",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.4) What is India’s rank in the Global Cybersecurity Index (GCI) 2020?",
      a: "[a] 10th",
      b: "[b] 55th",
      c: "[c] 87th",
      d: "[d] 63rd",
      e: "[e] 100th",
      answer: "[a] 10th",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.5) How much is the basic customs duty on crude palm oil in India?",
      a: "[a] 20%",
      b: "[b] 10%",
      c: "[c] 5%",
      d: "[d] 15%",
      e: "[e] 25%",
      answer: "[b] 10%",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.6) Who has been appointed as the US Charge’d Affairs in India?",
      a: "[a] Anil Yadav",
      b: "[b] B N Bhaskar",
      c: "[c] Atul Keshap",
      d: "[d] Binod Kumar",
      e: "[e] Astik Sinha",
      answer: "[c] Atul Keshap",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.7) When is the International Day of the Tropics observed?",
      a: "[a] June 29",
      b: "[b] June 20",
      c: "[c] June 18",
      d: "[d] June 13",
      e: "[e] June 11",
      answer: "[a] June 29",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.8) Which country does Sydney McLaughlin belong to?",
      a: "[a] Croatia",
      b: "[b] Australia",
      c: "[c] Poland",
      d: "[d] America",
      e: "[e] Serbia",
      answer: "[d] America",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.9) Who has made India's first ever entry to Olympics with 'A' qualification in swimming?",
      a: "[a] Gaurav Shukla",
      b: "[b] Suraj Prakash Sharma",
      c: "[c] Anil Yadav",
      d: "[d] Sajan Prakash",
      e: "[e] Sandeep Kumar",
      answer: "[d] Sajan Prakash",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.10) Who is the world number one archer at present in women’s category?",
      a: "[a] Dola Banerjee",
      b: "[b] Bombayla Devi Laishram",
      c: "[c] Chekrovolu Swuro",
      d: "[d] Deepika Kumari",
      e: "[e] Laxmi Rani Majhi",
      answer: "[d] Deepika Kumari",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.1) Where is Hemis Festival celebrated in India?",
      a: "[a] Assam",
      b: "[b] Tripura",
      c: "[c] Odisha",
      d: "[d] Ladakh",
      e: "[e] Nagaland",
      answer: "[d] Ladakh",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.2) Which of the following institution has partnered with Global Alliance for Mass Entrepreneurship (GAME) to help MSMEs address their challenges that arose during the pandemic?",
      a: "[a] NABARD",
      b: "[b] SIDBI",
      c: "[c] State Bank of India",
      d: "[d] Yes Bank",
      e: "[e] Ujjivan Small Finance Bank Limited",
      answer: "[b] SIDBI",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.3) Which company has invested in Instamojo for empowering millions of MSMEs and gig workers by helping them to digitize and set up online stores, digital payment acceptance infrastructure and reach out to customers, even during the pandemic?",
      a: "[a] Mastercard",
      b: "[b] Amazon",
      c: "[c] Flipkart",
      d: "[d] Google",
      e: "[e] Twitter",
      answer: "[a] Mastercard",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.4) In which state has World Bank launched SALT program?",
      a: "[a] Maharashtra",
      b: "[b] Gujarat",
      c: "[c] Andhra Pradesh",
      d: "[d] Tamil Nadu",
      e: "[e] Telangana",
      answer: "[c] Andhra Pradesh",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.5) Who has been appointed as the chairman of National Dairy Development Board?",
      a: "[a] Ashish Jaiswal",
      b: "[b] Sumit Verma",
      c: "[c] Sachin Vashisth",
      d: "[d] Vinita Sinha",
      e: "[e] Meenesh Shah",
      answer: "[e] Meenesh Shah",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.6) When was the Central Vigilance Commission established?",
      a: "[a] 1970",
      b: "[b] 1964",
      c: "[c] 1950",
      d: "[d] 1999",
      e: "[e] 1997",
      answer: "[b] 1964",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.7) Which airport from India has received Airport Council International’s (ACI) Roll of Excellence 2021?",
      a: "[a] Indira Gandhi International Airport",
      b: "[b] Chhatrapati Shivaji Maharaj International Airport",
      c: "[c] Kempegowda International Airport",
      d: "[d] Cochin International Airport Ltd",
      e: "[e] Netaji Subhash Chandra Bose International Airport",
      answer: "[d] Cochin International Airport Ltd",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.8) Who is the author of “Growing Up Biden: A Memoir”?",
      a: "[a] Christian Burno",
      b: "[b] Nandi Taylor",
      c: "[c] Zora Neale Hurston",
      d: "[d] Valerie Biden Owens",
      e: "[e] Mikki Kendall",
      answer: "[d] Valerie Biden Owens",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.9) Who is the chairperson of the taskforce formed by the govt under Mission Karamyogi?",
      a: "[a] Vijoy Kumar Singh",
      b: "[b] Sanjay Sharan",
      c: "[c] Jay Karan Singh",
      d: "[d] S D Shibu Lal",
      e: "[e] Gaurav Kumar",
      answer: "[d] S D Shibu Lal",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.10) Where is the headquarter of Airport Council International located?",
      a: "[a] Canada",
      b: "[b] Austria",
      c: "[c] Netherlands",
      d: "[d] Sweden",
      e: "[e] Denmark",
      answer: "[a] Canada",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.1) What is the name of the portal launched for enabling the parties to file their appeals, miscellaneous applications, documents, paper books, etc., related to income tax electronically?",
      a: "[a] iddat-e-dwar",
      b: "[b] vishwas-e-dwar",
      c: "[c] kar-e-dwar",
      d: "[d] itat-e-dwar",
      e: "[e] vikas-e-dwar",
      answer: "[d] itat-e-dwar",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.2) Which of the following statement is true about the Enforcing Contracts Portal?",
      a: "[a] It aims to promote the contract enforcement regime in the country",
      b: "[b] It aims to reinforce the contracts made by Exim Bank with other countries",
      c: "[c] It aims to increase the project exports",
      d: "[d] It aims to promote foreign direct investments in the country by strengthening contract enforcement",
      e: "[e] It aims to enforce the financial contracts solely",
      answer:
        "[a] It aims to promote the contract enforcement regime in the country",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.3) Where is Kudankulam nuclear power plant located?",
      a: "[a] Andhra Pradesh",
      b: "[b] Karnataka",
      c: "[c] Odisha",
      d: "[d] Kerala",
      e: "[e] Tamil Nadu",
      answer: "[e] Tamil Nadu",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.4) Which state has decided to set up district-level industry and investment promotion agencies to create more economic opportunities?",
      a: "[a] Madhya Pradesh",
      b: "[b] Odisha",
      c: "[c] Uttar Pradesh",
      d: "[d] Tamil Nadu",
      e: "[e] Telangana",
      answer: "[b] Odisha",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.5) Which of the following organization has launched the LowCarbon.Earth, in partnership with UNEP?",
      a: "[a] Society for Environment and Development",
      b: "[b] Forum of Activities for Community Environment",
      c: "[c] Centre for Environment Education",
      d: "[d] WWF India",
      e: "[e] Massive Earth Foundation",
      answer: "[e] Massive Earth Foundation",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.6) Who has won the Fukuoka Prize for 2021?",
      a: "[a] Vijoy Kumar Singh",
      b: "[b] Jogiranjan Panigrahi",
      c: "[c] Gaurav Kumar",
      d: "[d] P. Sainath",
      e: "[e] Kumar Padmapani Bora",
      answer: "[d] P. Sainath",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.7) How much interest rate will be applicable on loans taken by healthcare sector under the ₹1.1 lakh crore loan guarantee scheme for Covid-affected sectors of the govt?",
      a: "[a] 7.95%",
      b: "[b] 5.6%",
      c: "[c] 6.15%",
      d: "[d] 3.71%",
      e: "[e] 8.91%",
      answer: "[a] 7.95%",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.8) What is the total cap of Emergency Credit Line Guarantee scheme at present?",
      a: "[a] Rs 5 lakh crores",
      b: "[b] Rs 1 lakh crores",
      c: "[c] Rs 2.5 lakh crores",
      d: "[d] Rs 4.5 lakh crores",
      e: "[e] Rs 3 lakh crores",
      answer: "[d] Rs 4.5 lakh crores",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.9) How much loan will be provided to the tourist guides at 100% guarantee under the central govt’s economic relief measures?",
      a: "[a] Rs 2 lakh",
      b: "[b] Rs 5 lakh",
      c: "[c] Rs 4 lakh",
      d: "[d] Rs 1 lakh",
      e: "[e] Rs 3 lakh",
      answer: "[d] Rs 1 lakh",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.10) How much amount will be infused in the National Export Insurance Account (NEIA) as part of the economic relief measures to support project exporters?",
      a: "[a] ₹22,000 crore",
      b: "[b] ₹33,000 crore",
      c: "[c] ₹15,000 crore",
      d: "[d] ₹88,000 crore",
      e: "[e] ₹10,000 crore",
      answer: "[b] ₹33,000 crore",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.1) With which state has Triton Electric Vehicles (US firm) signed an MoU to set up its manufacturing facility of Rs 2100 crores for e-vehicles in the state?",
      a: "[a] Telangana",
      b: "[b] Madhya Pradesh",
      c: "[c] Maharashtra",
      d: "[d] Andhra Pradesh",
      e: "[e] Gujarat",
      answer: "[a] Telangana",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.2) Where was 16th Meeting of Security Council Secretaries of Shanghai Corporation Organisation (SCO) member states held?",
      a: "[a] Khujand",
      b: "[b] Kulob",
      c: "[c] Panjakent",
      d: "[d] Dushanbe",
      e: "[e] Nurek",
      answer: "[d] Dushanbe",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.3) Which agency has released the “Annual Report on Children and Armed Conflict” report?",
      a: "[a] UN",
      b: "[b] UNESCO",
      c: "[c] Kids Rights Foundation",
      d: "[d] Save the Children",
      e: "[e] UNICEF",
      answer: "[a] UN",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.4) Which university has topped the QS Executive MBA Rankings 2021?",
      a: "[a] HEC Paris",
      b: "[b] Stanford University",
      c: "[c] The University of Chicago Booth School of Business",
      d: "[d] Haas School of Business",
      e: "[e] IESE Business School",
      answer: "[a] HEC Paris",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.5) Which company has announced to set up India’s 1st Carbon Fibre Manufacturing Unit to cater to aerospace and defence needs?",
      a: "[a] Bharat Dynamics",
      b: "[b] BEML Limited",
      c: "[c] Ordnance Factory Board",
      d: "[d] Reliance Industries Ltd",
      e: "[e] Tata Advanced Systems",
      answer: "[d] Reliance Industries Ltd",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.6) Which company has launched a tailor-made insurance policy, “Women's cancer shield” for breast cancer female patients, in partnership with Alliance Insurance?",
      a: "[a] Fabindia",
      b: "[b] Unilever",
      c: "[c] Clovia",
      d: "[d] Pernod Ricard",
      e: "[e] Nykaa",
      answer: "[c] Clovia",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.7) Which of the following banks has approved the $125 million Kerala Resilient Program for supporting the state in preparing against natural disasters, climate change impacts, disease outbreaks, and pandemics?",
      a: "[a] Asian Infrastructure Investment Bank",
      b: "[b] New Development Bank",
      c: "[c] International Monetary Bank",
      d: "[d] European Bank for Reconstruction and Development",
      e: "[e] World Bank",
      answer: "[e] World Bank",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.8) When is the Day of the Seafarer observed?",
      a: "[a] June 17",
      b: "[b] June 13",
      c: "[c] June 25",
      d: "[d] June 11",
      e: "[e] June 15",
      answer: "[c] June 25",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.9) When is World Vitiligo Day observed?",
      a: "[a] June 11",
      b: "[b] June 13",
      c: "[c] June 14",
      d: "[d] June 25",
      e: "[e] June 10",
      answer: "[d] June 25",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.10) How many people were suffering from drug use disorders in 2020, as per the World Drug Report 2021 of United Nations' Office on Drugs and Crime (UNODC)?",
      a: "[a] 18 million",
      b: "[b] 24 million",
      c: "[c] 36 million",
      d: "[d] 20 million",
      e: "[e] 16 million",
      answer: "[c] 36 million",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.1) Which state has partnered with United Nations World Food Programme (WFP) to improve household food and nutritional security by strengthening livelihood initiatives, reaching thousands of state-supported Women's Self-Help Groups?",
      a: "[a] Odisha",
      b: "[b] Maharashtra",
      c: "[c] Andhra Pradesh",
      d: "[d] Gujarat",
      e: "[e] Telangana",
      answer: "[a] Odisha",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.2) Which of the following state / UT govt has announced to launch Mukhya Mantri Covid-19 Pariwar Aarthik Sahayata Yojana to provide financial aid to the families of victims of Covid-19?",
      a: "[a] Haryana",
      b: "[b] Punjab",
      c: "[c] Uttarakhand",
      d: "[d] Delhi",
      e: "[e] Puducherry",
      answer: "[d] Delhi",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.3) With which Caribbean country has India recently signed an MoU for the exchange of tax information and assistance in the tax collection?",
      a: "[a] Antigua and Barbuda",
      b: "[b] Dominica",
      c: "[c] Jamaica",
      d: "[d] Guyana",
      e: "[e] Saint Vincent and the Grenadines",
      answer: "[e] Saint Vincent and the Grenadines",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.4) In which country has Tax Inspectors Without Border Program been launched by India and UNDP?",
      a: "[a] Nepal",
      b: "[b] Papua New Guinea",
      c: "[c] Singapore",
      d: "[d] Thailand",
      e: "[e] Bhutan",
      answer: "[e] Bhutan",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.5) Which edition of the BRICS Young Scientist Conclave will be organized by India during 13-16 September 2021?",
      a: "[a] 6th",
      b: "[b] 3rd",
      c: "[c] 5th",
      d: "[d] 7th",
      e: "[e] 10th",
      answer: "[a] 6th",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.6) With which bank has Afthonia Lab (a fintech incubator) partnered to support fintech companies in India for transforming the Indian financial sector?",
      a: "[a] Bandhan Bank",
      b: "[b] Yes Bank",
      c: "[c] HDFC Bank",
      d: "[d] IndusInd Bank",
      e: "[e] RBL Bank",
      answer: "[b] Yes Bank",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.7) What is India’s GDP forecast for FY22 by S&P?",
      a: "[a] 9.5%",
      b: "[b] 10.1%",
      c: "[c] 8.5%",
      d: "[d] 8.8%",
      e: "[e] 7.8%",
      answer: "[a] 9.5%",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.8) What is the Global GDP forecast for FY23 by World Bank?",
      a: "[a] 4.3%",
      b: "[b] 5.6%",
      c: "[c] 3.1%",
      d: "[d] 5.5%",
      e: "[e] 4.6%",
      answer: "[a] 4.3%",
    },
    {
      question:
        'Q.9) Who is the singer of "Lakshya Tera Samne Hai", which is India\'s "Official Olympic Theme Song" for the upcoming Tokyo Olympics 2020?',
      a: "[a] Sonu Nigam",
      b: "[b] Shaan",
      c: "[c] Atif Aslam",
      d: "[d] Mohit Chauhan",
      e: "[e] Armaan Malik",
      answer: "[d] Mohit Chauhan",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.10) Who was the player of the match in the 1st edition of ICC World Test Championship 2021?",
      a: "[a] Kane Williamson",
      b: "[b] Devon Conway",
      c: "[c] Ross Taylor",
      d: "[d] Trent Boult",
      e: "[e] Kyle Jamieson",
      answer: "[e] Kyle Jamieson",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.1) Which has become India’s first rabies-free state?",
      a: "[a] Manipur",
      b: "[b] Tripura",
      c: "[c] Goa",
      d: "[d] Nagaland",
      e: "[e] Uttarakhand",
      answer: "[c] Goa",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.2) Which state has signed an MoU with the UK government to strengthen and support clean and green energy tech startups in the state?",
      a: "[a] Tamil Nadu",
      b: "[b] Maharashtra",
      c: "[c] Madhya Pradesh",
      d: "[d] Gujarat",
      e: "[e] Odisha",
      answer: "[b] Maharashtra",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.3) Which of the following institution developed world’s first genetically modified (GM) rubber plant?",
      a: "[a] Rubber Technology Institute",
      b: "[b] Rubber Research and Development Institute",
      c: "[c] IIT-Madras",
      d: "[d] Rubber Research Institute of India",
      e: "[e] Rubber Development Institute",
      answer: "[d] Rubber Research Institute of India",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.4) Which bank has launched 'Aarogyam Loan' business loan scheme for the healthcare sector to extend loan support in the wake of Covid-19 pandemic?",
      a: "[a] HDFC Bank",
      b: "[b] State Bank of India",
      c: "[c] Canara Bank",
      d: "[d] Axis Bank",
      e: "[e] ICICI Bank",
      answer: "[b] State Bank of India",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.5) Who heads the panel formed by International Financial Services Centres Authority to examine global best practices in ship financing and leasing, identify opportunities and prepare a roadmap to enable such activities from GIFT IFSC?",
      a: "[a] OM Prakash",
      b: "[b] Uttank Joshi",
      c: "[c] Vandana Agarwal",
      d: "[d] P. Rangarajan",
      e: "[e] Bidisha Sengupta",
      answer: "[c] Vandana Agarwal",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.6) When was Biotech-Krishi Innovation Science Application Network launched?",
      a: "[a] 2018",
      b: "[b] 2017",
      c: "[c] 2014",
      d: "[d] 2013",
      e: "[e] 2012",
      answer: "[b] 2017",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.7) Where is India’s largest solar carport located?",
      a: "[a] Pune",
      b: "[b] Cochin",
      c: "[c] Nagpur",
      d: "[d] Kanpur",
      e: "[e] Guwahati",
      answer: "[a] Pune",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.8) How much wealth was reduced in 2020 in India, as per the “Global Wealth Report” 2021?",
      a: "[a] 4.4%",
      b: "[b] 5.1%",
      c: "[c] 2.3%",
      d: "[d] 3.7%",
      e: "[e] 1.6%",
      answer: "[a] 4.4%",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.9) When is International Olympic Day observed?",
      a: "[a] June 25",
      b: "[b] June 23",
      c: "[c] June 17",
      d: "[d] June 15",
      e: "[e] June 12",
      answer: "[b] June 23",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.10) Who is the author of “It’s A Wonderful Life: Roads To Happiness”?",
      a: "[a] Devdutt Pattanaik",
      b: "[b] Anand Neelakantan",
      c: "[c] Vikram Chandra",
      d: "[d] Ruskin Bond",
      e: "[e] Upamanyu Chatterjee",
      answer: "[d] Ruskin Bond",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.1) Which company has received a contract from Ministry of Defence for the construction of two Pollution Control Vessels (PCVs) for the Indian Coast Guard?",
      a: "[a] L&T",
      b: "[b] Bharat Dynamic Ltd",
      c: "[c] GRSE Ltd",
      d: "[d] Goa Shipyard Ltd",
      e: "[e] Mahindra Defence Systems",
      answer: "[d] Goa Shipyard Ltd",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.2) With which European country has India formed a trilateral partnership to create stability in the Indo-Pacific region, along with Japan?",
      a: "[a] Germany",
      b: "[b] Belgium",
      c: "[c] Spain",
      d: "[d] UK",
      e: "[e] Italy",
      answer: "[e] Italy",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.3) How many integrated theatre commands are operating in India at present?",
      a: "[a] Five",
      b: "[b] Two",
      c: "[c] Three",
      d: "[d] Zero",
      e: "[e] One",
      answer: "[b] Two",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.4) With which country has India signed an MoU for cooperation in the field of agriculture and allied sectors?",
      a: "[a] Fiji",
      b: "[b] Cambodia",
      c: "[c] Laos",
      d: "[d] Vietnam",
      e: "[e] Philippines",
      answer: "[a] Fiji",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.5) The surplus transfer by RBI to Central Govt in FY21 is equivalent to __ percent of GDP, as per RBI’s State of Economy report?",
      a: "[a] 0.44%",
      b: "[b] 0.10%",
      c: "[c] 0.33%",
      d: "[d] 0.18%",
      e: "[e] 0.29%",
      answer: "[a] 0.44%",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.6) What is the GDP forecast for India for 2021 by Moody’s?",
      a: "[a] 10.5%",
      b: "[b] 9.3%",
      c: "[c] 8.8%",
      d: "[d] 11.5%",
      e: "[e] 9.6%",
      answer: "[e] 9.6%",
    },
    {
      question:
        'Q.7) Which ministry has launched "Jaan Hai To Jahan Hai" to create awareness about coronavirus vaccination and prevent apprehensions and rumours?',
      a: "[a] Ministry of Rural Development",
      b: "[b] Ministry of Minority Affairs",
      c: "[c] Ministry of Health and Family Welfare",
      d: "[d] Ministry of Tribal Affairs",
      e: "[e] Ministry of Panchayati Raj",
      answer: "[b] Ministry of Minority Affairs",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.8) Which state has signed an MoU with the Survey of India for implementing the Svamitva scheme in the state?",
      a: "[a] West Bengal",
      b: "[b] Odisha",
      c: "[c] Andhra Pradesh",
      d: "[d] Assam",
      e: "[e] Telangana",
      answer: "[d] Assam",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.9) Who has been appointed as the “Ambassador of Forest Frontline Heroes” by WWF India?",
      a: "[a] Lily Pal",
      b: "[b] Ashish Jaiswal",
      c: "[c] Upasana Kamineni",
      d: "[d] Deojeet Kumar",
      e: "[e] Nitesh Kumar",
      answer: "[c] Upasana Kamineni",
    },
    {
      question:
        'Q.10) Who is the author of "My Joys and Sorrows – as a Mother of a Special Child"?',
      a: "[a] Ravi Shanker",
      b: "[b] Vinita Sinha",
      c: "[c] Deojeet Kumar",
      d: "[d] Krishna Saksena",
      e: "[e] Sumit Verma",
      answer: "[d] Krishna Saksena",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.1) Where did Indian Navy and EU NAVFOR Somalia conduct a joint naval exercise?",
      a: "[a] Gulf of Berbera",
      b: "[b] Gulf of Tadjoura",
      c: "[c] Gulf of Aqaba",
      d: "[d] Gulf of Suez",
      e: "[e] Gulf of Aden",
      answer: "[e] Gulf of Aden",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.2) With which bank has National Small Industries Corporation (NSIC) recently signed an MoU to support MSMEs with credit requirements?",
      a: "[a] Indian Bank",
      b: "[b] DBS Bank India",
      c: "[c] Bandhan Bank",
      d: "[d] City Union Bank",
      e: "[e] Union Bank of India",
      answer: "[e] Union Bank of India",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.3) How much FDI flow did India receive in 2020, as per the World Investment Report 2021?",
      a: "[a] $64 billion",
      b: "[b] $51 billion",
      c: "[c] $80 billion",
      d: "[d] $35 billion",
      e: "[e] $20 billion",
      answer: "[a] $64 billion",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.4) Who is the chair of SEBI’s reconstituted Takeover Panel?",
      a: "[a] N Venkatram",
      b: "[b] Darius Khambata",
      c: "[c] Thomas Mathew T",
      d: "[d] NK Sodhi",
      e: "[e] K Kannan",
      answer: "[d] NK Sodhi",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.5) Who has been named as a member of a High-Level Advisory Group (HLAG) on Sustainable and Inclusive Recovery and Growth of World Bank-IMF from India?",
      a: "[a] Hardeep Singh Puri",
      b: "[b] Asoke Kumar Mukerji",
      c: "[c] Syed Akbaruddin",
      d: "[d] Montek Singh Ahluwalia",
      e: "[e] T. S. Tirumurti",
      answer: "[d] Montek Singh Ahluwalia",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.6) Who has won CEU’s Open Society Prize 2021?",
      a: "[a] Nirupam Sen",
      b: "[b] Vijay K. Nambiar",
      c: "[c] KK Shailaja",
      d: "[d] Kamalesh Sharma",
      e: "[e] Prakash Shah",
      answer: "[c] KK Shailaja",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.7) Where is the operational headquarter of Operation Atalanta located?",
      a: "[a] UK",
      b: "[b] Spain",
      c: "[c] Germany",
      d: "[d] Denmark",
      e: "[e] Norway",
      answer: "[b] Spain",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.8) As per the World Investment Report 2021, FDI inflows reduced by __ percent in 2020 to $1 trillion?",
      a: "[a] 35%",
      b: "[b] 40%",
      c: "[c] 20%",
      d: "[d] 10%",
      e: "[e] 15%",
      answer: "[a] 35%",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.9) Which state has launched ‘Ashirbad’ scheme for education, health and maintenance of Covid orphans?",
      a: "[a] Odisha",
      b: "[b] Andhra Pradesh",
      c: "[c] Karnataka",
      d: "[d] Kerala",
      e: "[e] Madhya Pradesh",
      answer: "[a] Odisha",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.10) Who is the author of 'The 7 Sins of Being A Mother'?",
      a: "[a] Aravind Adiga",
      b: "[b] Jeet Thayil",
      c: "[c] Tahira Kashyap Khurrana",
      d: "[d] Amit Chaudhuri",
      e: "[e] Kiran Desai",
      answer: "[c] Tahira Kashyap Khurrana",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.1) Recently, US-India hydrogen taskforce has been launched under the aegis of Strategic Clean Energy Partnership (SCEP) for the exploration of hydrogen. The taskforce has been launched by United States Department of Energy (DOE), the Indian Ministry of New and Renewable Energy (MNRE), along with the US India Strategic Partnership Forum (USISPF). US India Strategic Partnership Forum will act as the Secretariat for the Task Force. Dr Ken Vincent is the co-chair of US-India Hydrogen Task Force from US side, and director of Office of Asian Affairs, Office of International Affairs at Department of Energy (DOE). Who is the co-chair of this taskforce from India?",
      a: "[a] Madan Lal",
      b: "[b] Prakash Chandra Maithani",
      c: "[c] Bibhuti Bhushana Dash",
      d: "[d] Susheela Tigga",
      e: "[e] Banaja Behra",
      answer: "[b] Prakash Chandra Maithani",
    },
    {
      question:
        'Q.2) Which state government will constitute an "Economic Advisory Council to the Chief Minister" with leading economic experts like Esther Duflo and Raghuram Rajan as its members?',
      a: "[a] Maharashtra",
      b: "[b] Tamil Nadu",
      c: "[c] Karnataka",
      d: "[d] Odisha",
      e: "[e] Andhra Pradesh",
      answer: "[b] Tamil Nadu",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.3) Which country will get world's most powerful magnet?",
      a: "[a] Denmark",
      b: "[b] Germany",
      c: "[c] Italy",
      d: "[d] France",
      e: "[e] UK",
      answer: "[d] France",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.4) With which company has Bharti Airtel for implementing 5G network solutions for India?",
      a: "[a] HCL Technologies",
      b: "[b] Infosys",
      c: "[c] IBM",
      d: "[d] Tech Mahindra",
      e: "[e] Tata Consultancy Services",
      answer: "[e] Tata Consultancy Services",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.5) What is the name of the app launched by India, in partnership with WHO, to provide yoga training videos in different languages for people across the world?",
      a: "[a] m- Yoga app",
      b: "[b] v- Yoga app",
      c: "[c] t- Yoga app",
      d: "[d] u- Yoga app",
      e: "[e] w- Yoga app",
      answer: "[a] m- Yoga app",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.6) Who has become the first transgender athlete to compete at the Olympics?",
      a: "[a] Veronica Ivy",
      b: "[b] Chris Mosier",
      c: "[c] Andraya Yearwood",
      d: "[d] Laurel Hubbard",
      e: "[e] Hannah Mouncey",
      answer: "[d] Laurel Hubbard",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.7) When was India-US Strategic Energy Partnership launched?",
      a: "[a] 2017",
      b: "[b] 2015",
      c: "[c] 2010",
      d: "[d] 2018",
      e: "[e] 2019",
      answer: "[d] 2018",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.8) How many poor people (with income of $2 per day or less in purchasing power parity) have been estimated in India by Pew Research Centre and World Bank?",
      a: "[a] 100 million",
      b: "[b] 134 million",
      c: "[c] 80 million",
      d: "[d] 23 million",
      e: "[e] 90 million",
      answer: "[b] 134 million",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.9) What is the theme of World Refugee Day 2021?",
      a: "[a] Every Action Counts, All Lives Matter.",
      b: "[b] Together we heal, learn and shine",
      c: "[c] Now More Than Ever, We Need to Stand with Refugees",
      d: "[d] Understanding the Plight of Refugees",
      e: "[e] Act Now To Stop Displacement",
      answer: "[b] Together we heal, learn and shine",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.10) When is the World Hydrography Day observed?",
      a: "[a] June 21",
      b: "[b] June 28",
      c: "[c] June 11",
      d: "[d] June 18",
      e: "[e] June 19",
      answer: "[a] June 21",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.1) Who has won the UN Land for Life Award 2021?",
      a: "[a] Shyam Sunder Jyani",
      b: "[b] Vijoy Kumar Singh",
      c: "[c] Hemant Kumar Nanda",
      d: "[d] Ravi Shanker Shukla",
      e: "[e] Kumar Padmapani Bora",
      answer: "[a] Shyam Sunder Jyani",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.2) Which state has launched e-Pathsala and e-Mulyankan facilities for school students?",
      a: "[a] Madhya Pradesh",
      b: "[b] Odisha",
      c: "[c] Andhra Pradesh",
      d: "[d] Karnataka",
      e: "[e] Kerala",
      answer: "[b] Odisha",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.3) With which Indian Institute of Management has Central Institute of Road Transport signed an MoU to build competencies and generate industry-oriented knowledge in transport management?",
      a: "[a] IIM- Pune",
      b: "[b] IIM- Ahmedabad",
      c: "[c] IIM- Bangalore",
      d: "[d] IIM- Nagpur",
      e: "[e] IIM- Indore",
      answer: "[d] IIM- Nagpur",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.4) Which of the following institution is the lead agency for Polar-Areas Stellar-Imaging in Polarisation High-Accuracy Experiment (PASIPHAE)?",
      a: "[a] University of Crete, Greece",
      b: "[b] Inter-University Centre for Astronomy and Astrophysics, India",
      c: "[c] Caltech, USA",
      d: "[d] South African Astronomical Observatory",
      e: "[e] Institute of Astrophysics, Greece",
      answer: "[e] Institute of Astrophysics, Greece",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.5) Which of the following is the only state from North-East India to feature in the Top 5 performers list of the NITI Aayog’s Sustainable Development Index 2021?",
      a: "[a] Sikkim",
      b: "[b] Arunachal Pradesh",
      c: "[c] Mizoram",
      d: "[d] Tripura",
      e: "[e] Nagaland",
      answer: "[a] Sikkim",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.6) What is India’s rank in the Global Peace Index in 2020 and 2021?",
      a: "[a] 55 and 79",
      b: "[b] 143 and 144",
      c: "[c] 179 and 180",
      d: "[d] 139 and 135",
      e: "[e] 121 and 117",
      answer: "[d] 139 and 135",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.7) What is India’s score in the Sustainable Development Report 2021 of Sustainable Development Solutions Network?",
      a: "[a] 60.1",
      b: "[b] 78.2",
      c: "[c] 80.5",
      d: "[d] 75.5",
      e: "[e] 52.2",
      answer: "[a] 60.1",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.8) Who among the following has become the youngest player to win the US Women’s Open 2021 Golf tournament?",
      a: "[a] Yuka Saso",
      b: "[b] Kristi Albers",
      c: "[c] Helen Alfredsson",
      d: "[d] Amy Alcott",
      e: "[e] Danielle Ammaccapane",
      answer: "[a] Yuka Saso",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.9) Who has been chosen as the President of Iran?",
      a: "[a] Mohammad Khatami",
      b: "[b] Hassan Rouhani",
      c: "[c] Mahmoud Ahmadinejad",
      d: "[d] Ebrahim Raisi",
      e: "[e] Ali Khamenei",
      answer: "[d] Ebrahim Raisi",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.10) Who has become the first private person in India to be appointed at the Councillor, Permanent Mission of India at World Trade Organisation (WTO), Geneva?",
      a: "[a] Premjeet Singh",
      b: "[b] Aashish Chandorkar",
      c: "[c] Rajat Pal",
      d: "[d] Sumit Verma",
      e: "[e] Sachin Vashisth",
      answer: "[b] Aashish Chandorkar",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.1) What is the name of the portal launched by Minister of Tribal Affairs as the Central Repository of all training programs conducted by Tribal Research Institutes (TRIs), different divisions of the Ministry, National Society for Education of Tribal Students (NESTS), Centre of Excellences funded by Ministry of Tribal Affairs and National Tribal Research Institute?",
      a: "[a] Adi Prashikshan",
      b: "[b] Adi Prekshak",
      c: "[c] Adi Prerna",
      d: "[d] Adi Parakh",
      e: "[e] Adi Pareeksha",
      answer: "[a] Adi Prashikshan",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.2) Which edition of the NATO Summit took place in Brussels recently?",
      a: "[a] 41st",
      b: "[b] 52nd",
      c: "[c] 23rd",
      d: "[d] 31st",
      e: "[e] 70th",
      answer: "[d] 31st",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.3) Which of the following is not a founding member of Non-Aligned Movement countries?",
      a: "[a] Indonesia",
      b: "[b] Yugoslavia",
      c: "[c] India",
      d: "[d] Egypt",
      e: "[e] Sri Lanka",
      answer: "[e] Sri Lanka",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.4) How many children are working at the e-waste dumpsites every year, as per WHO’s “Children and Digital Dumpsites” report?",
      a: "[a] 18 million",
      b: "[b] 23 million",
      c: "[c] 19 million",
      d: "[d] 33 million",
      e: "[e] 40 million",
      answer: "[a] 18 million",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.5) What is India’s rank in the “Government Efficiency” sub-index of IMD’s World Competitiveness Index 2021?",
      a: "[a] 32",
      b: "[b] 18",
      c: "[c] 46",
      d: "[d] 20",
      e: "[e] 54",
      answer: "[c] 46",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.6) How many industrial corridors are being developed in India under the National Industrial Corridor Program?",
      a: "[a] Five",
      b: "[b] Ten",
      c: "[c] Eleven",
      d: "[d] Nine",
      e: "[e] Seven",
      answer: "[c] Eleven",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.7) What is CII’s forecast for India’s GDP for FY22?",
      a: "[a] 9.5%",
      b: "[b] 10.5%",
      c: "[c] 8.8%",
      d: "[d] 11.2%",
      e: "[e] 13.5%",
      answer: "[a] 9.5%",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.8) What is NSO’s GDP forecast (contraction) for India for FY21?",
      a: "[a] 8.9%",
      b: "[b] 5.4%",
      c: "[c] 6.6%",
      d: "[d] 7.3%",
      e: "[e] 7.7%",
      answer: "[d] 7.3%",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.9) Who has been chosen as the SDG Pioneers 2021 from India by UNGC?",
      a: "[a] Rajni Sharma",
      b: "[b] Bibhuti Bhushana Dash",
      c: "[c] Ujjaval Srivastava",
      d: "[d] Sumant Sinha",
      e: "[e] Vinod Kumar",
      answer: "[d] Sumant Sinha",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.10) As per the Global Assessment Report on Drought 2021, impact of severe droughts on India’s GDP can be about ____ per cent per annum, despite decreasing contribution of agriculture in the country’s expanding economy?",
      a: "[a] 2-5%",
      b: "[b] 3-6%",
      c: "[c] 4-8%",
      d: "[d] 3-7%",
      e: "[e] 5-10%",
      answer: "[a] 2-5%",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.1) How many components are there in Deep Ocean Mission?",
      a: "[a] Six",
      b: "[b] Ten",
      c: "[c] Five",
      d: "[d] Four",
      e: "[e] Three",
      answer: "[a] Six",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.2) How many Van Dhan Vikas Kendras are expected to be established through the “Sankalp Se Siddhi – Mission Van Dhan”?",
      a: "[a] 50,000",
      b: "[b] 10,000",
      c: "[c] 20,000",
      d: "[d] 30,000",
      e: "[e] 15,000",
      answer: "[a] 50,000",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.3) Which of the following statement is untrue about the India Interagency Expert Committee (IEC) on Malaria and Climate?",
      a: "[a] It has been launched by IMD, ICMR, and Malaria No More",
      b: "[b] It will explore and advance climate-based solutions for accelerating the elimination of the vector-borne disease from the country",
      c: "[c] India aims to eliminate Malaria by 2030",
      d: "[d] IMD will be providing weather data for issuing malaria forecasts",
      e: "[e] The IEC will receive technical assistance from WHO",
      answer: "[e] The IEC will receive technical assistance from WHO",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.4) Which state has launched ‘Yuva Shakti Corona Mukti Abhiyan’ to create awareness about the COVID pandemic?",
      a: "[a] Chhattisgarh",
      b: "[b] Madhya Pradesh",
      c: "[c] Karnataka",
      d: "[d] Punjab",
      e: "[e] Himachal Pradesh",
      answer: "[b] Madhya Pradesh",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.5) The GI- certified Jalgaon bananas belong to which state?",
      a: "[a] Tamil Nadu",
      b: "[b] Kerala",
      c: "[c] Maharashtra",
      d: "[d] Punjab",
      e: "[e] Gujarat",
      answer: "[c] Maharashtra",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.6) Emirates Group Security and GMR Aviation Academy signed a Memorandum of Understanding to promote cooperation for the development and exchange of information, technical expertise, and experiences in aviation security. Which country does the Emirates Group Security belong to?",
      a: "[a] Saudi Arabia",
      b: "[b] Israel",
      c: "[c] Oman",
      d: "[d] Qatar",
      e: "[e] UAE",
      answer: "[e] UAE",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.7) Which country has received Line of Credit (LOC) worth USD 108.28 million from India for construction of its new Parliament building?",
      a: "[a] Eswatini",
      b: "[b] Somalia",
      c: "[c] Ghana",
      d: "[d] Albania",
      e: "[e] Namibia",
      answer: "[a] Eswatini",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.8) When is the ASEAN Dengue Day observed?",
      a: "[a] June 18",
      b: "[b] June 15",
      c: "[c] June 17",
      d: "[d] June 20",
      e: "[e] June 23",
      answer: "[b] June 15",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.9) Which country organized the ASEAN Regional Forum on Dengue on the occasion of ASEAN Dengue Day?",
      a: "[a] Vietnam",
      b: "[b] Thailand",
      c: "[c] Laos",
      d: "[d] Brunei",
      e: "[e] Philippines",
      answer: "[e] Philippines",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.10) When is the International Day of Family Remittances observed?",
      a: "[a] June 15",
      b: "[b] June 16",
      c: "[c] June 17",
      d: "[d] June 20",
      e: "[e] June 5",
      answer: "[b] June 16",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.1) Which state has received GI tag for Jardalu mangoes?",
      a: "[a] Bihar",
      b: "[b] Maharashtra",
      c: "[c] Andhra Pradesh",
      d: "[d] Kerala",
      e: "[e] Odisha",
      answer: "[a] Bihar",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.2) European Space Agency (ESA) has planned to launch the world’s first wooden satellite, WISA Woodsat, on Earth’s orbit by the end of 2021. The mission will test the applicability of wooden materials like plywood in spacecraft structures and expose it to extreme space conditions, such as heat, cold, vacuum and radiation, for an extended period of time. The satellite will be launched on a Rocket Lab Electron rocket from the Mahia Peninsula launch complex. In which country is the complex located?",
      a: "[a] Belgium",
      b: "[b] Netherlands",
      c: "[c] Luxembourg",
      d: "[d] New Zealand",
      e: "[e] Croatia",
      answer: "[d] New Zealand",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.3) Who will deliver the 17th Raúl Prebisch lecture at UN Trade Forum 2021?",
      a: "[a] Ragnar Frisch",
      b: "[b] Jan Tinbergen",
      c: "[c] Elinor Ostrom",
      d: "[d] Esther Duflo",
      e: "[e] Paul Milgrom",
      answer: "[d] Esther Duflo",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.4) Which company produces the Advanced Light Helicopters ALH Mk-III for Indian Armed Forces?",
      a: "[a] Bharat Electronics",
      b: "[b] Kalyani Group",
      c: "[c] Larsen & Toubro",
      d: "[d] Hindustan Aeronautics Ltd",
      e: "[e] Tata Group",
      answer: "[d] Hindustan Aeronautics Ltd",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.5) Who is the ambassador of Audi in India?",
      a: "[a] Virat Kohli",
      b: "[b] Akshay Kumar",
      c: "[c] Rishabh Pant",
      d: "[d] Shahrukh Khan",
      e: "[e] Shahid Kapoor",
      answer: "[a] Virat Kohli",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.6) Who is the Prime Minister of Israel?",
      a: "[a] Benjamin Netanyahu",
      b: "[b] Naftali Bennett",
      c: "[c] Peretz Naftali",
      d: "[d] Ayman Odeh",
      e: "[e] Shlomo Molla",
      answer: "[b] Naftali Bennett",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.7) When is the International Albinism Awareness Day observed?",
      a: "[a] June 13",
      b: "[b] June 19",
      c: "[c] June 15",
      d: "[d] June 20",
      e: "[e] June 8",
      answer: "[a] June 13",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.8) What is the slogan of World Blood Donor Day 2021?",
      a: "[a] Blood donation and universal access to safe blood transfusion",
      b: "[b] Safe blood saves lives",
      c: "[c] Be there for someone else. Give blood",
      d: "[d] Give blood. Give now. Give often",
      e: "[e] Give blood and keep the world beating",
      answer: "[e] Give blood and keep the world beating",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.9) Who is the winner of French Open 2021 women’s singles?",
      a: "[a] Barbora Krejčíková",
      b: "[b] Evonne Goolagong",
      c: "[c] Justine Henin",
      d: "[d] Venus Williams",
      e: "[e] Margaret Court",
      answer: "[a] Barbora Krejčíková",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.10) Tsitsi Dangarembga has won the PEN Pinter Prize 2021. Which country does she belong to?",
      a: "[a] Albania",
      b: "[b] Monaco",
      c: "[c] Croatia",
      d: "[d] Cyprus",
      e: "[e] Zimbabwe",
      answer: "[e] Zimbabwe",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.1) Which of the following organization is funding the India-Russia Joint Technology Assessment and Accelerated Commercialisation Programme from Russia’s side?",
      a: "[a] FASIE",
      b: "[b] Rostec",
      c: "[c] Sberbank of Russia",
      d: "[d] Gazprom",
      e: "[e] Transneft",
      answer: "[a] FASIE",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.2) Which of the following Indian Navy Ship has participated in the India-Thailand coordinated patrol?",
      a: "[a] INS Cheetah",
      b: "[b] INS Magar",
      c: "[c] INS Shardul",
      d: "[d] INS Gharial",
      e: "[e] INS Saryu",
      answer: "[e] INS Saryu",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.3) With which country’s Security and Defence Industry Association has Society of Indian Defence Manufacturers signed an MoU to promote and strengthen the bilateral defence industrial relations?",
      a: "[a] Germany",
      b: "[b] Denmark",
      c: "[c] Israel",
      d: "[d] Sweden",
      e: "[e] France",
      answer: "[d] Sweden",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.4) Which bank has launched a collateral-free loan scheme called the ‘KAVACH Personal Loan' for the families affected by COVID-19?",
      a: "[a] HDFC Bank",
      b: "[b] Axis Bank",
      c: "[c] ICICI Bank",
      d: "[d] SBI",
      e: "[e] Kotak Mahindra Bank",
      answer: "[d] SBI",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.5) Who has been appointed as the chair of the Grievance Redressal Board of the recently formed Digital Publisher Content Grievances Council by IAMAI?",
      a: "[a] Justice R. Subhash Reddy",
      b: "[b] Justice Ajay Rastogi",
      c: "[c] Justice Sanjiv Khanna",
      d: "[d] Justice Bhushan Ramkrishna Gavai",
      e: "[e] Justice Arjan Kumar Sikri",
      answer: "[e] Justice Arjan Kumar Sikri",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.6) What is the capital of Central Africa Republic?",
      a: "[a] Freetown",
      b: "[b] Mogadishu",
      c: "[c] Accra",
      d: "[d] Bangui",
      e: "[e] Windhoek",
      answer: "[d] Bangui",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.7) Who has won Pulitzer Prize 2021 in Fiction for The Night Watchman?",
      a: "[a] Louise Erdrich",
      b: "[b] Armando Lucas Correa",
      c: "[c] Megan Miranda",
      d: "[d] Haruki Murakami",
      e: "[e] Kiley Reid",
      answer: "[a] Louise Erdrich",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.8) With which steel PSU has Energy Efficiency Services Limited signed an MoU for implementation of various energy efficiency and resources conservation measures in the steel sector and associated mining industry?",
      a: "[a] NMDC Ltd.",
      b: "[b] KIOCL Ltd.",
      c: "[c] Rashtriya Ispat Nigam Ltd.",
      d: "[d] MECON Ltd",
      e: "[e] SAIL",
      answer: "[d] MECON Ltd",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.9) Who has been appointed as the new brand ambassador of Mylab Discovery Solutions?",
      a: "[a] Alia Bhatt",
      b: "[b] Akshay Kumar",
      c: "[c] Varun Dhawan",
      d: "[d] Hrithik Roshan",
      e: "[e] Deepika Padukone",
      answer: "[b] Akshay Kumar",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.10) Which Indian journalist has received the Pulitzer Prize 2021 for exposing China’s detention camps?",
      a: "[a] P. Haridasan Pilllai",
      b: "[b] Rajesh Kumar Sahu",
      c: "[c] R. K. Bhati",
      d: "[d] Surendra Prasad",
      e: "[e] Megha Rajagoplan",
      answer: "[e] Megha Rajagoplan",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.1) What is the venue of G7 Summit 2021?",
      a: "[a] Carbis Bay",
      b: "[b] Montebello",
      c: "[c] Halifax",
      d: "[d] Williamsburg",
      e: "[e] Denver",
      answer: "[a] Carbis Bay",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.2) How many times has PM Narendra Modi been invited to the G7 summits?",
      a: "[a] Five",
      b: "[b] Three",
      c: "[c] One",
      d: "[d] Two",
      e: "[e] Four",
      answer: "[d] Two",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.3) Which of the following statement is not true about the TRIPS agreement?",
      a: "[a] TRIPS is an international legal agreement between all the member nations of the World Trade Organization",
      b: "[b] TRIPS stands for Agreement on Trade-Related Aspects of Intellectual Property Rights",
      c: "[c] TRIPS came into being, along with WTO, in 1997.",
      d: "[d] In 2001, Doha Declaration on the TRIPS Agreement and Public Health was adopted",
      e: "[e] In 2005, India came into compliance of TRIPS agreement.",
      answer: "[c] TRIPS came into being, along with WTO, in 1997.",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.4) Which country will establish a centre to develop vaccines for prevention of zoonotic disease, spreading from animals to humans, under the Carbis Bay Declaration?",
      a: "[a] Canada",
      b: "[b] US",
      c: "[c] UK",
      d: "[d] France",
      e: "[e] Italy",
      answer: "[c] UK",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.5) How much debt of developing countries will be reduced by the Build Back Better World (B3W) initiative?",
      a: "[a] $40 trillion",
      b: "[b] $2 trillion",
      c: "[c] $10 trillion",
      d: "[d] $15 trillion",
      e: "[e] $20 trillion",
      answer: "[a] $40 trillion",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.6) Which country hosted the 1st summit of G7?",
      a: "[a] France",
      b: "[b] Germany",
      c: "[c] Japan",
      d: "[d] Italy",
      e: "[e] USA",
      answer: "[a] France",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.7) Which institute has produced a 10-episode series on various aspects of Common Yoga Protocol which would be telecast on DD India at 7 pm from today till the 21st of this month?",
      a: "[a] Indian Institute Of Yoga And Naturopathy",
      b: "[b] Central Council for Research in Yoga & Naturopathy",
      c: "[c] The Yoga Institute Delhi",
      d: "[d] Morarji Desai National Institute of Yoga",
      e: "[e] All India Naturopathy and Yoga Education Council",
      answer: "[d] Morarji Desai National Institute of Yoga",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.8) Indian Coast Guard has been conducting “Operation Olivia”, every year since the early 1980s, to protect Olive Ridley turtles as they congregate along the ___ coast?",
      a: "[a] Karnataka",
      b: "[b] Kerala",
      c: "[c] Odisha",
      d: "[d] Tamil Nadu",
      e: "[e] Maharashtra",
      answer: "[c] Odisha",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.9) Which of the following is the proposed mission of European Space Agency for Venus?",
      a: "[a] Venus Express",
      b: "[b] Cassini",
      c: "[c] Akatsuki",
      d: "[d] EnVision",
      e: "[e] Venera",
      answer: "[d] EnVision",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.10) What is the theme of World Day Against Child Labour 2021?",
      a: "[a] Protect children from child labour, now more than ever",
      b: "[b] Act Now: End Child Labour",
      c: "[c] Children shouldn't work in fields, but on dreams",
      d: "[d] Generation Safe & Healthy",
      e: "[e] End child labour in supply chains – It's everyone's business!",
      answer: "[b] Act Now: End Child Labour",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.1) With which state has Flipkart partnered for ‘Medicines from the Sky’ project to deliver medicines by using drones to remote areas of state?",
      a: "[a] Telangana",
      b: "[b] Maharashtra",
      c: "[c] Madhya Pradesh",
      d: "[d] Kerala",
      e: "[e] Karnataka",
      answer: "[a] Telangana",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.2) How much increment was seen in the exports of organic products in 2020-21, as per the data of Ministry of Commerce?",
      a: "[a] 40%",
      b: "[b] 60%",
      c: "[c] 25%",
      d: "[d] 51%",
      e: "[e] 30%",
      answer: "[d] 51%",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.3) With which country has India signed an MoU to bring Indian domestic workers in the country within the ambit of a legal framework that streamlines their recruitment and provides them with the protection of the law?",
      a: "[a] Bahrain",
      b: "[b] Kuwait",
      c: "[c] Oman",
      d: "[d] Qatar",
      e: "[e] Saudi Arabia",
      answer: "[b] Kuwait",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.4) What is India’s rank in the Global House Price Index - Q1 2021 report of Knight Frank?",
      a: "[a] 60th",
      b: "[b] 88th",
      c: "[c] 35th",
      d: "[d] 55th",
      e: "[e] 20th",
      answer: "[d] 55th",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.5) How much wind capacity will be added by 2025 as per the “India Wind Energy Market Outlook 2025”?",
      a: "[a] 10 GW",
      b: "[b] 30 GW",
      c: "[c] 5.2 GW",
      d: "[d] 20 GW",
      e: "[e] 2.3 GW",
      answer: "[d] 20 GW",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.6) Google has announced to develop an open subsea cable to provide robust internet connectivity between US, Brazil, ___ and ___?",
      a: "[a] Uruguay",
      b: "[b] Argentina",
      c: "[c] Costa Rica",
      d: "[d] Both A and B",
      e: "[e] Both B and C",
      answer: "[d] Both A and B",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.7) Who has become the first woman to be appointed secretary-general of the United Nations Conference on Trade and Development?",
      a: "[a] Rebeca Grynspan",
      b: "[b] Betty Boothroy",
      c: "[c] Gwyneth Dunwoody",
      d: "[d] Doris Fisher",
      e: "[e] Peggy Fenner",
      answer: "[a] Rebeca Grynspan",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.8) Who is the chairperson of North-Eastern Council?",
      a: "[a] Secretary of Home Affairs",
      b: "[b] Union Minister of Home Affairs",
      c: "[c] Secretary of Ministry of Development of North Eastern Region",
      d: "[d] Union Minister of Ministry of Development of North Eastern Region",
      e: "[e] Secretary of Union Cabinet",
      answer: "[b] Union Minister of Home Affairs",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.9) When was UNCTAD established?",
      a: "[a] 1964",
      b: "[b] 1988",
      c: "[c] 2001",
      d: "[d] 2004",
      e: "[e] 1956",
      answer: "[a] 1964",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.10) Which of the following UN organ is not situated in New York?",
      a: "[a] Trusteeship Council",
      b: "[b] International Court of Justice",
      c: "[c] UN Economic and Social Council",
      d: "[d] Both A and B",
      e: "[e] Both B and C",
      answer: "[b] International Court of Justice",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.1) Which of the following is not a member of Confederation of Hospitality, Technology and Tourism Industry?",
      a: "[a] Oyo",
      b: "[b] Yatra",
      c: "[c] Airbnb",
      d: "[d] EaseMyTrip",
      e: "[e] MakeMyTrip",
      answer: "[e] MakeMyTrip",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.2) Which IIT has developed Early Cyclone Detection Technique for early detection of development or strengthening of tropical cyclones in the North Indian Ocean region?",
      a: "[a] IIT-Kanpur",
      b: "[b] IIT-Bombay",
      c: "[c] IIT-Delhi",
      d: "[d] IIT-Kharagpur",
      e: "[e] IIT-Madras",
      answer: "[d] IIT-Kharagpur",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.3) Which has become the first country in the world to adopt bitcoin as the legal tender?",
      a: "[a] Brazil",
      b: "[b] Mexico",
      c: "[c] El Salvador",
      d: "[d] Colombia",
      e: "[e] Puerto Rico",
      answer: "[c] El Salvador",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.4) How many children are into child labour at present, according to the “Child Labour: Global estimates 2020, trends and the road forward” report of ILO and UNICEF?",
      a: "[a] 110 million",
      b: "[b] 160 million",
      c: "[c] 230 million",
      d: "[d] 80 million",
      e: "[e] 70 million",
      answer: "[b] 160 million",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.5) Climate change would increase the poverty in India by __ percent in 2040, as per the ‘The Costs of Climate Change in India’ report?",
      a: "[a] 3.5%",
      b: "[b] 4.4%",
      c: "[c] 2.7%",
      d: "[d] 5.4%",
      e: "[e] 6.3%",
      answer: "[a] 3.5%",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.1) Which company has created the DNA matching software in Interpol’s ‘I-Familia’ global database?",
      a: "[a] Mellanox",
      b: "[b] Aladdin Knowledge Systems",
      c: "[c] NICE Systems",
      d: "[d] Smart Research",
      e: "[e] Tadiran Telecom",
      answer: "[d] Smart Research",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.2) Which of the following countries has been elected to the UN Economic and Social Council for the 2022-24 term, in the Asia-Pacific category, along with India?",
      a: "[a] Afghanistan",
      b: "[b] Oman",
      c: "[c] Kazakhstan",
      d: "[d] Only A and B",
      e: "[e] All of the Above",
      answer: "[e] All of the Above",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.3) As per the new tax pact agreed by G7 for taxing multinational companies, the minimum corporate tax threshold should be at least __ per cent?",
      a: "[a] 15%",
      b: "[b] 20%",
      c: "[c] 25%",
      d: "[d] 10%",
      e: "[e] 12%",
      answer: "[a] 15%",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.4) Which company has announced to develop world’s first carbon-neutral cement plant?",
      a: "[a] LafargeHolcim",
      b: "[b] Anhui Conch",
      c: "[c] Heidelberg Cement",
      d: "[d] Cemex",
      e: "[e] Italcementi",
      answer: "[c] Heidelberg Cement",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.5) Who has been appointed as the CEO of HSBC Bank India?",
      a: "[a] Anand Mohan Bajaj",
      b: "[b] Hitendra Dave",
      c: "[c] Sunita Sharma",
      d: "[d] N. Srinivasan",
      e: "[e] Baldeo Purushartha",
      answer: "[b] Hitendra Dave",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.1) Which is the expense sharing ratio between centre and state in the Seed Minikit Program respectively?",
      a: "[a] 60:40",
      b: "[b] 70:30",
      c: "[c] 20:80",
      d: "[d] 100:0",
      e: "[e] 50:50",
      answer: "[d] 100:0",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.2) What is the total food grain production estimate for 2020-21 as per the 3rd Advance Estimate of Principal Crops for 2020-21?",
      a: "[a] 277.20 million tonnes",
      b: "[b] 560.18 million tonnes",
      c: "[c] 333.89 million tonnes",
      d: "[d] 305.44 million tonnes",
      e: "[e] 102.29 million tonnes",
      answer: "[d] 305.44 million tonnes",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.3) How many total indicators were used in the Performance Grading Index (PGI) 2019-20?",
      a: "[a] 70",
      b: "[b] 100",
      c: "[c] 40",
      d: "[d] 25",
      e: "[e] 10",
      answer: "[a] 70",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.4) What is India’s rank in the State of India’s Environment Report 2021 of CSE?",
      a: "[a] 117",
      b: "[b] 58",
      c: "[c] 103",
      d: "[d] 166",
      e: "[e] 120",
      answer: "[a] 117",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.5) Who has been appointed as the President of FINA?",
      a: "[a] Husain Al Musallam",
      b: "[b] Sam Ramsamy",
      c: "[c] Daichi Suzuki",
      d: "[d] Algernon Cargill",
      e: "[e] Veronica Stanham",
      answer: "[a] Husain Al Musallam",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.1) How much assistance will be provided to the selected start-ups under the SAGE (Senior-care Aging Growth Engine) initiative of the govt?",
      a: "[a] Rs 1 crore",
      b: "[b] Rs 50 lakhs",
      c: "[c] Rs 2 crore",
      d: "[d] Rs 10 lakhs",
      e: "[e] Rs 90 lakhs",
      answer: "[a] Rs 1 crore",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.2) Recently, Indian Navy has decommissioned ‘INS Sandhayak’, after 40 years of service, at Naval Dockyard in Visakhapatnam. What kind of ship INS Sandhayak is?",
      a: "[a] Container Ships",
      b: "[b] Offshore Ships",
      c: "[c] Tanker Ships",
      d: "[d] Bulk Carrier",
      e: "[e] Hydrographic Survey Ship",
      answer: "[e] Hydrographic Survey Ship",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.3) Who is the MD and CEO of RBL Bank?",
      a: "[a] Vijoy Kumar Singh",
      b: "[b] Shashi Ranjan Kumar",
      c: "[c] Nihar Ranjan Dash",
      d: "[d] Vishwavir Ahuja",
      e: "[e] Sanjay Sharan",
      answer: "[d] Vishwavir Ahuja",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.4) Who has been elected to the board of the International Dairy Federation (IDF) from India?",
      a: "[a] RS Sodhi",
      b: "[b] Jogiranjan Panigrahi",
      c: "[c] Gaurav Kumar",
      d: "[d] Jenny Kiloung",
      e: "[e] Dipankar Dutta",
      answer: "[a] RS Sodhi",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.5) Which country is the global host of World Environment Day 2021?",
      a: "[a] Spain",
      b: "[b] India",
      c: "[c] Pakistan",
      d: "[d] Nepal",
      e: "[e] Vietnam",
      answer: "[c] Pakistan",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.1) How much financial assistance is provided to the patients under the Rashtriya Aarogya Nidhi for medical treatment at Government hospitals?",
      a: "[a] Rs 20 lakhs",
      b: "[b] Rs 15 lakhs",
      c: "[c] Rs 10 lakhs",
      d: "[d] Rs 25 lakhs",
      e: "[e] Rs 30 lakhs",
      answer: "[b] Rs 15 lakhs",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.2) When was the Central Govt Health Scheme launched?",
      a: "[a] 1983",
      b: "[b] 1999",
      c: "[c] 1954",
      d: "[d] 2001",
      e: "[e] 1993",
      answer: "[c] 1954",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.3) Which state has announced the creation of Special Purpose Vehicle (SPV) to ensure supply of potable water on a long term sustainable basis in rural areas of water quality affected districts?",
      a: "[a] Punjab",
      b: "[b] Maharashtra",
      c: "[c] Gujarat",
      d: "[d] Andhra Pradesh",
      e: "[e] Kerala",
      answer: "[a] Punjab",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.4) Which company has received a contract from Ministry of Defence for 11 airport surveillance radars for the Indian Navy and the Indian Coast Guard?",
      a: "[a] Hindustan Aeronautics Ltd.",
      b: "[b] Bharat Electronics Ltd",
      c: "[c] Mahindra Telephonics",
      d: "[d] Apollo Micro Systems",
      e: "[e] Astra Microwave Products",
      answer: "[c] Mahindra Telephonics",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.5) What is the Global unemployment rate forecast for 2021 by “World Employment and Social Outlook: Trends 2021” report of ILO?",
      a: "[a] 6.3%",
      b: "[b] 5.4%",
      c: "[c] 7.7%",
      d: "[d] 2.3%",
      e: "[e] 4.5%",
      answer: "[a] 6.3%",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.6) How much investment is being put in the nature-based solutions worldwide at present, as per the State of Finance for Nature report?",
      a: "[a] $145 billion",
      b: "[b] $180 billion",
      c: "[c] $170 billion",
      d: "[d] $133 billion",
      e: "[e] $203 billion",
      answer: "[d] $133 billion",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.7) Who heads the Expert Committee on Variable Capital Company set up by IFSCA to explore the potential for allowing variable capital company (VCC) to operate in the IFSCA?",
      a: "[a] Nihar Ranjan Dash",
      b: "[b] Sanjay Sharan",
      c: "[c] Dipankar Dutta",
      d: "[d] Kumar Padmapani Bora",
      e: "[e] K.P. Krishnan",
      answer: "[e] K.P. Krishnan",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.8) Which of the following statement is incorrect with respect to Rural Infrastructure Development Fund?",
      a: "[a] Government of India created the RIDF in NABARD in 1995-96, with an initial corpus of Rs.2,000 crore",
      b: "[b] There are 37 eligible activities under RIDF. The eligible activities are classified under four broad categories",
      c: "[c] The interest rates payable to banks on deposits placed with NABARD and loans disbursed by NABARD from RIDF have been linked to the Bank Rate",
      d: "[d] RIDF Loan is to be repaid in equal annual instalments within seven years from the date of withdrawal, including a grace period of two years",
      e: "[e] The implementation phase for projects sanctioned is spread over 2-5 years, varying with type of the project and also location of the State",
      answer:
        "[b] There are 37 eligible activities under RIDF. The eligible activities are classified under four broad categories",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.9) What is the corpus of on-tap liquidity set up by RBI for contact intensive sectors at repo rate?",
      a: "[a] Rs 10,000 crore",
      b: "[b] Rs 15,000 crore",
      c: "[c] Rs 25,000 crore",
      d: "[d] Rs 30,000 crore",
      e: "[e] Rs 40,000 crore",
      answer: "[b] Rs 15,000 crore",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.10) When is the International Day of Innocent Children Victims of Aggression observed?",
      a: "[a] June 4",
      b: "[b] June 20",
      c: "[c] June 6",
      d: "[d] June 15",
      e: "[e] June 10",
      answer: "[a] June 4",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.1) On which committee’s recommendation was the Financial Stability and Development Council created?",
      a: "[a] Y M Deosthalee Committee",
      b: "[b] Raghuram Rajan committee",
      c: "[c] U.C. Banerjee Commission",
      d: "[d] Thakkar Commission",
      e: "[e] Srikrishna Commission",
      answer: "[b] Raghuram Rajan committee",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.2) Who heads the expert group formed by Ministry of Labour and Employment to provide technical inputs and recommendations on fixation of minimum wages and national floor minimum wages?",
      a: "[a] Rahul Jain",
      b: "[b] Shoeb Samad",
      c: "[c] Arun Srivastava",
      d: "[d] Ajit Mishra",
      e: "[e] Sanjay Singh",
      answer: "[d] Ajit Mishra",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.3) Who is the convenor of 8 member group of ministers of the Goods and Services Tax (GST) Council?",
      a: "[a] Pankaj Kumar Devrani",
      b: "[b] Subrata Halder",
      c: "[c] R. N. Bharti",
      d: "[d] Conrad Sangma",
      e: "[e] Shyam Sundar Verma",
      answer: "[d] Conrad Sangma",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.4) Which country has launched Fengyun-4B weather satellite?",
      a: "[a] Japan",
      b: "[b] France",
      c: "[c] Republic of Korea",
      d: "[d] China",
      e: "[e] Saudi Arabia",
      answer: "[d] China",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.5) Davinci+ and Veritas are the planned mission of NASA to which planet?",
      a: "[a] Venus",
      b: "[b] Neptune",
      c: "[c] Saturn",
      d: "[d] Jupiter",
      e: "[e] Mars",
      answer: "[a] Venus",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.6) Who has been appointed as Chair of WHO Executive Board 2021-22?",
      a: "[a] Charles Michel",
      b: "[b] Alexander De Croo",
      c: "[c] Andrej Plenković Croatia",
      d: "[d] Patrick Amoth",
      e: "[e] Sebastian Kurz",
      answer: "[d] Patrick Amoth",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.7) Who has won the International Booker Prize 2021?",
      a: "[a] Mette Frederiksen",
      b: "[b] Rumen Radev",
      c: "[c] David Diop",
      d: "[d] Alexander De Croo",
      e: "[e] Mario Draghi",
      answer: "[c] David Diop",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.1) Which IIT has developed a first-of-its-kind Internet of Things (IoT) device – AmbiTag?",
      a: "[a] IIT-Delhi",
      b: "[b] IIT-Ropar",
      c: "[c] IIT-Kharagpur",
      d: "[d] IIT-Roorkie",
      e: "[e] IIT-Hyderabad",
      answer: "[b] IIT-Ropar",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.2) With which airline company has J&K UT govt signed an MoU for the transportation of perishable horticulture and agricultural produce to various destinations across the country?",
      a: "[a] Daman & Diu and Dadra & Haveli",
      b: "[b] Puducherry",
      c: "[c] Andaman and Nicobar",
      d: "[d] Delhi",
      e: "[e] Jammu and Kashmir",
      answer: "[e] Jammu and Kashmir",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.3) Who has become the first Indian to be elected as the president of the International Narcotics Control Board?",
      a: "[a] Jagjit Pavadia",
      b: "[b] Nivedita Pandey",
      c: "[c] Kirti Sharma",
      d: "[d] Akansha Singh",
      e: "[e] Purvi Chandela",
      answer: "[a] Jagjit Pavadia",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.4) Who has won the men’s singles at the 2021 Emilia-Romagna Open (Tennis) held in Italy?",
      a: "[a] Rafael Nadal",
      b: "[b] Novak Djokovic",
      c: "[c] Sebastian Korda",
      d: "[d] Andre Agassi",
      e: "[e] Andy Murray",
      answer: "[c] Sebastian Korda",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.5) Who is the author of “All Roads Lead North: Nepal's Turn to China”?",
      a: "[a] Jay Karan Singh",
      b: "[b] Shakuntla",
      c: "[c] Amish Raj Mulmi",
      d: "[d] Gaurav Kumar",
      e: "[e] Hemant kumar Nanda",
      answer: "[c] Amish Raj Mulmi",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.1) Which of the following statement is not true about PM CARES for Children scheme?",
      a: "[a] PM CARES will contribute through a specially designed scheme to create a corpus of Rs 10 lakh for each child when he or she reaches 18 years of age",
      b: "[b] The child will be given admission in any Central Government residential school such as Sainik School, Navodaya Vidyalaya etc.",
      c: "[c] If the child is admitted in a private school, the fees as per the RTE norms will be given from the PM CARES",
      d: "[d] All children will be enrolled as a beneficiary under Ayushman Bharat Scheme (PM-JAY) with a health insurance cover of Rs. 5 lakhs.",
      e: "[e] None of the Above",
      answer: "[e] None of the Above",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.2) What is the GDP forecast for India for FY22?",
      a: "[a] 8.9%",
      b: "[b] 6.7%",
      c: "[c] 4.5%",
      d: "[d] 9.9%",
      e: "[e] 10.2%",
      answer: "[d] 9.9%",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.3) Who has been appointed as the interim chief of the Central Board of Direct Taxes?",
      a: "[a] Sadanand",
      b: "[b] Agam Mittal",
      c: "[c] V.D Jaswani",
      d: "[d] J.B. Mohapatra",
      e: "[e] Vikash Sheel",
      answer: "[d] J.B. Mohapatra",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.4) Who is the President of CII for 2021-22?",
      a: "[a] Rakesh Kumar",
      b: "[b] Manohar Agnani",
      c: "[c] T V Narendran",
      d: "[d] B.Shobha",
      e: "[e] Harish Lugani",
      answer: "[c] T V Narendran",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.5) How many defence goods will be indigenously produced in India by 2025 as per the 2nd list of Defence Indigenization Goods?",
      a: "[a] 141",
      b: "[b] 150",
      c: "[c] 108",
      d: "[d] 123",
      e: "[e] 167",
      answer: "[c] 108",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.1) What is the name of the online tracking portal launched by National Commission for Protection of Child Rights for children in need of care and protection?",
      a: "[a] Bal Swaraj",
      b: "[b] Bal Suraksha",
      c: "[c] Bal Abhiyan",
      d: "[d] Bal Vikas",
      e: "[e] Bal Protsahan",
      answer: "[a] Bal Swaraj",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.2) Who heads the Empowered Group on Vaccination formed by Central Govt?",
      a: "[a] Amitabh Kant",
      b: "[b] Ajay Seth",
      c: "[c] VK Paul",
      d: "[d] Amit Khare",
      e: "[e] Balram Bhargava",
      answer: "[c] VK Paul",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.3) Which state has launched Udaan scheme to provide free sanitary napkins to needy girls and women across the state?",
      a: "[a] Punjab",
      b: "[b] Maharashtra",
      c: "[c] Gujarat",
      d: "[d] West Bengal",
      e: "[e] Karnataka",
      answer: "[a] Punjab",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.4) National Security Advisor (NSA) Ajit Doval has commissioned the Indian Coast Guard (ICG) Offshore Patrol Vessel (OPV) Sajag, which has been constructed by Goa Shipyard Limited. Sajag is the ___ in a series of five offshore patrol vessels indigenously designed by GSL?",
      a: "[a] first",
      b: "[b] fifth",
      c: "[c] fourth",
      d: "[d] third",
      e: "[e] second",
      answer: "[d] third",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.5) Who has been elected as the Asia-Oceania representative at the 2021 International Association of Ultrarunners (IAU) Congress?",
      a: "[a] Radha Venkatesan",
      b: "[b] Nagraj Adiga",
      c: "[c] D. K. OJHA",
      d: "[d] Charan Jeet Singh Nirman",
      e: "[e] Nivedita Gupta",
      answer: "[b] Nagraj Adiga",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.) Who has won the International Dublin Literary Award 2021 for 'Lost Children Archive' novel?",
      a: "[a] Valeria Luiselli",
      b: "[b] Hilary Mantel",
      c: "[c] Eleanor Catton",
      d: "[d] Howard Jacobson",
      e: "[e] Aravind Adiga",
      answer: "[a] Valeria Luiselli",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.2) Which IIT has developed the unique detector named ‘FakeBuster’, along with Australia based Monash University, to detect imposters attending a virtual conference without anybody’s knowledge?",
      a: "[a] IIT-Bombay",
      b: "[b] IIT-Madras",
      c: "[c] IIT-Delhi",
      d: "[d] IIT-Kharagpur",
      e: "[e] IIT-Ropar",
      answer: "[e] IIT-Ropar",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.3) Which of the following organizations collaborated to develop world’s first satellite-based monitoring system for coral reefs?",
      a: "[a] Arizona State University",
      b: "[b] National Geographic Society",
      c: "[c] Vulcan",
      d: "[d] University of Queensland",
      e: "[e] All of the Above",
      answer: "[e] All of the Above",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.4) Which company has developed “first of its kind” crypto lending model in India?",
      a: "[a] Binance India",
      b: "[b] WazirX",
      c: "[c] Coinbase",
      d: "[d] ZebPay",
      e: "[e] Bitfinex",
      answer: "[d] ZebPay",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.5) When is the International Day of UN Peacekeepers observed?",
      a: "[a] May 29",
      b: "[b] October 10",
      c: "[c] August 13",
      d: "[d] June 14",
      e: "[e] July 17",
      answer: "[a] May 29",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.1) Which IIM has partnered with German companies - GIZ and BMZ - to identify the challenges caused by Covid-19 pandemic across various sectors and find measures for them?",
      a: "[a] IIM-Calcutta",
      b: "[b] IIM-Ahmedabad",
      c: "[c] IIM-Bangalore",
      d: "[d] IIM-Lucknow",
      e: "[e] IIM-Indore",
      answer: "[e] IIM-Indore",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.2) Which of the following organization is getting support from the Department of Biotechnology under Mission Covid Suraksha for developing Covid vaccine?",
      a: "[a] Haffkine Biopharmaceutical Corporation",
      b: "[b] Bharat biotech International Ltd",
      c: "[c] Biological E.",
      d: "[d] Biomed Pvt. Ltd",
      e: "[e] Cadila healthcare",
      answer: "[a] Haffkine Biopharmaceutical Corporation",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.3) Which state has launched an online portal named “Akansha” to provide details of all the Corporate Social Responsibility projects or activities, being carried out, in the state?",
      a: "[a] Uttar Pradesh",
      b: "[b] Bihar",
      c: "[c] Uttarakhand",
      d: "[d] Himachal Pradesh",
      e: "[e] Karnataka",
      answer: "[e] Karnataka",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.4) Which state has launched Ankur scheme to reward citizens for planting trees during monsoon?",
      a: "[a] Madhya Pradesh",
      b: "[b] Arunachal Pradesh",
      c: "[c] Odisha",
      d: "[d] Telangana",
      e: "[e] West Bengal",
      answer: "[a] Madhya Pradesh",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.5) Which state / UT has launched the Special Assistance Scheme for Covid Mortalities (SASCM) scheme for providing financial assistance to families, who lost their only bread earner to the Coronavirus pandemic?",
      a: "[a] Ladakh",
      b: "[b] Delhi",
      c: "[c] Lakshadweep",
      d: "[d] Jammu & Kashmir",
      e: "[e] Andaman and Nicobar",
      answer: "[d] Jammu & Kashmir",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.6) National Technology Centre for Ports Waterways and Coasts - the technology arm of the Ministry of Ports, Shipping and Waterways – is located at which IIT?",
      a: "[a] IIT-Kanpur",
      b: "[b] IIT-Delhi",
      c: "[c] IIT-Madras",
      d: "[d] IIT-Bombay",
      e: "[e] IIT-Kharagpur",
      answer: "[c] IIT-Madras",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.7) Which country’s Met Office has partnered World Meteorological Organization for releasing the Global Annual to Decadal Climate Update?",
      a: "[a] UK",
      b: "[b] Germany",
      c: "[c] Sweden",
      d: "[d] Norway",
      e: "[e] Netherland",
      answer: "[a] UK",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.8) Which team won the UEFA Women’s Champions League 2021?",
      a: "[a] Arsenal",
      b: "[b] Barcelona FC",
      c: "[c] Manchester City",
      d: "[d] Birmingham City",
      e: "[e] Tottenham Hotspur",
      answer: "[b] Barcelona FC",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.9) Who among the following is known as the China's 'father of hybrid rice'?",
      a: "[a] Ba Denian",
      b: "[b] Cai Xitao",
      c: "[c] Chang Chi-yun",
      d: "[d] T. T. Chang",
      e: "[e] Yuan Longping",
      answer: "[e] Yuan Longping",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.10) Who is the author of “India and Asian Geopolitics: The Past, Present” book?",
      a: "[a] Amar Pal",
      b: "[b] Shivshankar Menon",
      c: "[c] Kimjamlhing Changloi",
      d: "[d] Sharad Saxena",
      e: "[e] K R Shyam Babu",
      answer: "[b] Shivshankar Menon",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.1) When was One-Stop Centres (OSC) — Sakhi – scheme launched?",
      a: "[a] 2013",
      b: "[b] 2015",
      c: "[c] 2009",
      d: "[d] 2011",
      e: "[e] 2016",
      answer: "[b] 2015",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.2) Where is India's first city-wide environmental surveillance platform for COVID -‘Precision Health Platform’ - launched?",
      a: "[a] Ajmer",
      b: "[b] Agra",
      c: "[c] Bengaluru",
      d: "[d] Guwahati",
      e: "[e] Imphal",
      answer: "[c] Bengaluru",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.3) NASA is planning to send its first mobile robot named Volatiles Investigating Polar Exploration Rover (VIPER) to which planet?",
      a: "[a] Solar",
      b: "[b] Lunar",
      c: "[c] Jupiter",
      d: "[d] Neptune",
      e: "[e] Venus",
      answer: "[b] Lunar",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.4) Who has become the first-ever Indian medical practitioner to receive the Rudolf V. Schindler Award from the American Society of Gastrointestinal Endoscopy?",
      a: "[a] D Nageshwar Reddy",
      b: "[b] Uttank Joshi",
      c: "[c] P. Rangarajan",
      d: "[d] Bharti Kashyap Sharma",
      e: "[e] Rajesh Talwar",
      answer: "[a] D Nageshwar Reddy",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.5) Who has won the 13th International Eni Award 2020 from India?",
      a: "[a] C.N.R. Rao",
      b: "[b] Tuntuni Chowdhry",
      c: "[c] R. K. Bhati",
      d: "[d] Bidisha Sengupta",
      e: "[e] Pranav Prakash",
      answer: "[a] C.N.R. Rao",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.1) Who is the President of Indian Broadcasting Foundation?",
      a: "[a] R. K. Dhawan",
      b: "[b] Sanjay Pandey",
      c: "[c] Anita Baghel",
      d: "[d] K Madhavan",
      e: "[e] Gyan Bhushan",
      answer: "[d] K Madhavan",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.2) How much financial assistance will be provided to the authors selected under the YUVA scheme for six months?",
      a: "[a] Rs 15,000 per month",
      b: "[b] Rs 20,000 per month",
      c: "[c] Rs 50,000 per month",
      d: "[d] Rs 30,000 per month",
      e: "[e] Rs 40,000 per month",
      answer: "[c] Rs 50,000 per month",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.3) Who is the convener of the 7- member Panel of State Ministers set up by GOI for better valuation of services of casinos, online gaming portal and race courses for levying Goods and Services Tax?",
      a: "[a] Madan Lal",
      b: "[b] Fakhre Alam",
      c: "[c] Bibhuti Bhushana Dash",
      d: "[d] Nitin Patel",
      e: "[e] Santosh Shilpokar",
      answer: "[d] Nitin Patel",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.4) How much GST is levied on services of casinos, horse racing and online gaming at present?",
      a: "[a] 18%",
      b: "[b] 12%",
      c: "[c] 5%",
      d: "[d] 28%",
      e: "[e] 20%",
      answer: "[a] 18%",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.5) Who has recorded the world’s fastest ascent of Everest by a woman with a time of just 25 hours and 50 minutes?",
      a: "[a] Tsang Yin-hung",
      b: "[b] Melissa Arnot",
      c: "[c] Junko Tabei",
      d: "[d] Pasang Lhamu Sherpa",
      e: "[e] Lydia Bradey",
      answer: "[a] Tsang Yin-hung",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.6) What is the name of the exercise conducted by NATO members across the Atlantic, through Europe and into the Black Sea region?",
      a: "[a] Mainbrace- 21",
      b: "[b] Steadfast Defender 21",
      c: "[c] Grand Repulse 21",
      d: "[d] Italic Weld 21",
      e: "[e] Longstep 21",
      answer: "[b] Steadfast Defender 21",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.7) How much amount is RBI transferring to the Central Government for 2020-21, as per its Annual Report for 2020-21?",
      a: "[a] Rs 57,000 crores",
      b: "[b] Rs. 99,122 crores",
      c: "[c] Rs 80,000 crores",
      d: "[d] Rs 60,190 crores",
      e: "[e] Rs 45,150 crores",
      answer: "[b] Rs. 99,122 crores",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.8) Bashar Al-Assad has sworn in as the President of which country?",
      a: "[a] South Africa",
      b: "[b] Syria",
      c: "[c] Oman",
      d: "[d] Kenya",
      e: "[e] Morocco",
      answer: "[b] Syria",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.9) Which section of RBI Act, 1934 allows the transfer of surplus RBI funds to the Central Govt?",
      a: "[a] Section 47",
      b: "[b] Section 75",
      c: "[c] Section 90",
      d: "[d] Section 30",
      e: "[e] Section 55",
      answer: "[a] Section 47",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.10) What is the capital of Syria?",
      a: "[a] Damascus",
      b: "[b] Nairobi",
      c: "[c] Accra",
      d: "[d] Dodoma",
      e: "[e] Kinshasa",
      answer: "[a] Damascus",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.1) Which is the first Indian state to join the global COVAX alliance for sourcing the immunisation shots at the best price?",
      a: "[a] Telangana",
      b: "[b] Tamil Nadu",
      c: "[c] Punjab",
      d: "[d] Maharashtra",
      e: "[e] Gujarat",
      answer: "[c] Punjab",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.2) Which state has launched “Swasthya Aahar Yojana” for providing healthy food to the covid-19 patients?",
      a: "[a] Madhya Pradesh",
      b: "[b] Karnataka",
      c: "[c] Kerala",
      d: "[d] Assam",
      e: "[e] Uttarakhand",
      answer: "[a] Madhya Pradesh",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.3) Who has created a world record by scaling Mount Everest twice in the just 4 days?",
      a: "[a] Junko Tabei",
      b: "[b] Nawang Gombu",
      c: "[c] Lhakpa Sherpa",
      d: "[d] Mingma Tenji Sherpa",
      e: "[e] Sungdare Sherpa",
      answer: "[d] Mingma Tenji Sherpa",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.4) When was the Special Window for Affordable and Mid-Income Housing (SWAMIH) Fund scheme launched?",
      a: "[a] 2018",
      b: "[b] 2019",
      c: "[c] 2020",
      d: "[d] 2017",
      e: "[e] 2016",
      answer: "[b] 2019",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.5) Which of the following company has acquired Indiabulls Asset Management Company Ltd and Indiabulls Trustee Company Ltd?",
      a: "[a] Nextbillion Technology Pvt. Ltd",
      b: "[b] HCL Infosystems",
      c: "[c] CK Birla Group",
      d: "[d] Intex Technologies",
      e: "[e] Iris Computers",
      answer: "[a] Nextbillion Technology Pvt. Ltd",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.6) Which football club has won the Premier League 2020-21 (football)?",
      a: "[a] Arsenal",
      b: "[b] Manchester City",
      c: "[c] Bayern München",
      d: "[d] Manchester United",
      e: "[e] Paris Saint-Germain",
      answer: "[b] Manchester City",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.7) With which field Roman Khassanov related to?",
      a: "[a] Archery",
      b: "[b] Badminton",
      c: "[c] Volleyball",
      d: "[d] Tennis",
      e: "[e] Baseball",
      answer: "[d] Tennis",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.8) What is the corpus of SWAMIH Fund?",
      a: "[a] Rs 50,000 crores",
      b: "[b] Rs 25,000 crores",
      c: "[c] Rs 35,000 crores",
      d: "[d] Rs 30,000 crores",
      e: "[e] Rs 40,000 crores",
      answer: "[b] Rs 25,000 crores",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.9) What is the theme of International Day of Families 2021?",
      a: "[a] Families and New Technologies",
      b: "[b] Families in Development: Copenhagen & Beijing + 25",
      c: "[c] Families and Climate Action: Focus on SDG13",
      d: "[d] Families and inclusive societies",
      e: "[e] Families, education and well-being",
      answer: "[a] Families and New Technologies",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.10) Which year is International Year of the Family?",
      a: "[a] 2021",
      b: "[b] 2024",
      c: "[c] 2027",
      d: "[d] 2025",
      e: "[e] 2030",
      answer: "[b] 2024",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.1) What is the name of the helpline launched by National Commission for Protection of Child Rights to provide psychological first-aid and emotional support to children affected during COVID-19 Pandemic?",
      a: "[a] SAMVEDNA",
      b: "[b] DRISHTI",
      c: "[c] SANYAM",
      d: "[d] JYOTI",
      e: "[e] PRAGATI",
      answer: "[a] SAMVEDNA",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.2) Which of the following university collaborated with Department of Science and Technology for conducting the BRICS Astronomy Working Group (BAWG)?",
      a: "[a] Indian Institute of Science",
      b: "[b] Indian Institute of Astrophysics",
      c: "[c] Inter-University Centre for Astronomy and Astrophysics",
      d: "[d] National Centre for Radio Astrophysics",
      e: "[e] Indian Institute of Space Science and Technology",
      answer: "[c] Inter-University Centre for Astronomy and Astrophysics",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.3) As per the Indian Insurance Companies (Foreign Investment) Rules, 2021, the foreign direct investment limit in the insurance sector has been increased from __ to ___?",
      a: "[a] 49% to 74%",
      b: "[b] 23% to 55%",
      c: "[c] 37% to 65%",
      d: "[d] 45% to 66%",
      e: "[e] 71% to 100%",
      answer: "[a] 49% to 74%",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.4) Which company has launched 'School of Hope and Empowerment' (S.H.E.) as its CSR project at the 2021 UNESCO World Conference on Education for Sustainable Development?",
      a: "[a] Larsen and Toubro",
      b: "[b] Alphabet Inc",
      c: "[c] JSW Steel Ltd",
      d: "[d] Tata Communications",
      e: "[e] IBM",
      answer: "[d] Tata Communications",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.5) Which has become the first Small Finance Bank to offer online account opening services to its NRI customers?",
      a: "[a] Ujjivan Small Finance Bank",
      b: "[b] Janalakshmi Small Finance Bank",
      c: "[c] A U Small Finance Bank",
      d: "[d] Equitas Small Finance Bank",
      e: "[e] Utkarsh Small Finance Bank",
      answer: "[d] Equitas Small Finance Bank",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.1) Which of the following helpline has been launched by Ministry of Social Justice & Empowerment to address the problems of elders in the context of the ongoing COVID pandemic?",
      a: "[a] Elderline",
      b: "[b] Helpdesk",
      c: "[c] Ask Eld",
      d: "[d] Vayo Mitra",
      e: "[e] Vayovridha",
      answer: "[a] Elderline",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.2) MyGov has partnered with Department of Higher Education to launch an innovation challenge for creating ___ App?",
      a: "[a] Startup Incubation App",
      b: "[b] Covid Response App",
      c: "[c] Vaccine Registration App",
      d: "[d] Indian Language Learning App",
      e: "[e] International Scholarship Information App",
      answer: "[d] Indian Language Learning App",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.3) With which country has India renewed its MoU on military cooperation and maritime cooperation?",
      a: "[a] Qatar",
      b: "[b] Oman",
      c: "[c] Saudi Arabia",
      d: "[d] Israel",
      e: "[e] Egypt",
      answer: "[b] Oman",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.4) According to the latest estimates published by the WHO and International Labour Organization (ILO) in Environment International, working ___ hours or more per week is a serious health hazard?",
      a: "[a] 55 hours",
      b: "[b] 35 hours",
      c: "[c] 60 hours",
      d: "[d] 45 hours",
      e: "[e] 70 hours",
      answer: "[a] 55 hours",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.5) Which has become the world’s first country to ban all synthetic cannabinoid substances?",
      a: "[a] Japan",
      b: "[b] South Korea",
      c: "[c] Russia",
      d: "[d] China",
      e: "[e] Israel",
      answer: "[d] China",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.1) Which state has launched ‘Sanjeevani Pariyojana’ to provide medical care to people in district in home isolation and having mild and moderate Covid-19 symptoms?",
      a: "[a] Maharashtra",
      b: "[b] Gujarat",
      c: "[c] Tamil Nadu",
      d: "[d] Haryana",
      e: "[e] Punjab",
      answer: "[d] Haryana",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.2) Who is the President of FIH?",
      a: "[a] Thierry Weil",
      b: "[b] Fumio Ogura",
      c: "[c] Narinder Batra",
      d: "[d] Marijke Fleuren",
      e: "[e] Clare Prideaux",
      answer: "[c] Narinder Batra",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.3) Who has been appointed as the CEO of Reserve Bank Innovation Hub?",
      a: "[a] Gyan Bhushan",
      b: "[b] Rajesh Bansal",
      c: "[c] R. K. Bhati",
      d: "[d] Pranav Prakash",
      e: "[e] Susheela Tigga",
      answer: "[b] Rajesh Bansal",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.4) Which of the following has won the Best Biodiversity Management Committee award at the 5th edition of India Biodiversity Awards?",
      a: "[a] Shergaon BMC",
      b: "[b] Changlang BMC",
      c: "[c] Kra Daadi BMC",
      d: "[d] Kurung Kumey BMC",
      e: "[e] Itanagar BMC",
      answer: "[a] Shergaon BMC",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.5) Which lab of DRDO has developed 'DIPCOVAN' - an antibody detection kit for SARS-CoV-2 virus?",
      a: "[a] Defence Avionics Research Establishment",
      b: "[b] Defence Institute of Bio-Energy Research",
      c: "[c] Defence Institute of High Altitude Research",
      d: "[d] Defence Institute of Physiology and Allied Sciences",
      e: "[e] Defence Scientific Information & Documentation Centre",
      answer: "[d] Defence Institute of Physiology and Allied Sciences",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.1) Which country hosted the Summit on Financing African Economies 2021?",
      a: "[a] France",
      b: "[b] Russia",
      c: "[c] Poland",
      d: "[d] Nigeria",
      e: "[e] Ethiopia",
      answer: "[a] France",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.2) What is India’s rank in the “Renewable Energy Country Attractiveness Index” (RECAI) 2021?",
      a: "[a] 103",
      b: "[b] 3",
      c: "[c] 57",
      d: "[d] 88",
      e: "[e] 15",
      answer: "[b] 3",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.3) What is the total number of internally displaced people at the end of 2020, as per the 2021 Global Report on Internal Displacement (GRID): Internal Displacement in Changing Climate report?",
      a: "[a] 30 million",
      b: "[b] 23 million",
      c: "[c] 40 million",
      d: "[d] 55 million",
      e: "[e] 60 million",
      answer: "[d] 55 million",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.4) Which is the top ranked Indian city in the “Prime Global Cities Index: Q1 2021” report of Knight Frank?",
      a: "[a] Bangalore",
      b: "[b] Ahmedabad",
      c: "[c] Delhi",
      d: "[d] Mumbai",
      e: "[e] Chennai",
      answer: "[c] Delhi",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.5) When is the World Bee Day observed?",
      a: "[a] May 23",
      b: "[b] May 20",
      c: "[c] May 11",
      d: "[d] May 6",
      e: "[e] May 10",
      answer: "[b] May 20",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.6) Which country has developed Simurgh supercomputer?",
      a: "[a] Turkey",
      b: "[b] Israel",
      c: "[c] Lebanon",
      d: "[d] Iran",
      e: "[e] Egypt",
      answer: "[d] Iran",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.7) Where is the Megalithic site of Hire Benkal located?",
      a: "[a] Madhya Pradesh",
      b: "[b] Gujarat",
      c: "[c] Karnataka",
      d: "[d] Kerala",
      e: "[e] Odisha",
      answer: "[c] Karnataka",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.8) Malerkotla is the 23rd district of which state?",
      a: "[a] Karnataka",
      b: "[b] Odisha",
      c: "[c] Andhra Pradesh",
      d: "[d] Telangana",
      e: "[e] Punjab",
      answer: "[e] Punjab",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.9) What is the maximum value limit of a prepaid Gift PPI instrument?",
      a: "[a] Rs 2,000",
      b: "[b] Rs 6,000",
      c: "[c] Rs 7,000",
      d: "[d] Rs 5,000",
      e: "[e] Rs 10,000",
      answer: "[e] Rs 10,000",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.10) Which bank has launched Loan Processing System (LPS), a fully digitised loan processing system, for MSME and Agri products?",
      a: "[a] HDFC Bank",
      b: "[b] IDBI Bank",
      c: "[c] SBI",
      d: "[d] PNB",
      e: "[e] Kotak Mahindra Bank",
      answer: "[b] IDBI Bank",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.1) Which state has launched Amrit Vahini website, app and the related chatbot to help people book hospital beds online?",
      a: "[a] Tripura",
      b: "[b] Jharkhand",
      c: "[c] Himachal Pradesh",
      d: "[d] Uttarakhand",
      e: "[e] Odisha",
      answer: "[b] Jharkhand",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.2) Which state has signed an MoU with the National Health Authority (NHA) for the implementation of Ayushman Bharat (Pradhan Mantri Jan Arogya Yojana) scheme in the State?",
      a: "[a] Telangana",
      b: "[b] Delhi",
      c: "[c] West Bengal",
      d: "[d] Odisha",
      e: "[e] Jammu and Kashmir",
      answer: "[a] Telangana",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.3) Which nation has launched the Haiyang-2D satellite?",
      a: "[a] Republic of Korea",
      b: "[b] China",
      c: "[c] Japan",
      d: "[d] Mongolia",
      e: "[e] Russia",
      answer: "[b] China",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.4) Who has won the 2020 Millennium Technology Prize?",
      a: "[a] Shankar Balasubramanian",
      b: "[b] David Klenerman",
      c: "[c] Shankar Maheshwari",
      d: "[d] Both A and B",
      e: "[e] Both B and C",
      answer: "[d] Both A and B",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.5) Which state has topped in establishing Health and Wellness Centres under Ayushman Bharat Program in 2020-21?",
      a: "[a] Karnataka",
      b: "[b] Kerala",
      c: "[c] Maharashtra",
      d: "[d] Assam",
      e: "[e] Uttar Pradesh",
      answer: "[a] Karnataka",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.1) Recently, India renewed its Cultural Exchange Programme (CEP) with a country till 2023?",
      a: "[a] Afghanistan",
      b: "[b] Mongolia",
      c: "[c] Philippines",
      d: "[d] Thailand",
      e: "[e] Maldives",
      answer: "[b] Mongolia",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.2) Which city is the healthiest city in the country as per the “State Of Indian Healthcare Indian Cities Through The Lens Of Healthcare 2021” report?",
      a: "[a] Kolkata",
      b: "[b] Pune",
      c: "[c] Ahmedabad",
      d: "[d] Mumbai",
      e: "[e] Delhi",
      answer: "[b] Pune",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.3) Where is the India's first Agriculture Export Facilitation Centre established?",
      a: "[a] Nagpur",
      b: "[b] Amravati",
      c: "[c] Aurangabad",
      d: "[d] Pune",
      e: "[e] Nashik",
      answer: "[d] Pune",
    },
    {
      question:
        'Q.4) Which bank has launched “I choose my number" feature for all its customers across India?',
      a: "[a] Capital Small Finance Bank",
      b: "[b] Jana Small Finance Bank",
      c: "[c] Equitas Small Finance Bank",
      d: "[d] A U Small Finance Bank",
      e: "[e] Suryoday Small Finance Bank",
      answer: "[b] Jana Small Finance Bank",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.5) What is the theme of UN Global Road Safety Week 2021?",
      a: "[a] SpeakUp to save lives",
      b: "[b] Improving global road safety",
      c: "[c] Leadership for RoadSafety",
      d: "[d] Save Lives – #SlowDown",
      e: "[e] Streets for Life",
      answer: "[e] Streets for Life",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.1) How many Indian cities are most vulnerable cities as per Verisk Maplecroft Global Risk Analytics Dataset?",
      a: "[a] 57",
      b: "[b] 30",
      c: "[c] 43",
      d: "[d] 40",
      e: "[e] 25",
      answer: "[c] 43",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.2) Which multilateral bank has made its highest ever annual lending commitment of USD 3.92 billion to India in 2020?",
      a: "[a] European Investment Bank",
      b: "[b] Asian Development Bank",
      c: "[c] International Monetary Fund",
      d: "[d] World Bank",
      e: "[e] European Central Bank",
      answer: "[b] Asian Development Bank",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.3) Who has been appointed as the CEO of BATA India?",
      a: "[a] Gunjan Shah",
      b: "[b] Santosh Kumar",
      c: "[c] Anita Baghel",
      d: "[d] Gyan Bhushan",
      e: "[e] Madan Lal",
      answer: "[a] Gunjan Shah",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.4) Who has topped the Fortune’s world’s 50 greatest leaders 2021 list?",
      a: "[a] Justin Trudeau",
      b: "[b] Emmanuel Macron",
      c: "[c] Jacinda Ardern",
      d: "[d] Shimon Peres",
      e: "[e] Joe Biden",
      answer: "[c] Jacinda Ardern",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.5) Who has won the Whitley Award 2021?",
      a: "[a] Ridhima Pandey",
      b: "[b] Aditya Mukarji",
      c: "[c] Licypriya Kangujam",
      d: "[d] Nuklu Phom",
      e: "[e] Anadish Pal",
      answer: "[d] Nuklu Phom",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.1) With which company has Ministry of Tribal Affairs signed an MoU for digital transformation of Tribal Schools such as Eklavya Model Residential Schools and Ashram Schools?",
      a: "[a] IBM",
      b: "[b] Intel",
      c: "[c] Adobe",
      d: "[d] Microsoft",
      e: "[e] Apple",
      answer: "[d] Microsoft",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.2) Who among the following has become the first Indian woman to summit Mount Pumori?",
      a: "[a] Baljeet Kaur",
      b: "[b] Gunbala Sharma",
      c: "[c] Nitu Pathak",
      d: "[d] Both A and B",
      e: "[e] Both B and C",
      answer: "[d] Both A and B",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.3) Which company has launched world’s first private digital court?",
      a: "[a] Intello Labs",
      b: "[b] HyperVerge",
      c: "[c] Niki.ai",
      d: "[d] Jupitice Justice Technologies",
      e: "[e] Artivatic.ai",
      answer: "[d] Jupitice Justice Technologies",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.4) In which state is 'Vaidya Aapke Dwar' scheme launched by Department of AYUSH to provide free medical consultation through video call?",
      a: "[a] Uttarakhand",
      b: "[b] Madhya Pradesh",
      c: "[c] Maharashtra",
      d: "[d] Gujarat",
      e: "[e] Tamil Nadu",
      answer: "[b] Madhya Pradesh",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.5) In which state has AYUSH Department launched 'AYUSH Ghar Dwar' for COVID-19 patients?",
      a: "[a] Odisha",
      b: "[b] Telangana",
      c: "[c] Andhra Pradesh",
      d: "[d] Himachal Pradesh",
      e: "[e] Arunachal Pradesh",
      answer: "[d] Himachal Pradesh",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.1) COVID-19 Crisis Through a Migration Lens report?",
      a: "[a] $83 billion",
      b: "[b] $97 billion",
      c: "[c] $67 billion",
      d: "[d] $102 billion",
      e: "[e] $23 billion",
      answer: "[a] $83 billion",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.2) What is the name of the portal launched by NITI Aayog to monitor the aid received by the govt of India for fighting the Covid-19 pandemic?",
      a: "[a] CovAid",
      b: "[b] CovShield",
      c: "[c] Def-Cov",
      d: "[d] Covax-Aid",
      e: "[e] Covin",
      answer: "[a] CovAid",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.3) Which organization has partnered with OneWeb for mutual cooperation to promote OneWeb's satellite communication services in the global and Japan markets?",
      a: "[a] Mitsubishi UFJ Financial Group",
      b: "[b] Sumitomo Mitsui Financial Group",
      c: "[c] Norinchukin Bank",
      d: "[d] Mizuho Financial Group",
      e: "[e] SoftBank Corp",
      answer: "[e] SoftBank Corp",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.4) Where is United Co-operative Bank Ltd located?",
      a: "[a] West Bengal",
      b: "[b] Maharashtra",
      c: "[c] Madhya Pradesh",
      d: "[d] Gujarat",
      e: "[e] Odisha",
      answer: "[a] West Bengal",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.5) Which company has launched DigiGold platform?",
      a: "[a] NSDL Payments Bank.",
      b: "[b] Jio Payments Bank",
      c: "[c] Fino Payments Bank",
      d: "[d] Airtel Payments Bank",
      e: "[e] India Post Payments Bank",
      answer: "[d] Airtel Payments Bank",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.1) Which state has launched “Mission Oxygen” to encourage the private sector to generate liquid medical oxygen?",
      a: "[a] West Bengal",
      b: "[b] Karnataka",
      c: "[c] Kerala",
      d: "[d] Maharashtra",
      e: "[e] Delhi",
      answer: "[d] Maharashtra",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.2) As per the International Energy Agency’s “Renewable Energy Market Update Outlook for 2021 and 2022” report, the renewable energy capacity addition increased by 45% in 2020 to ______ which is the highest year on year increase since 1999?",
      a: "[a] 190 GW",
      b: "[b] 450 GW",
      c: "[c] 280 GW",
      d: "[d] 370 GW",
      e: "[e] 540 GW",
      answer: "[c] 280 GW",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.3) With which bank has Geojit Financial Services partnered to offer 3-in-1 account services to its retail customers?",
      a: "[a] Bank of Baroda",
      b: "[b] State Bank of India",
      c: "[c] Canara Bank",
      d: "[d] Punjab National Bank",
      e: "[e] Axis Bank",
      answer: "[d] Punjab National Bank",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.4) Which of the following company has launched the Farmizo Khata, a B2C Farm accounting mobile application, in partnership with Yono app?",
      a: "[a] Agrowave",
      b: "[b] BharatAgri",
      c: "[c] BigHaat",
      d: "[d] Shivrai Technologies",
      e: "[e] Clover Ventures",
      answer: "[d] Shivrai Technologies",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.5) Who has been appointed as the CEO of the National Asset Reconstruction Company Ltd?",
      a: "[a] Arvind Singh",
      b: "[b] Padmakumar M Nair",
      c: "[c] R. K. Dhawan",
      d: "[d] Sanjay Pandey",
      e: "[e] S.Prasannan",
      answer: "[b] Padmakumar M Nair",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.6) What is the GDP forecast for India for FY22, as per the UN’s World Economic Situation and Prospects report?",
      a: "[a] 7.5%",
      b: "[b] 8.8%",
      c: "[c] 9.3%",
      d: "[d] 10.2%",
      e: "[e] 5.4%",
      answer: "[a] 7.5%",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.7) Who has become the first woman of Asian descent to win the 2021 World Food Prize?",
      a: "[a] Saroj Chooramani Gopal",
      b: "[b] Mirudhubashini Govindarajan",
      c: "[c] Shakuntala Haraksingh Thilsted",
      d: "[d] Janaki Ammal",
      e: "[e] Asima Chatterjee",
      answer: "[c] Shakuntala Haraksingh Thilsted",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.8) Which of the following has won the “Green Urja Award”?",
      a: "[a] Energy Efficiency Services Limited",
      b: "[b] Coal India Ltd",
      c: "[c] National Thermal Power Corporation",
      d: "[d] Indian Renewable Energy Development Agency Ltd.",
      e: "[e] Powergrid Corporation of India",
      answer: "[d] Indian Renewable Energy Development Agency Ltd.",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.9) Who is the author of “1971: The Beginning of India's Cricketing Greatness” book?",
      a: "[a] Boria Majumdar",
      b: "[b] Gautam Bhattacharya",
      c: "[c] Sarojini Shekhar",
      d: "[d] Both A and B",
      e: "[e] Both B and C",
      answer: "[d] Both A and B",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.10) What is the GDP growth rate forecasted by Nomura for FY22?",
      a: "[a] 11.2%",
      b: "[b] 10.6%",
      c: "[c] 5.2%",
      d: "[d] 9.8%",
      e: "[e] 10.8%",
      answer: "[e] 10.8%",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.1) Which IIT has partnered with Mobile Payment Forum of India (MPFI) to develop voice-based solutions in multiple vernacular languages to enable larger adoption of digital money transactions in the country?",
      a: "[a] IIT- Madras",
      b: "[b] IIT- Guwahati",
      c: "[c] IIT- Kanpur",
      d: "[d] IIT- Bombay",
      e: "[e] IIT- Varanasi",
      answer: "[a] IIT- Madras",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.2) With which organization has NASA collaborated for first private astronaut mission to the International Space Station?",
      a: "[a] Virgin Galactic",
      b: "[b] SpaceX",
      c: "[c] Axiom Space",
      d: "[d] Blue Origin",
      e: "[e] Bigelow Aerospace",
      answer: "[c] Axiom Space",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.3) Who has been appointed as the chairman and managing director of Bharat Petroleum Corporation Ltd?",
      a: "[a] Neerja Sekhar",
      b: "[b] Arun Kumar Singh",
      c: "[c] P C Bodh",
      d: "[d] Vikram Sahay",
      e: "[e] Anju Nigam",
      answer: "[b] Arun Kumar Singh",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.4) What is the theme of International Nurses Day 2021?",
      a: "[a] Achieving the Sustainable Development Goals",
      b: "[b] Health is a Human right",
      c: "[c] Health for All",
      d: "[d] Nursing the World to Health",
      e: "[e] A Vision for future healthcare",
      answer: "[e] A Vision for future healthcare",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.5) Who has become the first person from India to win the 15th Sheikh Zayed Book Award?",
      a: "[a] Tahera Qutbuddin",
      b: "[b] Iman Mersal",
      c: "[c] Mizouni Bannani",
      d: "[d] Asma Muqbil",
      e: "[e] Khelil Gouia",
      answer: "[a] Tahera Qutbuddin",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.6) Who has become the first Indian to receive the Arline Pacht Global Vision Award for 2021?",
      a: "[a] Gita Mittal",
      b: "[b] Fathima Beevi",
      c: "[c] Sujata Manohar",
      d: "[d] Ruma Pal",
      e: "[e] Gyan Sudha Misra",
      answer: "[a] Gita Mittal",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.7) Which company has collaborated with NIRA (Bengaluru-based fintech) to strengthen its digital footprint?",
      a: "[a] HDB Finance Services",
      b: "[b] Bajaj Finance Limited",
      c: "[c] Muthoot Finance Limited",
      d: "[d] Mahindra & Mahindra Financial Services",
      e: "[e] Power Finance Corporation",
      answer: "[c] Muthoot Finance Limited",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.8) Which bank has partnered with Mashreq Bank (based in UAE) to facilitate money transfers from the UAE?",
      a: "[a] ICICI Bank",
      b: "[b] Axis Bank",
      c: "[c] State Bank of India",
      d: "[d] Federal Bank",
      e: "[e] Punjab National Bank",
      answer: "[d] Federal Bank",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.9) With which organization has NITI Aayog partnered to release the ‘Connected Commerce: Creating a Roadmap for a Digitally Inclusive Bharat’ report?",
      a: "[a] The Lancet",
      b: "[b] Bloomberg",
      c: "[c] Paytm",
      d: "[d] Cornell University",
      e: "[e] Mastercard",
      answer: "[e] Mastercard",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.10) Who heads the committee formed by Maharashtra govt for studying the Supreme Court's order striking down quota for the Maratha community in Maharashtra?",
      a: "[a] Rajkumar Singh Thakur",
      b: "[b] Dilip Bhosale",
      c: "[c] Bibhuti Bhushana Dash",
      d: "[d] Fakhre Alam",
      e: "[e] Kimjamlhing Changloi",
      answer: "[b] Dilip Bhosale",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.1) Recently, India, Israel and the UAE have signed their first ever trilateral pact. This is the first such arrangement since Israel and UAE established diplomatic ties. The agreement facilitates development of an innovative robotic solar cleaning technology in India for a landmark project in the UAE. The trilateral partnership has been initiated by the International Federation of Indo-Israel Chambers of Commerce. Which company will produce this technology?",
      a: "[a] Light IT",
      b: "[b] Solvd Inc",
      c: "[c] Aalpha Information Systems",
      d: "[d] Ecoppia",
      e: "[e] NIX",
      answer: "[d] Ecoppia",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.2) Which state has started a new Mukhyamantri Seva Sankalp Helpline Number 1100 for public grievance addressal in the state?",
      a: "[a] Maharashtra",
      b: "[b] Uttar Pradesh",
      c: "[c] Himachal Pradesh",
      d: "[d] Uttarakhand",
      e: "[e] Rajasthan",
      answer: "[c] Himachal Pradesh",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.3) What is the venue of G7 Foreign Minister’s Meeting 2021?",
      a: "[a] London",
      b: "[b] Vienna",
      c: "[c] Sofia",
      d: "[d] Minsk",
      e: "[e] Brussels",
      answer: "[a] London",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.4) Who is the CEO of Deloitte?",
      a: "[a] Tammy Baldwin",
      b: "[b] Gary Peters",
      c: "[c] Catherine Cortez Masto",
      d: "[d] Punit Renjen",
      e: "[e] Jeff Merkley",
      answer: "[d] Punit Renjen",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.5) As per the “Global Methane Assessment 2021”, __ percent reduction in methane emissions by 2030 would reduce global warming by 0.3º C by 2040s?",
      a: "[a] 50%",
      b: "[b] 45%",
      c: "[c] 30%",
      d: "[d] 25%",
      e: "[e] 60%",
      answer: "[b] 45%",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.6) Which bank has won five awards (Lead to Leap, APY Makers of Excellence, Game Changers, Leadership Capital and Amazing Achievers) from the Pension Fund Regulatory and Development Authority?",
      a: "[a] Andhra Pradesh Grameena Vikas Bank",
      b: "[b] Bangiya Gramin Vikash Bank",
      c: "[c] Karnataka Vikas Grameen Bank",
      d: "[d] Baroda Rajasthan Kshetriya Gramin Bank",
      e: "[e] Baroda Gujarat Gramin Bank",
      answer: "[c] Karnataka Vikas Grameen Bank",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.7) Under which section of Companies Act 2013 was National Financial Reporting Authority created?",
      a: "[a] Section 101",
      b: "[b] Section 279",
      c: "[c] Section 338",
      d: "[d] Section 420",
      e: "[e] Section 132",
      answer: "[e] Section 132",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.8) Who is the Chairperson of National Financial Reporting Authority?",
      a: "[a] Prasenjit Mukherjee",
      b: "[b] Vivek Narayan",
      c: "[c] Venkateswarlu Peri",
      d: "[d] R. Sridharan",
      e: "[e] Arun Kumar",
      answer: "[d] R. Sridharan",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.9) Who has become the CM of Puducherry?",
      a: "[a] A.K. Sai J Saravanan Kumar",
      b: "[b] N Rangasamy",
      c: "[c] A. Johnkumar",
      d: "[d] A. Namassivayam",
      e: "[e] V. Saminathan",
      answer: "[b] N Rangasamy",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.10) Which company introduced world’s first 2-nanometre chipmaking technology?",
      a: "[a] IBM",
      b: "[b] Intel",
      c: "[c] Qualcomm",
      d: "[d] TSMC",
      e: "[e] Micron Technology",
      answer: "[a] IBM",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.1) Which state has launched the 'Mukhyamantri COVID Upchar Yojana'?",
      a: "[a] Uttar Pradesh",
      b: "[b] Jharkhand",
      c: "[c] Chhattisgarh",
      d: "[d] Madhya Pradesh",
      e: "[e] Punjab",
      answer: "[d] Madhya Pradesh",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.2) What is the name of the app launched by Interpol to help identify stolen cultural property, reduce illicit trafficking, and increase the chances of recovering stolen works and artefacts?",
      a: "[a] Trace",
      b: "[b] ID-Art",
      c: "[c] Path",
      d: "[d] Stalk-Art",
      e: "[e] Track-Art",
      answer: "[b] ID-Art",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.3) Who heads the RBI’s six-member Advisory Group set up under the Regulations Review Authority (RRA 2.0)?",
      a: "[a] S Janakiraman",
      b: "[b] T. Rabi Sankar",
      c: "[c] M. Rajeshwar Rao",
      d: "[d] M. D. Patra",
      e: "[e] M. K. Jain",
      answer: "[a] S Janakiraman",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.4) How much percentage of investible surplus is the Employees Provident Fund Organisation allowed to invest in alternate investment funds?",
      a: "[a] 10%",
      b: "[b] 3%",
      c: "[c] 5%",
      d: "[d] 12%",
      e: "[e] 20%",
      answer: "[c] 5%",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.5) Which company has launched 'Savdhan Rahein. Safe Rahein' public awareness campaign to educate customers and public at large on financial fraud risks?",
      a: "[a] Muthoot Finance Ltd",
      b: "[b] HDB Finance Services",
      c: "[c] Tata Capital Financial Services",
      d: "[d] Power Finance Corporation",
      e: "[e] Bajaj Finserv",
      answer: "[e] Bajaj Finserv",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.6) Who has been appointed as the 38th President of the FICCI Ladies Organization?",
      a: "[a] Sarojini Shekhar",
      b: "[b] Anita Baghel",
      c: "[c] Ujjwala Singhania",
      d: "[d] Rajni Sharma",
      e: "[e] Radhika Shah",
      answer: "[c] Ujjwala Singhania",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.7) Who has been awarded the Laureus World Sportsman of The Year 2021?",
      a: "[a] Naomi Osaka",
      b: "[b] Patrick Mahomes",
      c: "[c] Max Parrot",
      d: "[d] Rafael Nadal",
      e: "[e] Billie Jean King",
      answer: "[d] Rafael Nadal",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.8) Which country organized the 3rd Arctic Science Ministerial?",
      a: "[a] Japan",
      b: "[b] Iceland",
      c: "[c] Norway",
      d: "[d] Both A and B",
      e: "[e] Both B and C",
      answer: "[d] Both A and B",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.9) Who among the following is the convener of the 12-member National Task Force set up by Supreme Court to streamline the process of oxygen distribution between states and UT on the basis of scientific and specialised domain knowledge?",
      a: "[a] Devender Singh Rana",
      b: "[b] Bhabatosh Biswas",
      c: "[c] Gagandeep Kang",
      d: "[d] Rajiv Gauba",
      e: "[e] Naresh Trehan",
      answer: "[d] Rajiv Gauba",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.10) Who has won the women’s singles title at Madrid Open tennis?",
      a: "[a] Lesia Tsurenko",
      b: "[b] Elina Svitolina",
      c: "[c] Simona Halep",
      d: "[d] Aryna Sabalenka",
      e: "[e] Ashleigh Barty",
      answer: "[d] Aryna Sabalenka",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.1) Which state has become India’s first state to adopt online flood forecasting system?",
      a: "[a] Madhya Pradesh",
      b: "[b] Arunachal Pradesh",
      c: "[c] Assam",
      d: "[d] Odisha",
      e: "[e] West Bengal",
      answer: "[c] Assam",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.2) Which bank has partnered with Common Services Centres to launch the chatbot ‘Eva’ on CSCs Digital Seva Portal to support the Village Level Entrepreneurs?",
      a: "[a] ICICI Bank",
      b: "[b] HDFC Bank",
      c: "[c] Axis Bank",
      d: "[d] Yes Bank",
      e: "[e] DCB Bank",
      answer: "[b] HDFC Bank",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.3) What is the theme of National Technology Day 2021?",
      a: "[a] Rebooting the Economy through Science, Technology and Research Translations",
      b: "[b] Space Technologies and ISRO",
      c: "[c] Technology for inclusive and sustainable growth",
      d: "[d] Science and Technology for a Sustainable Future",
      e: "[e] Technology Enablers of Startup India",
      answer: "[d] Science and Technology for a Sustainable Future",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.4) Whose debut book is titled as ‘Life in the Clock Tower Valley’?",
      a: "[a] Amar Pal",
      b: "[b] Rajkumar Singh Thakur",
      c: "[c] R. K. Dhawan",
      d: "[d] S.Prasannan",
      e: "[e] Shakoor Rather",
      answer: "[e] Shakoor Rather",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.5) With which country has India jointly launched the Neev Fund I?",
      a: "[a] Germany",
      b: "[b] Finland",
      c: "[c] France",
      d: "[d] Japan",
      e: "[e] UK",
      answer: "[e] UK",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.1) Which of the following IIT has launched Mission Bharat O2?",
      a: "[a] IIT Madras",
      b: "[b] IIT Delhi",
      c: "[c] IIT Bombay",
      d: "[d] IIT Kanpur",
      e: "[e] IIT Kharagpur",
      answer: "[d] IIT Kanpur",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.2) With which company has National Dairy Development Board signed an agreement to promote efficient renewable technologies in the dairy industry?",
      a: "[a] National Thermal Power Corporation",
      b: "[b] Energy Efficiency Services Ltd",
      c: "[c] North Eastern Electric Power Corporation",
      d: "[d] National Hydroelectric Power Corporation",
      e: "[e] Power Grid Corporation of India",
      answer: "[b] Energy Efficiency Services Ltd",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.3) With which country has India signed an MoU on Migration and Mobility Partnership (MMP) to facilitate legal movement of students and professionals, and combating illegal migration and organised immigration crime?",
      a: "[a] Thailand",
      b: "[b] UK",
      c: "[c] Japan",
      d: "[d] USA",
      e: "[e] Australia",
      answer: "[b] UK",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.4) With which of the following entity has Telecom Equipment Manufacturers Association of India signed an MoU to cooperate on a series of mutually beneficial matters?",
      a: "[a] Indo-Italy Chamber of Commerce",
      b: "[b] Indo-Germany Chamber of Commerce",
      c: "[c] Indo-Canada Chamber of Commerce",
      d: "[d] Indo-US Chamber of Commerce",
      e: "[e] Indo-Singapore Chamber of Commerce",
      answer: "[c] Indo-Canada Chamber of Commerce",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.5) Which country will host the European Council meeting 2021?",
      a: "[a] Austria",
      b: "[b] Croatia",
      c: "[c] Belgium",
      d: "[d] Bulgaria",
      e: "[e] Portugal",
      answer: "[e] Portugal",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.1) Which state has launched CLAP to promote cleanliness in the state?",
      a: "[a] Andhra Pradesh",
      b: "[b] Maharashtra",
      c: "[c] Tamil Nadu",
      d: "[d] Telangana",
      e: "[e] Punjab",
      answer: "[a] Andhra Pradesh",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.2) Which company has partnered with the Indian government to launch a Vaccine Finder Tool on its mobile app in India?",
      a: "[a] Mobikwik",
      b: "[b] Amazon",
      c: "[c] Facebook",
      d: "[d] Twitter",
      e: "[e] Google",
      answer: "[c] Facebook",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.3) What is the GDP forecast for India for FY22 by S&P?",
      a: "[a] 11.9%",
      b: "[b] 12.3%",
      c: "[c] 10.5%",
      d: "[d] 9.8%",
      e: "[e] 8.7%",
      answer: "[d] 9.8%",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.4) What is LIC’s rank in Brand Finance Insurance 100 2021 report in terms of value?",
      a: "[a] 10th",
      b: "[b] 8th",
      c: "[c] 5th",
      d: "[d] 20th",
      e: "[e] 15th",
      answer: "[a] 10th",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.5) Who is the director of Jungle Cry?",
      a: "[a] Kamal Haasan",
      b: "[b] Dibakar Banerjee",
      c: "[c] Mani Ratnam",
      d: "[d] Sagar Ballary",
      e: "[e] Anurag Kashyap",
      answer: "[d] Sagar Ballary",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.6) What is India’s rank in ICC’s annual rankings in the category of Test matches?",
      a: "[a] 1st",
      b: "[b] 4th",
      c: "[c] 5th",
      d: "[d] 10th",
      e: "[e] 3rd",
      answer: "[a] 1st",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.7) “The Bench” is the first children’s book of which of the following?",
      a: "[a] Paul Mendez",
      b: "[b] Abi Daré",
      c: "[c] Deepa Anappara",
      d: "[d] Elaine Feeney",
      e: "[e] Meghan Markel",
      answer: "[e] Meghan Markel",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.8) Who is the writer of “BENGAL 2021: An Election Diary”?",
      a: "[a] Megha Majumdar",
      b: "[b] Deep Halder",
      c: "[c] Kunal Basu",
      d: "[d] Deepa Anappara",
      e: "[e] Jayasree Kalathil",
      answer: "[b] Deep Halder",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.9) What is the outlay of liquidity facility window provided by RBI to banks for on-lending to health services, as part of the relief measure for Covid-19?",
      a: "[a] Rs 10,000 crores",
      b: "[b] Rs 20,000 crores",
      c: "[c] Rs 35,000 crores",
      d: "[d] Rs 50,000 crores",
      e: "[e] Rs 60,000 crores",
      answer: "[d] Rs 50,000 crores",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.10) As per the State of the World’s Midwifery 2021 report, there is a global shortage of around _____ midwives, which is 1/3rd of the required global midwife workforce?",
      a: "[a] 2 lakh",
      b: "[b] 9 lakh",
      c: "[c] 7 lakh",
      d: "[d] 10 lakh",
      e: "[e] 3 lakh",
      answer: "[b] 9 lakh",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.1) Where is the 'Auro Scholarship Programme' launched?",
      a: "[a] Maharashtra",
      b: "[b] Tripura",
      c: "[c] Tamil Nadu",
      d: "[d] West Bengal",
      e: "[e] Manipur",
      answer: "[b] Tripura",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.2) On which ICGS has the Hindustan Aeronautics Limited's (HAL) Advanced Light Helicopter Dhruv Mk III MR completed deck operation trials?",
      a: "[a] ICGS Vajra",
      b: "[b] ICGS Samrat",
      c: "[c] ICGS Sujay",
      d: "[d] ICGS Sankalp",
      e: "[e] ICGS Samarth",
      answer: "[c] ICGS Sujay",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.3) Online sales accounted for ___ percent of the total retail sales in 2020, according to the UNCTAD’s “Estimates Of Global E-Commerce 2019 And Preliminary Assessment Of Covid-19 Impact On Online Retail 2020” report?",
      a: "[a] 19%",
      b: "[b] 23%",
      c: "[c] 17%",
      d: "[d] 11%",
      e: "[e] 10%",
      answer: "[a] 19%",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.4) What is the GDP forecast for India for FY22 by Goldman Sachs?",
      a: "[a] 10.3%",
      b: "[b] 11.1%",
      c: "[c] 9.3%",
      d: "[d] 8.5%",
      e: "[e] 12.7%",
      answer: "[b] 11.1%",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.5) Who have been nominated as athlete ambassador for International Olympic Committee’s ‘Believe in Sports’ campaign?",
      a: "[a] PV Sindhu",
      b: "[b] Pullela Gopichand",
      c: "[c] Saina Nehwal",
      d: "[d] Parupalli Kashyap",
      e: "[e] Aparna Popat",
      answer: "[a] PV Sindhu",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.6) Who has become the First woman Officer Executive Engineer (Civil) taking over as Officer Commanding of a Road Construction Company in BRO?",
      a: "[a] Sneha Vashisth",
      b: "[b] Vinita Sinha",
      c: "[c] Vaishali S Hiwase",
      d: "[d] Kavita Shanker",
      e: "[e] Priya Pal",
      answer: "[c] Vaishali S Hiwase",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.7) When is the International Firefighters' Day 2021 observed?",
      a: "[a] May 23",
      b: "[b] May 16",
      c: "[c] May 4",
      d: "[d] May 7",
      e: "[e] May 10",
      answer: "[c] May 4",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.8) What is the theme of World Asthma Day 2021?",
      a: "[a] Enough Asthma Deaths",
      b: "[b] Uncovering Asthma Misconceptions",
      c: "[c] STOP for asthma",
      d: "[d] Allergy and Asthma",
      e: "[e] You Can Control Your Asthma",
      answer: "[b] Uncovering Asthma Misconceptions",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.9) What is the cash prize given under the 'Satyajit Ray Lifetime Achievement Award for Excellence in Cinema'?",
      a: "[a] ₹30 lakh",
      b: "[b] ₹15 lakh",
      c: "[c] ₹20 lakh",
      d: "[d] ₹10 lakh",
      e: "[e] ₹5 lakh",
      answer: "[d] ₹10 lakh",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.10) Where is the National Museum of Indian Cinema located?",
      a: "[a] Mumbai",
      b: "[b] Kolkata",
      c: "[c] Delhi",
      d: "[d] Chandigarh",
      e: "[e] Bangalore",
      answer: "[a] Mumbai",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.1) Which of the following operation has been launched by the Indian Navy for procuring oxygen from different countries to India in the wake of Covid-19?",
      a: "[a] Operation Vayu II",
      b: "[b] Operation Samudra Setu II",
      c: "[c] Operation Sagar I",
      d: "[d] Operation Sanjeevani I",
      e: "[e] Operation Jeevan Raksha II",
      answer: "[b] Operation Samudra Setu II",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.2) Recently, Indian Army has inaugurated the First Green Solar Energy harnessing plant of 56 KVA using Vanadium based battery technology in ____ at an altitude of 16000 ft?",
      a: "[a] Arunachal Pradesh",
      b: "[b] Himachal Pradesh",
      c: "[c] Assam",
      d: "[d] Sikkim",
      e: "[e] Jammu and Kashmir",
      answer: "[d] Sikkim",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.3) How much food grain production target has been set up by the Central govt for 2021-22?",
      a: "[a] 170.77 million tonnes",
      b: "[b] 181.90 million tonnes",
      c: "[c] 307.31 million tonnes",
      d: "[d] 108.76 million tonnes",
      e: "[e] 223.11 million tonnes",
      answer: "[c] 307.31 million tonnes",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.4) Which bank has launched a special deposit scheme named “Immune India Deposit Scheme” to encourage people to get COVID-19 vaccines?",
      a: "[a] Central Bank of India",
      b: "[b] Indian Overseas Bank",
      c: "[c] Punjab and Sind Bank",
      d: "[d] Bank of Maharashtra",
      e: "[e] UCO Bank",
      answer: "[a] Central Bank of India",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.5) Which bank has acquired stake in two companies – India INX and India ICC – in GIFT City?",
      a: "[a] Union Bank of India",
      b: "[b] Bandhan Bank",
      c: "[c] Axis Bank",
      d: "[d] DCB Bank",
      e: "[e] Federal Bank",
      answer: "[d] DCB Bank",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.6) Which bank has launched two new quick credit delivery schemes –– SHWAS and AROG?",
      a: "[a] SIDBI",
      b: "[b] South Indian Bank",
      c: "[c] SBI",
      d: "[d] CSB Bank",
      e: "[e] Saurashtra Gramin Bank",
      answer: "[a] SIDBI",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.7) Who has been chosen for the post of CMD of BEML Limited?",
      a: "[a] Amit Banerjee",
      b: "[b] Upendra Prasad Singh",
      c: "[c] Vijoy Kumar Singh",
      d: "[d] Shashi Ranjan Kumar",
      e: "[e] Nihar Ranjan Dash",
      answer: "[a] Amit Banerjee",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.8) Who has been appointed as the MD of Kotak Mahindra Life Insurance Company Limited?",
      a: "[a] Sanjay Sharan",
      b: "[b] Jay Karan Singh",
      c: "[c] Gaurav Kumar",
      d: "[d] Mahesh Balasubramanian",
      e: "[e] Hemant kumar Nanda",
      answer: "[d] Mahesh Balasubramanian",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.9) Where will the 2021 ASBC Asian Elite Men and Women Boxing Championships be held?",
      a: "[a] Doha",
      b: "[b] Dubai",
      c: "[c] Cairo",
      d: "[d] Beirut",
      e: "[e] İstanbul",
      answer: "[b] Dubai",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.10) How much Central govt will give to state for capital expenditure under the “Scheme of Financial Assistance to States for Capital Expenditure” for 2021-22?",
      a: "[a] Rs 15,000 crore",
      b: "[b] Rs 25,000 crore",
      c: "[c] Rs 10,000 crore",
      d: "[d] Rs 12,000 crore",
      e: "[e] Rs 9,000 crore",
      answer: "[a] Rs 15,000 crore",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.1) Who chairs the Capacity Building Commission of India?",
      a: "[a] Rahul Chhabra",
      b: "[b] Vikas Swarup",
      c: "[c] Riva Ganguly Das",
      d: "[d] Adil Zainulbhai",
      e: "[e] Sanjay Bhattacharyya",
      answer: "[d] Adil Zainulbhai",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.2) In which state is the KVIC’s RE-HAB (Reducing Elephant-Human Attacks using Bees) pilot project launched?",
      a: "[a] Karnataka",
      b: "[b] Odisha",
      c: "[c] Andhra Pradesh",
      d: "[d] Maharashtra",
      e: "[e] Madhya Pradesh",
      answer: "[a] Karnataka",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.3) Where is Nagarahole National Park and Tiger Reserve located?",
      a: "[a] Odisha",
      b: "[b] Andhra Pradesh",
      c: "[c] Telangana",
      d: "[d] Tamil Nadu",
      e: "[e] Karnataka",
      answer: "[e] Karnataka",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.4) Which bank has partnered with Axis Securities to offer its customers the perfect mix of banking and investing through 3-in-1 account?",
      a: "[a] Ujjivan Small Finance Bank",
      b: "[b] Janalakshmi Small Finance Bank",
      c: "[c] Jana Small Finance Bank",
      d: "[d] Capital Small Finance Bank",
      e: "[e] Utkarsh Small Finance Bank",
      answer: "[c] Jana Small Finance Bank",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.5) What is India’s debt to GDP ratio according to the International Monetary Fund?",
      a: "[a] 80%",
      b: "[b] 90%",
      c: "[c] 75%",
      d: "[d] 60%",
      e: "[e] 95%",
      answer: "[b] 90%",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.6) Who has been appointed as the brand ambassador of Vivo?",
      a: "[a] Ravindra Jadeja",
      b: "[b] Virat Kohli",
      c: "[c] Rohit Sharma",
      d: "[d] KL Rahul",
      e: "[e] Rishabh Pant",
      answer: "[b] Virat Kohli",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.7) Who has made two Guinness World Records for fastest solo cycling from India?",
      a: "[a] Bharat Pannu",
      b: "[b] Sushil R Gaikwad",
      c: "[c] Gurpreet Singh",
      d: "[d] K.K. Singh",
      e: "[e] Suraj C. Naik",
      answer: "[a] Bharat Pannu",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.8) Which field does Fatima R Zakaria belong to? (She passed away recently.)",
      a: "[a] Journalist",
      b: "[b] Author",
      c: "[c] Professor",
      d: "[d] Both A and B",
      e: "[e] Both B and C",
      answer: "[d] Both A and B",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.9) Who is the author of ‘Odisha Itihaas’?",
      a: "[a] Harekrushna Mahatab",
      b: "[b] Vaidya Rajesh Kotecha",
      c: "[c] Dinesh Setia",
      d: "[d] Pramod Kumar Pathak",
      e: "[e] Dharmendra Singh Gangwar",
      answer: "[a] Harekrushna Mahatab",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.10) Where is Valley of Flowers National Park located?",
      a: "[a] Arunachal Pradesh",
      b: "[b] Assam",
      c: "[c] Madhya Pradesh",
      d: "[d] Uttarakhand",
      e: "[e] Himachal Pradesh",
      answer: "[d] Uttarakhand",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.1) Where is the secretariate of Codex Alimentarius Commission located?",
      a: "[a] Rome",
      b: "[b] Geneva",
      c: "[c] Amsterdam",
      d: "[d] Davos",
      e: "[e] Vienna",
      answer: "[a] Rome",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.2) How much is the maximum sum assured under the new Employees’ Deposit Linked Insurance Scheme, 2021?",
      a: "[a] Rs 5 lakh",
      b: "[b] Rs 6 lakh",
      c: "[c] Rs 1.5 lakh",
      d: "[d] Rs 7 lakh",
      e: "[e] Rs 2 lakh",
      answer: "[d] Rs 7 lakh",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.3) How much FDI has the govt allowed in the road sector?",
      a: "[a] 49%",
      b: "[b] 100%",
      c: "[c] 74%",
      d: "[d] 80%",
      e: "[e] 50%",
      answer: "[b] 100%",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.4) Which of the following institute has developed a high-yielding and pest-resistant variety of soybean, called MACS 1407?",
      a: "[a] Agharkar Research Institute",
      b: "[b] Indian Council of Agricultural Research",
      c: "[c] Indian Agricultural Research Institute",
      d: "[d] Both A and B",
      e: "[e] Both A and C",
      answer: "[d] Both A and B",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.5) Which edition of the G7 Summit will take place in UK?",
      a: "[a] 45th",
      b: "[b] 50th",
      c: "[c] 47th",
      d: "[d] 70th",
      e: "[e] 20th",
      answer: "[c] 47th",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.6) On which river is the World’s longest pedestrian suspension bridge located?",
      a: "[a] Danube",
      b: "[b] Rhine",
      c: "[c] Seine",
      d: "[d] Elbe",
      e: "[e] Paiva",
      answer: "[e] Paiva",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.7) On how many Global Forest Goals does the Global Forest Goals 2021 Report assesses the performance of countries?",
      a: "[a] Six",
      b: "[b] Ten",
      c: "[c] Twelve",
      d: "[d] Fifteen",
      e: "[e] Five",
      answer: "[a] Six",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.8) Which company has launched a first-of-its-kind $200 million Restore Fund to remove 1 million metric tons of carbon dioxide annually from the atmosphere?",
      a: "[a] Apple",
      b: "[b] Amazon",
      c: "[c] Upgrad",
      d: "[d] Byju’s",
      e: "[e] Tesla",
      answer: "[a] Apple",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.9) Who has become the first Indian-American to be appointed as the US' Associate Attorney General?",
      a: "[a] Vanita Gupta",
      b: "[b] Premjeet Singh",
      c: "[c] Rajat Pal",
      d: "[d] Sumit Verma",
      e: "[e] Sachin Vashisth",
      answer: "[a] Vanita Gupta",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.10) Who has won the singles at the Porsche Tennis Grand Prix 2021?",
      a: "[a] Naomi Osaka",
      b: "[b] Simona Halep",
      c: "[c] Sofia Kenin",
      d: "[d] Ashleigh Barty",
      e: "[e] Aryna Sabalenka",
      answer: "[d] Ashleigh Barty",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.1) Which state has signed an MoU with Microsoft for imparting digital skills to 1.62 lakh students and unemployed youth across 300 plus colleges and skill development centres in the state?",
      a: "[a] Maharashtra",
      b: "[b] Gujarat",
      c: "[c] West Bengal",
      d: "[d] Andhra Pradesh",
      e: "[e] Tamil Nadu",
      answer: "[d] Andhra Pradesh",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.2) Which state’s Urja Vikas Nigam has signed a first of its kind power purchase agreement with Coal India?",
      a: "[a] Arunachal Pradesh",
      b: "[b] Gujarat",
      c: "[c] Chhattisgarh",
      d: "[d] West Bengal",
      e: "[e] Odisha",
      answer: "[b] Gujarat",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.3) Singapore Indian Chamber of Commerce and Industry (SICCI) and Start-up Incubation and Innovation Centre (SIIC) to provide opportunities to tech-based start-ups for a circular economy and an entrepreneurial ecosystem. Both organisations have launched “SICCI-SIIC INNOVATION LAUNCHPAD” challenge for startups. Start-up Incubation and Innovation Centre is located at which IIT?",
      a: "[a] IIT-Kanpur",
      b: "[b] IIT- Kharagpur",
      c: "[c] IIT- Bombay",
      d: "[d] IIT- Madras",
      e: "[e] IIT-Ropar",
      answer: "[a] IIT-Kanpur",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.4) Which IIT has Ministry of Housing & Urban Affairs signed an MoU to set up an Accelerator Centre for Research & Development at the institute?",
      a: "[a] IIT- Dharwad",
      b: "[b] IIT- Goa",
      c: "[c] IIT- Jammu",
      d: "[d] IIT-Kharagpur",
      e: "[e] IIT- Dhanbad",
      answer: "[d] IIT-Kharagpur",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.5) Which has become the second African country to eliminate Trachoma?",
      a: "[a] Ghana",
      b: "[b] Kenya",
      c: "[c] Tanzania",
      d: "[d] Gambia",
      e: "[e] Morocco",
      answer: "[d] Gambia",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.6) When is International Day of Multilateralism and Diplomacy for Peace observed?",
      a: "[a] April 24",
      b: "[b] April 5",
      c: "[c] April 29",
      d: "[d] April 13",
      e: "[e] April 11",
      answer: "[a] April 24",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.7) Who has won the League Cup 2021 (English football tournament)?",
      a: "[a] Arsenal",
      b: "[b] Chelsea",
      c: "[c] Barcelona",
      d: "[d] Atletico Madrid",
      e: "[e] Manchester City",
      answer: "[e] Manchester City",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.8) Where will the ITTF World Table Tennis Championships be held?",
      a: "[a] Brasília, Brazil",
      b: "[b] Sucre, Bolivia",
      c: "[c] Houston, USA",
      d: "[d] Santiago, Chile",
      e: "[e] Bogotá, Colombia",
      answer: "[c] Houston, USA",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.9) Where are the Maui Dolphins found?",
      a: "[a] Philippines",
      b: "[b] Singapore",
      c: "[c] Myanmar",
      d: "[d] Australia",
      e: "[e] New Zealand",
      answer: "[e] New Zealand",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.10) Who is the author of “Living Mountain” book?",
      a: "[a] Amitav Ghosh",
      b: "[b] Hari Kunzru",
      c: "[c] Ashok K. Banker",
      d: "[d] Devdutt Pattanaik",
      e: "[e] Ashwin Sanghi",
      answer: "[a] Amitav Ghosh",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.1) Which IIT has created India’s first 3D printed house?",
      a: "[a] IIT- Delhi",
      b: "[b] IIT- Bombay",
      c: "[c] IIT- Kharagpur",
      d: "[d] IIT- Ropar",
      e: "[e] IIT-Madras",
      answer: "[e] IIT-Madras",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.2) How much is India’s target for the Indian chemicals industry by 2025?",
      a: "[a] $304 billion",
      b: "[b] $178 billion",
      c: "[c] $145 billion",
      d: "[d] $220 billion",
      e: "[e] $180 billion",
      answer: "[a] $304 billion",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.3) Which edition of Varuna exercise was conducted by India and France in 2021?",
      a: "[a] 21st",
      b: "[b] 35th",
      c: "[c] 19th",
      d: "[d] 11th",
      e: "[e] 10th",
      answer: "[c] 19th",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.4) Which country does Tianhe space station module belong to?",
      a: "[a] Japan",
      b: "[b] South Korea",
      c: "[c] Vietnam",
      d: "[d] China",
      e: "[e] Philippines",
      answer: "[d] China",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.5) What is the corpus of Mastercard Impact Fund launched by Mastercard to address the COVID-19 crisis in India?",
      a: "[a] USD 2 million",
      b: "[b] USD 10 million",
      c: "[c] USD 60 million",
      d: "[d] USD 50 million",
      e: "[e] USD 30 million",
      answer: "[b] USD 10 million",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.6) Who has been designated as the Finance Secretary?",
      a: "[a] Kaptan Singh",
      b: "[b] Arvind Singh",
      c: "[c] R. K. Dhawan",
      d: "[d] Sanjay Pandey",
      e: "[e] T V Somanathan",
      answer: "[e] T V Somanathan",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.7) When is the World Day for Safety and Health at Work observed?",
      a: "[a] April 10",
      b: "[b] April 21",
      c: "[c] April 28",
      d: "[d] April 12",
      e: "[e] April 11",
      answer: "[c] April 28",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.8) Who has been chosen as the first Indian and Asian woman for the 2021 'WILD Innovator Award'?",
      a: "[a] Sarojini Shekhar",
      b: "[b] Neha Baghel",
      c: "[c] Krithi K Karanth",
      d: "[d] Priyanka Mishra",
      e: "[e] Reshma Bhushan",
      answer: "[c] Krithi K Karanth",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.9) Which of the following Indian company has entered TIME’s 100 Most Influential Companies 2021 list?",
      a: "[a] Byju’s",
      b: "[b] Razorpay",
      c: "[c] Jio Platform",
      d: "[d] Both A and B",
      e: "[e] Both A and C",
      answer: "[e] Both A and C",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.10) With which field is Manoj Das related to?",
      a: "[a] Badminton player",
      b: "[b] Author",
      c: "[c] Singer",
      d: "[d] Sitarist",
      e: "[e] Environment Conservationist",
      answer: "[b] Author",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.1) On which aircraft has the 5th generation Python-5 Air-to-Air Missile been equipped?",
      a: "[a] Tejas",
      b: "[b] Mirage 2000",
      c: "[c] MiG-29",
      d: "[d] Boeing 737",
      e: "[e] Ilyushin Il-76",
      answer: "[a] Tejas",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.2) With which country has India signed an MoU for Customs Cooperation and Mutual Administrative Assistance in Customs Matters?",
      a: "[a] UK",
      b: "[b] USA",
      c: "[c] France",
      d: "[d] Germany",
      e: "[e] Japan",
      answer: "[a] UK",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.3) Blue Nature Alliance aims to conserve at least ___ percent of the world’s ocean by 2030?",
      a: "[a] 40%",
      b: "[b] 50%",
      c: "[c] 20%",
      d: "[d] 30%",
      e: "[e] 15%",
      answer: "[d] 30%",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.4) NEO-01 is the robot prototype for clean the orbit off the debris left behind by other spacecraft. Which country does the prototype belong to?",
      a: "[a] Germany",
      b: "[b] France",
      c: "[c] China",
      d: "[d] Russia",
      e: "[e] Finland",
      answer: "[c] China",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.5) What is India’s rank in the Chandler Good Government Index 2021?",
      a: "[a] 75th",
      b: "[b] 49th",
      c: "[c] 68th",
      d: "[d] 83rd",
      e: "[e] 91st",
      answer: "[b] 49th",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.6) Which company has launched India’s first Wealth Community based on video?",
      a: "[a] Google Pay",
      b: "[b] BHIM Axis Pay",
      c: "[c] Mobikwik",
      d: "[d] Paytm",
      e: "[e] PhonePe",
      answer: "[d] Paytm",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.7) What is India’s GDP growth rate for FY22 by Asian Development Outlook?",
      a: "[a] 11%",
      b: "[b] 7.7%",
      c: "[c] 8%",
      d: "[d] 9.5%",
      e: "[e] 10.3%",
      answer: "[a] 11%",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.8) Where is the Khelo India State Centre of Excellence (KISCEs) for rowing located?",
      a: "[a] Chandigarh",
      b: "[b] Ranakpur",
      c: "[c] Kausani",
      d: "[d] Patnitop",
      e: "[e] Srinagar",
      answer: "[e] Srinagar",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.9) Recently, Prime Minister Narendra Modi condoled the demise of Dadudan Gadhvi. Which field did he belong to?",
      a: "[a] Literature",
      b: "[b] Sports",
      c: "[c] Politics",
      d: "[d] Environmentalist",
      e: "[e] Orator",
      answer: "[a] Literature",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.10) Non-deposit taking NBFCs with asset size below ___ have the option to not follow the 'Guidelines for Appointment of Statutory Central Auditors / Statutory Auditors of Commercial Banks (excluding RRBs), UCBs and NBFCs (including HFCs)'?",
      a: "[a] ₹1,500 crore",
      b: "[b] ₹1,000 crore",
      c: "[c] ₹2,500 crore",
      d: "[d] ₹2,000 crore",
      e: "[e] ₹500 crore",
      answer: "[b] ₹1,000 crore",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.1) Where has India's first Floating Storage and Regasification Unit (FSRU) of LNG arrived from Singapore?",
      a: "[a] Kerala",
      b: "[b] Gujarat",
      c: "[c] Andhra Pradesh",
      d: "[c] Andhra Pradesh",
      e: "[e] Maharashtra",
      answer: "[e] Maharashtra",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.2) With which company has Indian Army partnered for Ladakh Ignited Minds: A Centre of Excellence and Wellness project to provide better educational opportunities for Ladakhi students?",
      a: "[a] National Thermal Power Corporation",
      b: "[b] Hindustan Petroleum Corporation Limited",
      c: "[c] Coal India Limited",
      d: "[d] Bharat Heavy Electricals Limited",
      e: "[e] Steel Authority of India Limited",
      answer: "[b] Hindustan Petroleum Corporation Limited",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.3) How much fund will be provided to the youth to recover from the Covid-19 pandemic under the UN “Global Youth Mobilization Local Solutions” campaign?",
      a: "[a] $5 million",
      b: "[b] $3 million",
      c: "[c] $4 million",
      d: "[d] $2 million",
      e: "[e] $1 million",
      answer: "[d] $2 million",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.4) Zhurong is the first Mars rover of which country?",
      a: "[a] China",
      b: "[b] Russia",
      c: "[c] Philippines",
      d: "[d] Japan",
      e: "[e] Singapore",
      answer: "[a] China",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.5) Which country has partnered with Microsoft to build the world’s most powerful supercomputer to forecast weather and climate-change?",
      a: "[a] Israel",
      b: "[b] UK",
      c: "[c] Japan",
      d: "[d] Singapore",
      e: "[e] US",
      answer: "[b] UK",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.6) According to Stockholm International Peace Research Institute’s (SIPRI) “Trends In World Military Expenditure, 2020” report, India accounts for ___ percent of world’s military expenditure?",
      a: "[a] 8.9%",
      b: "[b] 3.7%",
      c: "[c] 4.5%",
      d: "[d] 1.5%",
      e: "[e] 10.3%",
      answer: "[b] 3.7%",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.7) What is the prescribed tenure for MD and CEO of banks as per the new guidelines of RBI?",
      a: "[a] 15 years",
      b: "[b] 10 years",
      c: "[c] 12 years",
      d: "[d] 5 years",
      e: "[e] 20 years",
      answer: "[a] 15 years",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.8) Who has been appointed as the new MD and CEO of National Commodity and Derivatives Exchange Ltd?",
      a: "[a] Sharad Goklani",
      b: "[b] Matam Venkata Rao",
      c: "[c] Pramod Chandra Mody",
      d: "[d] Arun Raste",
      e: "",
      answer: "[d] Arun Raste",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.9) How many countries were supported by the E-2020 campaign of WHO for the elimination of malaria?",
      a: "[a] 21",
      b: "[b] 25",
      c: "[c] 32",
      d: "[d] 15",
      e: "[e] 10",
      answer: "[a] 21",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.10) Which picture has received the Best Picture award at the Oscars 2021?",
      a: "[a] The Father",
      b: "[b] Nomadland",
      c: "[c] Another Round",
      d: "[d] Judas and the Black Messiah",
      e: "[e] A Shaun the Sheep",
      answer: "[b] Nomadland",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.1) Which is India’s first city to have a cycling policy?",
      a: "[a] Pune",
      b: "[b] Delhi",
      c: "[c] Mumbai",
      d: "[d] Chandigarh",
      e: "[e] Puducherry",
      answer: "[d] Chandigarh",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.2) What is the target of mustard cultivation set up by Ministry of Agriculture and Family Welfare for 2025-26?",
      a: "[a] 20 million tonnes",
      b: "[b] 19 million tonnes",
      c: "[c] 30 million tonnes",
      d: "[d] 17 million tonnes",
      e: "[e] 29 million tonnes",
      answer: "[d] 17 million tonnes",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.3) Where will the 6th Global Forum on TB Vaccine be held?",
      a: "[a] Bern, Switzerland",
      b: "[b] Toulouse, France",
      c: "[c] San Marino",
      d: "[d] Warsaw, Poland",
      e: "[e] Kyiv, Ukraine",
      answer: "[b] Toulouse, France",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.4) Who among the following will be representing India at the World Cities Culture Forum 2021?",
      a: "[a] Sarbananda Sonowal",
      b: "[b] Pramod Sawant",
      c: "[c] Vijay Rupani",
      d: "[d] Arvind Kejriwal",
      e: "[e] Jai Ram Thakur",
      answer: "[d] Arvind Kejriwal",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.5) Which of the following mission has been sent by NASA to study the interstellar particles in the heliosphere?",
      a: "[a] ARCTAS",
      b: "[b] CHAMP",
      c: "[c] BARREL",
      d: "[d] SHIELDS",
      e: "[e] ATTREX",
      answer: "[d] SHIELDS",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.6) Which university has topped in the The Times Higher Education (THE) Impact Rankings 2021?",
      a: "[a] University of Manchester",
      b: "[b] RMIT University",
      c: "[c] University of Sydney",
      d: "[d] Massachusetts Institute of Technology",
      e: "[e] University of Cambridge",
      answer: "[a] University of Manchester",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.7) Which company has executed world’s first blockchain-enabled paperless trade transaction in the steel industry?",
      a: "[a] ArcelorMittal",
      b: "[b] China Baowu Group",
      c: "[c] Nippon Steel Corporation",
      d: "[d] HBIS Group",
      e: "[e] Tata Steel",
      answer: "[e] Tata Steel",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.8) Who has been chosen as the external auditor of the Organisation for the Prohibition of Chemical Weapons from India?",
      a: "[a] Riva Ganguly Das",
      b: "[b] GC Murmu",
      c: "[c] Satwant Khanalia",
      d: "[d] Harsh Vardhan Shringla",
      e: "[e] Rahul Chhabra",
      answer: "[b] GC Murmu",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.9) Who has been appointed as the chairperson of NASSCOM for 2021-22?",
      a: "[a] Akhilesh Mishra",
      b: "[b] Reenat Sandhu",
      c: "[c] Nagma M. Mallick",
      d: "[d] Rekha M. Menon",
      e: "[e] Prabhat Kumar",
      answer: "[d] Rekha M. Menon",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.10) When is the International Girls in ICT (Information & Communications Technology) Day observed?",
      a: "[a] April 10",
      b: "[b] April 16",
      c: "[c] April 22",
      d: "[d] April 18",
      e: "[e] April 13",
      answer: "[c] April 22",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.1) Which state has signed an MoU with Microsoft for imparting digital skills to 1.62 lakh students and unemployed youth across 300 plus colleges and skill development centres in the state?",
      a: "[a] Maharashtra",
      b: "[b] Gujarat",
      c: "[c] West Bengal",
      d: "[d] Andhra Pradesh",
      e: "[e] Tamil Nadu",
      answer: "[d] Andhra Pradesh",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.2) Which state’s Urja Vikas Nigam has signed a first of its kind power purchase agreement with Coal India?",
      a: "[a] Arunachal Pradesh",
      b: "[b] Gujarat",
      c: "[c] Chhattisgarh",
      d: "[d] West Bengal",
      e: "[e] Odisha",
      answer: "[b] Gujarat",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.3) Singapore Indian Chamber of Commerce and Industry (SICCI) and Start-up Incubation and Innovation Centre (SIIC) to provide opportunities to tech-based start-ups for a circular economy and an entrepreneurial ecosystem. Both organisations have launched “SICCI-SIIC INNOVATION LAUNCHPAD” challenge for startups. Start-up Incubation and Innovation Centre is located at which IIT?",
      a: "[a] IIT-Kanpur",
      b: "[b] IIT- Kharagpur",
      c: "[c] IIT- Bombay",
      d: "[d] IIT- Madras",
      e: "[e] IIT-Ropar",
      answer: "[a] IIT-Kanpur",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.4) Which IIT has Ministry of Housing & Urban Affairs signed an MoU to set up an Accelerator Centre for Research & Development at the institute?",
      a: "[a] IIT- Dharwad",
      b: "[b] IIT- Goa",
      c: "[c] IIT- Jammu",
      d: "[d] IIT-Kharagpur",
      e: "[e] IIT- Dhanbad",
      answer: "[d] IIT-Kharagpur",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.5) Which has become the second African country to eliminate Trachoma?",
      a: "[a] Ghana",
      b: "[b] Kenya",
      c: "[c] Tanzania",
      d: "[d] Gambia",
      e: "[e] Morocco",
      answer: "[d] Gambia",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.6) When is International Day of Multilateralism and Diplomacy for Peace observed?",
      a: "[a] April 24",
      b: "[b] April 5",
      c: "[c] April 29",
      d: "[d] April 13",
      e: "[e] April 11",
      answer: "[a] April 24",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.7) Who has won the League Cup 2021 (English football tournament)?",
      a: "[a] Arsenal",
      b: "[b] Chelsea",
      c: "[c] Barcelona",
      d: "[d] Atletico Madrid",
      e: "[e] Manchester City",
      answer: "[e] Manchester City",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.8) Where will the ITTF World Table Tennis Championships be held?",
      a: "[a] Brasília, Brazil",
      b: "[b] Sucre, Bolivia",
      c: "[c] Houston, USA",
      d: "[d] Santiago, Chile",
      e: "[e] Bogotá, Colombia",
      answer: "[c] Houston, USA",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.9) Where are the Maui Dolphins found?",
      a: "[a] Philippines",
      b: "[b] Singapore",
      c: "[c] Myanmar",
      d: "[d] Australia",
      e: "[e] New Zealand",
      answer: "[e] New Zealand",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.10) Who is the author of “Living Mountain” book?",
      a: "[a] Amitav Ghosh",
      b: "[b] Hari Kunzru",
      c: "[c] Ashok K. Banker",
      d: "[d] Devdutt Pattanaik",
      e: "[e] Ashwin Sanghi",
      answer: "[a] Amitav Ghosh",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.1) Who has become the first Indian woman to scale Mt Annapurna, the 10th highest mountain peak in the world?",
      a: "[a] Rakhi Shekhar",
      b: "[b] Anita Verma",
      c: "[c] Parul Baghel",
      d: "[d] Priyanka Mohite",
      e: "[e] Chanchal Sharma",
      answer: "[d] Priyanka Mohite",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.2) Which state has launched HARIHAR policy for providing employment, educational and financial benefits to abandoned and surrendered children?",
      a: "[a] Haryana",
      b: "[b] Chhattisgarh",
      c: "[c] Jharkhand",
      d: "[d] West Bengal",
      e: "[e] Tripura",
      answer: "[a] Haryana",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.3) What is the total foodgrain production estimate for 2020-21 as per the second advance estimates of production of principal crops by the Ministry of Agriculture & Farmers Welfare?",
      a: "[a] 120.32 million tonnes",
      b: "[b] 109.24 million tonnes",
      c: "[c] 49.36 million tonnes",
      d: "[d] 397.66 million tonnes",
      e: "[e] 303.34 million tonnes",
      answer: "[e] 303.34 million tonnes",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.4) Where did the Indian Army conducted ‘ARMEX-21’ exercise?",
      a: "[a] Ladakh",
      b: "[b] Uttarakhand",
      c: "[c] Himachal Pradesh",
      d: "[d] Both A and B",
      e: "[e] Both B and C",
      answer: "[d] Both A and B",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.5) Which city is the UNESCO’s World Book Capital for the 2021?",
      a: "[a] San Diego",
      b: "[b] Seattle",
      c: "[c] Boston",
      d: "[d] Tbilisi",
      e: "[e] Chicago",
      answer: "[d] Tbilisi",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.6) Which bank has collaborated with Google Pay and VISA to enable secured tokenisation on its credit cards?",
      a: "[a] Bank of Baroda",
      b: "[b] HSBC India",
      c: "[c] Bank of Maharashtra",
      d: "[d] Canara Bank",
      e: "[e] Bank of India",
      answer: "[b] HSBC India",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.7) Who has been appointed as the part-time chairman of HDFC Bank?",
      a: "[a] Atanu Chakraborty",
      b: "[b] Sharad Goklani",
      c: "[c] Matam Venkata Rao",
      d: "[d] Arun Kumar Singh",
      e: "[e] Pramod Chandra Mody",
      answer: "[a] Atanu Chakraborty",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.8) Who has won the ‘Nelson Mandela World Humanitarian Award 2021’?",
      a: "[a] Nitesh Kumar Mishra",
      b: "[b] Gyan Bhushan",
      c: "[c] Madan Lal",
      d: "[d] Rumana Sinha Sehgal",
      e: "[e] Bibhuti Bhushana Dash",
      answer: "[d] Rumana Sinha Sehgal",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.9) Which bank has signed an MOU with The Chennai Angles (angel investment group) to finance startups?",
      a: "[a] Indian Overseas Bank",
      b: "[b] Indian Bank",
      c: "[c] State Bank of India",
      d: "[d] UCO Bank",
      e: "[e] Union Bank of India",
      answer: "[b] Indian Bank",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.10) With which company has Mastercard partnered to launch ConQR - a Mastercard QR on Card solution - a payment solution for cardholders?",
      a: "[a] SREI Infrastructure Finance Limited",
      b: "[b] BOB Financial Solutions Limited",
      c: "[c] Religare Finvest Limited",
      d: "[d] PTC India Financial Services Limited",
      e: "[e] JM Financial Credit Solutions Limited",
      answer: "[b] BOB Financial Solutions Limited",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.1) In how many states has the govt launched the Unique Land Parcel Identification Number (ULPIN) scheme?",
      a: "[a] 15",
      b: "[b] 22",
      c: "[c] 35",
      d: "[d] 18",
      e: "[e] 10",
      answer: "[e] 10",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.2) How many digits will the Unique Land Parcel Identification Number – “the Aadhaar for land” – contain?",
      a: "[a] Twelve",
      b: "[b] Fourteen",
      c: "[c] Ten",
      d: "[d] Fifteen",
      e: "[e] Seven",
      answer: "[b] Fourteen",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.3) Who heads the Expert Committee for Factories and Dock Works?",
      a: "[a] Pankaj Kumar Devrani",
      b: "[b] Subrata Halder",
      c: "[c] R. K. Elangovan",
      d: "[d] Surendra Kumar",
      e: "[e] R. N. Bharti",
      answer: "[c] R. K. Elangovan",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.4) Who heads the Expert Committees on Fire Safety formed by Ministry of Labour?",
      a: "[a] Ram Lakhan Gupta",
      b: "[b] D. K. Shami",
      c: "[c] Shyam Sundar Verma",
      d: "[d] OM Prakash",
      e: "[e] Uttank Joshi",
      answer: "[b] D. K. Shami",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.5) Recently formed Expert Committees for the Building & Other Construction Works will review the Building and Other Construction Workers (Regulation of Employment and Conditions of Service) Central Rules. When were these ruled implemented?",
      a: "[a] 1889",
      b: "[b] 1980",
      c: "[c] 1998",
      d: "[d] 2001",
      e: "[e] 1999",
      answer: "[c] 1998",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.6) Which country chaired the 17th Bay of Bengal Initiative for Multi-Sectoral Technical and Economic Cooperation (BIMSTEC) Ministerial Meeting?",
      a: "[a] Bangladesh",
      b: "[b] Thailand",
      c: "[c] India",
      d: "[d] Sri Lanka",
      e: "[e] Myanmar",
      answer: "[d] Sri Lanka",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.7) Which country is hosting the BIMSTEC Centre for Weather and Climate?",
      a: "[a] Bangladesh",
      b: "[b] Thailand",
      c: "[c] India",
      d: "[d] Sri Lanka",
      e: "[e] Myanmar",
      answer: "[c] India",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.8) According to the “Prime Time for Real Time” report, more than 70.3 billion real-time payments transactions were processed globally in 2020, which highlights a surge of 41% as compared to the previous year. Worldwide the mobile wallet adoption rose to a historic high of 46% in 2020, up from 40.6% in 2019 and 18.9% in 2018. As far as India is concerned, the report exuberates confidence in the growth of real time payments transactions which, according to the report, are expected to account for 50% of the overall electronic transactions by 2024. Which of the following organizations has released this report?",
      a: "[a] Niti Aayog",
      b: "[b] Rocky Mountain Institute",
      c: "[c] Grant Thornton",
      d: "[d] ACI Worldwide",
      e: "[e] Brookings Institution",
      answer: "[d] ACI Worldwide",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.9) How much is the paid share capital of NPCI Bharat BillPay Ltd?",
      a: "[a] Rs 25 lakh",
      b: "[b] Rs 50 lakh",
      c: "[c] Rs 20 lakh",
      d: "[d] Rs 5 lakh",
      e: "[e] Rs 10 lakh",
      answer: "[d] Rs 5 lakh",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.10) Who has been appointed as the chairperson of the Public Enterprises Selection Board?",
      a: "[a] Rajesh Talwar",
      b: "[b] Mallika Srinivasan",
      c: "[c] Bharti Kashyap Sharma",
      d: "[d] Tuntuni Chowdhry",
      e: "[e] R. K. Bhati",
      answer: "[b] Mallika Srinivasan",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.11) With which company has UK-based CDC Group company partnered to conduct its first-ever pooled bond issuance (PBI) transaction in India worth Rs 320 crore?",
      a: "[a] Magma Fincorp Limited",
      b: "[b] SREI Infrastructure Finance Limited",
      c: "[c] PTC India Financial Services Limited",
      d: "[d] SBI DFHI Limited",
      e: "[e] Northern Arc Capital",
      answer: "[e] Northern Arc Capital",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.12) Who has been appointed as the brand ambassador of the Digit Insurance?",
      a: "[a] Harbhajan Singh",
      b: "[b] Geeta Basra",
      c: "[c] Mahendra Singh Dhoni",
      d: "[d] Virat Kohli",
      e: "[e] Yuvraj Singh",
      answer: "[c] Bratislava",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.13) What is the capital of Slovakia?",
      a: "[a] Tirana",
      b: "[b] Andorra la Vella",
      c: "[c] Bratislava",
      d: "[d] Yerevan",
      e: "[e] Yaounde",
      answer: "[a] Mukhmeet S. Bhatia",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.14) Who has been appointed as the new director general of Employees State Insurance Corporation?",
      a: "[a] Mukhmeet S. Bhatia",
      b: "[b] Bidisha Sengupta",
      c: "[c] Pranav Prakash",
      d: "[d] Susheela Tigga",
      e: "[e] Harpal Singh",
      answer: "[d] Rajnikanth",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.15) Who will be receiving the 51st edition of Dadasaheb Phalke award for the year 2020?",
      a: "[a] Dilip Kumar",
      b: "[b] Mumtaz Begum",
      c: "[c] Late Rishi Kapoor",
      d: "[d] Rajnikanth",
      e: "[e] Amitabh Bachchan",
      answer: "[a] Carmen Maria Machado",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.16) Who is the author of 'In The Dream House: A Memoir'?",
      a: "[a] Carmen Maria Machado",
      b: "[b] Armando Lucas Correa",
      c: "[c] Martha McPhee",
      d: "[d] Megan Miranda",
      e: "[e] Helen Phillips",
      answer: "[c] Mohan Kanda",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.17) Who is the author of Agriculture in India: Contemporary Challenges - in the Context of Doubling Farmers Income book?",
      a: "[a] Niraj Sharan",
      b: "[b] Kirti Nandkishor Gaikwad",
      c: "[c] Mohan Kanda",
      d: "[d] Sharad Saxena",
      e: "[e] Surendra Prasad",
      answer: "[d] April 2",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.18) When is World Autism Awareness Day celebrated?",
      a: "[a] April 20",
      b: "[b] April 11",
      c: "[c] April 12",
      d: "[d] April 2",
      e: "[e] April 3",
      answer: "[e] Kshama Fernandes",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.19) Who is the CEO of Northern Arc Capital?",
      a: "[a] Peter Simpson",
      b: "[b] Andrew Haines",
      c: "[c] Craig Donaldson",
      d: "[d] Juergen Maier",
      e: "[e] Kshama Fernandes",
      answer: "[a] Dilip Asbe",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.1) Which IIT has successfully commercialised COVIRAP - the novel diagnostic technology?",
      a: "[a] IIT-Kharagpur",
      b: "[b] IIT-Hyderabad",
      c: "[c] IIT-Gandhinagar",
      d: "[d] IIT-Delhi",
      e: "[e] IIT-Kanpur",
      answer: "[a] IIT-Kharagpur",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.2) How much is the Agriculture Infrastructure and Development Cess on Petrol?",
      a: "[a] Rs 5 per litre",
      b: "[b] Rs 3 per litre",
      c: "[c] Rs 0.5 per litre",
      d: "[d] Rs 2.5 per litre",
      e: "[e] Rs 1 per litre",
      answer: "[d] Rs 2.5 per litre",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.3) Which has become the first state in India to have uniform civil code?",
      a: "[a] Mizoram",
      b: "[b] Sikkim",
      c: "[c] Nagaland",
      d: "[d] Tripura",
      e: "[e] Goa",
      answer: "[e] Goa",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.4) Which state has signed an MoU with World Trade Centre to provide a conclusive environment in the state for bringing investment through the new modes and operations?",
      a: "[a] Gujarat",
      b: "[b] Telangana",
      c: "[c] Odisha",
      d: "[d] Andhra Pradesh",
      e: "[e] Haryana",
      answer: "[e] Haryana",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.5) With which IIT has National Cooperative Development Corporation (NCDC) signed an MoU for collaboration in areas related to the development of cooperatives, agriculture and allied sectors for sustainable development?",
      a: "[a] IIT Patna",
      b: "[b] IIT Kharagpur",
      c: "[c] IIT Bhuvneshwar",
      d: "[d] IIT Guwahati",
      e: "[e] IIT Ropar",
      answer: "[b] IIT Kharagpur",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.6) Which has become the first country in the world to ratify the Regional Comprehensive Economic Partnership (RCEP) agreement?",
      a: "[a] Australia",
      b: "[b] South Korea",
      c: "[c] China",
      d: "[d] Japan",
      e: "[e] Singapore",
      answer: "[e] Singapore",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.7) What is the name of the instruments used by NASA to generate oxygen on Mars?",
      a: "[a] Moxie",
      b: "[b] Max",
      c: "[c] Skylab",
      d: "[d] Ingenuity",
      e: "[e] Ceres",
      answer: "[a] Moxie",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.8) Which of the following country has been recommended as the Countries of Particular Concern by U.S. Commission on International Religious Freedom (USCIRF)?",
      a: "[a] India",
      b: "[b] Russia",
      c: "[c] Vietnam",
      d: "[d] Syria",
      e: "[e] All of the Above",
      answer: "[e] All of the Above",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.9) What is the 2021 Global average score in the World Economic Forum’s Global Energy Transition Index 2021?",
      a: "[a] 59",
      b: "[b] 60",
      c: "[c] 80",
      d: "[d] 43",
      e: "[e] 72",
      answer: "[a] 59",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.10) What is India’s rank in the Global Energy Transition Index 2021?",
      a: "[a] 87",
      b: "[b] 142",
      c: "[c] 102",
      d: "[d] 98",
      e: "[e] 67",
      answer: "[a] 87",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.1) With which country’s Administrative Council for Economic Defense has Competition Commission of India signed an MoU for cooperation?",
      a: "[a] Brazil",
      b: "[b] New Papua Guinea",
      c: "[c] Vanuatu",
      d: "[d] Fiji",
      e: "[e] New Caledonia",
      answer: "[a] Brazil",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.2) According to the Global Energy Review 2021 by International Energy Agency (IEA), global carbon dioxide (CO2) emissions would rise to ___ this year?",
      a: "[a] 20 billion tonnes",
      b: "[b] 40 billion tonnes",
      c: "[c] 33 billion tonnes",
      d: "[d] 50 billion tonnes",
      e: "[e] 13 billion tonnes",
      answer: "[c] 33 billion tonnes",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.3) What is the total corpus of the RBI’s government securities acquisition programme (G-SAP) 1.0?",
      a: "[a] ₹4 trillion",
      b: "[b] ₹1 trillion",
      c: "[c] ₹2 trillion",
      d: "[d] ₹10 trillion",
      e: "[e] ₹5 trillion",
      answer: "[b] ₹1 trillion",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.4) Asian Development Bank (ADB) has partnered with Habitat for Humanity International to help microfinance institutions (MFIs) deliver housing loans to low-income families in rural and peri-urban areas of India, Bangladesh, ____ , and the _____?",
      a: "[a] Indonesia",
      b: "[b] Philippines",
      c: "[c] Malaysia",
      d: "[d] Both A and B",
      e: "[e] Both B and C",
      answer: "[d] Both A and B",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.5) Who has been appointed as the new chairman of Credit Suisse?",
      a: "[a] Warren East",
      b: "[b] Horta-Osorio",
      c: "[c] Andy Ransom",
      d: "[d] Liv Garfield",
      e: "[e] Emma Walmsley",
      answer: "[b] Horta-Osorio",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.6) Who is the MD and CEO of DCB Bank?",
      a: "[a] Karnam Sekar",
      b: "[b] Sandeep Bakhshi",
      c: "[c] V. Vaidyananthan",
      d: "[d] Murali M. Natrajan",
      e: "[e] R. Seshasayee",
      answer: "[d] Murali M. Natrajan",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.7) When is National Civil Services Day observed?",
      a: "[a] April 20",
      b: "[b] April 21",
      c: "[c] April 18",
      d: "[d] April 10",
      e: "[e] April 11",
      answer: "[b] April 21",
    },
    {
      question: "Q.8) G Venkata Subbaiah is related to which field?",
      a: "[a] Writer",
      b: "[b] Journalism",
      c: "[c] Environmentalist",
      d: "[d] Banker",
      e: "[e] Shuttler",
      answer: "[a] Writer",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.9) Where is the headquarters of Universal Postal Union (UPU)?",
      a: "[a] Helsinki",
      b: "[b] Riga",
      c: "[c] Tallinn",
      d: "[d] Berne",
      e: "[e] Warsaw",
      answer: "[d] Berne",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.10) Who among the following is known as the Father of Banking Reforms in India?",
      a: "[a] M. Narasimham",
      b: "[b] Raghuram Rajan",
      c: "[c] D. Subbarao",
      d: "[d] H. V. R. Iyengar",
      e: "[e] P. C. Bhattacharya",
      answer: "[a] M. Narasimham",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.1) NITI Aayog launched ‘Surakshit Hum Surakshit Tum Abhiyan’ in 112 aspirational districts with the collaboration of _____?",
      a: "[a] Piramal Foundation",
      b: "[b] Smile foundation",
      c: "[c] YES foundation",
      d: "[d] Ganga Social foundation",
      e: "[e] CARE India",
      answer: "[a] Piramal Foundation",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.2) NHPC Pvt limited and ______ State Power Development Corporation Ltd has formed a joint venture company, “Ratle Hydroelectric Power Corporation Limited”.",
      a: "[a] Jammu and Kashmir",
      b: "[b] Ladakh",
      c: "[c] Kerala",
      d: "[d] Assam",
      e: "[e] Uttarakhand",
      answer: "[a] Jammu and Kashmir",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.3) Consider the following statements with regards to Black Carbon- (1) Black carbon is the second most important global warming pollutant after CO­2. (2) ‘Mass absorption cross-section- MAC’ is an essential parameter used for obtaining Black Carbon mass concentrations. (3) Accurate estimation of black carbon is possible using optical instruments in the Himalayan region. (4) Accurate estimation of black carbon is not possible using optical instruments in the Himalayan region. Which statements are correct?",
      a: "[a] 1, 2 and 3",
      b: "[b] 1, 2 and 4",
      c: "[c] Only 1 and 4",
      d: "[d] Only 2 and 3",
      e: "[e] 2 and 3",
      answer: "[a] 1, 2 and 3",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.4) The Supreme Court has released the Draft Model Rules for Live-Streaming and Recording of Court Proceedings. What is not correct regarding this draft?",
      a: "[a] Live streaming proceedings are part of the right to access justice under Article 21",
      b: "[b] Swapnil Tripathi v Supreme Court of India (2018) principles are base of the model rules of the draft.",
      c: "[c] Discussion between judges and advocates will not be telecast.",
      d: "[d] Proceedings instituted under Section 376 of Indian Penal Code will not be live streamed.",
      e: "[e] All are correct",
      answer: "[e] All are correct",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.1) NITI Aayog launched ‘Surakshit Hum Surakshit Tum Abhiyan’ in 112 aspirational districts with the collaboration of _____?",
      a: "[a] Piramal Foundation",
      b: "[b] Smile foundation",
      c: "[c] YES foundation",
      d: "[d] Ganga Social foundation",
      e: "[e] CARE India",
      answer: "[a] Piramal Foundation",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.2) NHPC Pvt limited and ______ State Power Development Corporation Ltd has formed a joint venture company, “Ratle Hydroelectric Power Corporation Limited”.",
      a: "[a] Jammu and Kashmir",
      b: "[b] Ladakh",
      c: "[c] Kerala",
      d: "[d] Assam",
      e: "[e] Uttarakhand",
      answer: "[a] Jammu and Kashmir",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.3) Consider the following statements with regards to Black Carbon- (1) Black carbon is the second most important global warming pollutant after CO­2. (2) ‘Mass absorption cross-section- MAC’ is an essential parameter used for obtaining Black Carbon mass concentrations. (3) Accurate estimation of black carbon is possible using optical instruments in the Himalayan region. (4) Accurate estimation of black carbon is not possible using optical instruments in the Himalayan region. Which statements are correct?",
      a: "[a] 1, 2 and 3",
      b: "[b] 1, 2 and 4",
      c: "[c] Only 1 and 4",
      d: "[d] Only 2 and 3",
      e: "[e] 2 and 3",
      answer: "[a] 1, 2 and 3",
    },
    {
      question:
        "Q.4) The Supreme Court has released the Draft Model Rules for Live-Streaming and Recording of Court Proceedings. What is not correct regarding this draft?",
      a: "[a] Live streaming proceedings are part of the right to access justice under Article 21",
      b: "[b] Swapnil Tripathi v Supreme Court of India (2018) principles are base of the model rules of the draft.",
      c: "[c] Discussion between judges and advocates will not be telecast.",
      d: "[d] Proceedings instituted under Section 376 of Indian Penal Code will not be live streamed.",
      e: "[e] All are correct",
      answer: "[e] All are correct",
    },
  ];
  const currentSetNumber = window.location.search.replace("?", "") * 50;
  const currentSetQuestion = shuffle(
    allQ.slice(currentSetNumber - 50, currentSetNumber)
  );

  console.log(q);
  const quizContainer = document.getElementById("quiz");
  const resultsContainer = document.getElementById("results");
  const submitButton = document.getElementById("submit");
  const myQuestions = currentSetQuestion.map((q) => {
    const t = {
      question: q.question,
      correctAnswer: q.answer,
    };
    t.answer[`${q.a}`] = `${q.a}`;
    t.answer[`${q.b}`] = `${q.b}`;
    t.answer[`${q.c}`] = `${q.c}`;
    t.answer[`${q.d}`] = `${q.d}`;
    t.answer[`${q.e}`] = `${q.e}`;
    return t;
  });

  // Kick things off
  buildQuiz();

  // Event listeners
  submitButton.addEventListener("click", showResults);
})();
